<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vviddoves mite cast into the treasure-house of the prerogatiues, and prayses of our B. Lady, the immaculate, and most glorious Virgin Mary, the Mother of God. With reasons why we are to haue great confidence in her prayers. Whereunto is annexed, A prayer, for the loue of God, made in contemplation of the passion of Christ our Sauiour.</title>
            <author>A. G., fl. 1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118624</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853831</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853831</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19229</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01368)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19229)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 578:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vviddoves mite cast into the treasure-house of the prerogatiues, and prayses of our B. Lady, the immaculate, and most glorious Virgin Mary, the Mother of God. With reasons why we are to haue great confidence in her prayers. Whereunto is annexed, A prayer, for the loue of God, made in contemplation of the passion of Christ our Sauiour.</title>
                  <author>A. G., fl. 1619.</author>
                  <author>Matthew, Tobie, Sir, 1577-1655, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 199, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Published by allowance of superiours. Anno M. DC. XIX. [1619]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: A.G.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>"A prayer for the loue of God" is in verse; possibly by Sir Tobie Matthew.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Errata on  *4r.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VVIDDOVVES MITE, Caſt into the Treaſure-houſe of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues, and Prayſes of our B. Lady, the Immaculate, and moſt Glorious Virgin Mary, the Mother of God. With Reaſons why we are to haue great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in her Prayers.</p>
            <p>WHEREVNTO <hi>Is annexed, A Prayer, for the Loue of God, made in Contemplation of the Paſsion of Chriſt our Sauiour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by allowance of Superiours. ANNO M.DC.XIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:3"/>
            <head>TO MY NOBLE AND MOST DEARE FRIEND S. A.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Should haue byn moſt gladde to print your name at large, and in capitall Letters, in this front of the Dedication; vvhich might haue paſſed for ſome
<pb facs="tcp:19229:4"/>
little teſtimony of the much ſeruice, that I ovve, &amp; deſire to pay you. But inſteed of doing you ſeruice, I vvould be ſure not to do you diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: and vve are fallen into ſo miſerable tymes, as vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I might better cheape in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate you to protect ſome thiefe or outlavv, then to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize a vvorke that tends to the honour of our B. Lady. It shall therefore ſuffice that heerein vve knovv the mind of one another. And although there vvas no remedy, but I muſt needs ſpare to mention your name; yet I could not
<pb facs="tcp:19229:4"/>
thinke of fayling to addreſſe the Treatiſe to your Fauour. Both for the entiere deuotion vvhich you carry to the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Queene of Heauen (and that of the beſt kind, becauſe it leads you to as exact an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of her high Purity, as euer I haue diſcouered in any creature of your condition &amp; vocation:) &amp; beſides for that this Patterne vvas moſt due to you, to vvhome the vvhole Peece of that belongs, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may any vvay acknovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the noble Fauour of a moſt vvorthy and vvell deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Friend. I hope you
<pb facs="tcp:19229:5"/>
vvill excuſe it for his ſake by vvhome it is vvritten; nay I knovv you vvill eſteem it for her ſake of vvhome it is vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. And I hope, that both you, and I shall one day be ſo happy, vnder the patronage of this immaculate Virgin, the Mother of God, as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer, and behould that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible Glory, vvhich she obtayned by cooperating vvith Gods incomparable Grace.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Seruant, &amp; true Friend. <hi>A. G.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:5"/>
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in printing.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Page.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Line.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Fault.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Correction.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>which</cell>
                     <cell>with</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>dele</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>of degrees</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>their turnes</cell>
                     <cell>the turnes</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>and not</cell>
                     <cell>but rather.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>moſt</cell>
                     <cell>moiſt</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>43.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>is</cell>
                     <cell>were</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44.</cell>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>which</cell>
                     <cell>with</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>46.</cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>beleeue</cell>
                     <cell>to beleeue</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>46.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>with</cell>
                     <cell>which</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>62.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>were need</cell>
                     <cell>were in need</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>79.</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>ſpeach</cell>
                     <cell>her ſpeach</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>122.</cell>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>done</cell>
                     <cell>due</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>124.</cell>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>is no queſtion</cell>
                     <cell>is queſtion</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>124.</cell>
                     <cell>24.</cell>
                     <cell>plaine</cell>
                     <cell>great</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>126.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>of the</cell>
                     <cell>by the</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>133.</cell>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>comfortable</cell>
                     <cell>comfortably</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>137.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>for now</cell>
                     <cell>and now</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>143.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>miſery</cell>
                     <cell>miſtery</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>184.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>duety</cell>
                     <cell>drily</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>155.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>diſtinct</cell>
                     <cell>diſtinctiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>159.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>aſſumeth</cell>
                     <cell>aſſureth</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>tottering</cell>
                     <cell>torturing</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>184.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>thy taſt</cell>
                     <cell>the taſt</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>192.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>This not</cell>
                     <cell>T'is not</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>195.</cell>
                     <cell>24.</cell>
                     <cell>protection</cell>
                     <cell>proiection</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19229:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE WIDDOWES MITE. CAST INTO THE TREASVRE-HOVSE OF OVR <hi>B. LADYES</hi> PRAYSES. With reaſons why we are to haue great confidence in her Prayers.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE was neuer fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d within the compaſſe of Morality a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Receipt and Secret, then that of <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> towardes the ſoftning &amp; ſweetning of all the miſeryes of this life. <hi>Friendſhip</hi> it is which doubleth our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19229:7"/>
it diuideth our cares, it locketh vp our ſecrets, it reuengeth our wrongs, and it maketh a large and liberall contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuccour towardes the reliefe of all our neceſſityes. I ſpeake not this of the thing which ſome miſcall by the name of <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> and which indeed is no more, then a meere acquaintance, or familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of conuerſation; though the world be growne to the conceipt of taking ſuch froath as this, for the quinteſſence which I heer commend: But I meane that moſt faythfull and inuiolable <hi>Friendſhip</hi> which mingleth or confoundeth fortunes, and vniteth minds, and which accompteth it for one of the greateſt hart ſoares it hath that it cannot euer reach out the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hand.</p>
               <p>And yet euen this trueſt <hi>Friendſhip</hi> (which being all that I haue ſayd) is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect both to imperfection &amp; deſtruction; for ſometymes it is changed by ficklenes, ſometymes it is vnſtitcht by abſence, ſometims it is torn in ſunder by vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes, at leaſt it is ſure to dye when they dye that did profeſſe it; and in fine, it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19229:7"/>
euer carryeth ſuch a teſtimony, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription in the forhead of it, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to point men out to ſomewhat els, aſſuring them that it cannot poſſibly be complete, becauſe all the parties to this contract are no better then ſinnefull and mortall creatures.</p>
               <p>One help there is, whereby we may feed vpon this ſweet bitt, without being troubled and tyred with gnawing vpon ſuch bones as theſe, &amp; it is by tranſlating our affection from theſe inferiour obiects to thoſe other of Saints and Angells, in whome there liueth a faculty of correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponding with vs much more nobly, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with an impoſſibility of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the true lawes of <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> which conſiſt in the entire communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things, and hath for ſpurs an extreme ardour of affection, &amp; for bridle an impuiſſance to offend in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
               <p>A patterne or proofe heerof may be taken from thoſe extaticall wiſhes of the Patriarch <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who did ſo thirſt after the eternall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19229:8"/>
happynes of their brethren, as that they ſeemed content to lay aſide the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and care of their owne. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f whileſt they were yet encumbred with the heauy cloaths of fleſh and bloud, they could ſoare ſo high into that ſpher of fire; how much more eminent are they now in this kind, togeather with all thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther celeſtiall ſpirits, ſince now they are freed from all impediments, &amp; ſtand en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying, &amp; feeding face to face, vpon the eſſence of God, which is the fountayne of <hi>Loue</hi> it ſelfe, into which by him they are transformed?</p>
               <p>We are alſo taught by holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with what zeale the holy Angels do behould, &amp; protect their ſeuerall charges heere on earth.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.</note> The Angell Guardian of <hi>Iacob,</hi> was a Champion that defended &amp; drew him out of all inconueniences. The Angel <hi>Raphael</hi> mentioned in the book of <hi>Tobias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tob.</hi> 11.</note> was both a Phiſitian in reſtoring his ſight, and a ſollicitour, or Maiſter of requeſts in preferring his ſuites, to the throne of Almighty God. Our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe hath inferred,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.</note> that if we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19229:8"/>
ſcandalize any of his little ones, their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Angells (who ſee the face of God) will reſent their wrongs. And (which yet may ſeem more ſtrang) the Angel to whoſe care the <hi>Medes</hi> were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.</note> did contradict and oppoſe to that other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> in the quarrells and combats which their people had with one another; to ſhew vs that they do not only watch ouer our ſoules, but euen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our fortunes and bodyes alſo, with all which dependeth thereupon, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our good.</p>
               <p>This care and loue of thoſe happy ſoules and ſpirits, towards the poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this world, proceedeth from the knowledge they haue of the bounty which his diuine Maieſty hath vſed in beſtowing parts of his owne perfection, and in deſigning that vnſpeakable glory which he hath prepared for vs; ſo that in their louing of vs, and cooperating to our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their aſſiſtance, they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme an act of reuerence, and homage to our common Creatour. And therfore if the Angells and other Saints deſire and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19229:9"/>
procure our happines, if they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of our affliction, if they interpoſe for vs the merits of Chriſts death and paſſion in the degree of one, there can be no queſtion amongſt Chriſtians (if indeed they be ſo) but that the Queene of Saints and Angels, the ſacred and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Virgin, the immaculate and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Mother of God, doth performe to vs all theſe things (with infinite others which through our baſenes and blindnes we cannot thinke of:) I ſay not in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of one, but in the degree of ſo many millions of degrees as ſhe exceedeth all the Angells and Saints of Heauen in the perfection and height of the knowledge and loue of God.</p>
               <p>One particuler reaſon of her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable tendernes towards vs all (to omit many others) may be the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Chriſt our Lords humanity, with he tooke wholy of her, &amp; which he ſpent wholy vpon vs; beſides that vpon the Croſſe, he reſigned her as it were, to be the Mother of all mankind, whereof heereafter I ſhall haue occaſion to make
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19229:9"/>
further mention. Now, as the vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able loue of God which he inſpired her hart withall, and wherewith ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſhe cooperated, maketh God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakably to loue and delight in her: ſo it is reaſon, that for her loue to vs, we procure to correſpond in all ſuch deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; reuerence to her who is ſo gracious in the ſight of God, and ſo well deſeruing of vs, as may be affoarded to the moſt incomparably ſublime Creature, of a meer creature, that euer was, &amp; the moſt abundant, &amp; deere benefactour of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind that can be thought of vnder God.</p>
               <p>There is not in this world ſo great a Monarch, to whome if we had obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and meant to make any retribution we might not impart ſomewhat which might concerne him in a ſubſtantiall and ſolid manner. For a very wealthy man might make him ſomewhat the richer, a valiant man might make his dominions the larger, a wiſe man might make his gouernement the happyer, a skillful man might make his health the firmer, and a confident faythfull man might chance
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19229:10"/>
to make his life the ſafer. But with the Saints of heauen, it is not ſo; for al they, and eſpecially this Queene of Heauen, hath ſuch a fullnes of all that, whereof they are capable, as excludeth the poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of mankind from giuing any thing to them, and much leſſe to her, which may increaſe her happynes in any thing that inwardly concerneth her; but whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we can offer, is extrinſecal vnto her, as namely Honour, whereof ſhe is only capable at our hands.</p>
               <p>The expreſſion of this Honour may be made by diuers wayes: by prayſing her, by praying vnto her, by imitating in ſome ſmall meaſure of her admirable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, &amp; by carrying in our harts a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall tendernes of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towards her.</p>
               <p>By this tyme, if the Reader be a Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſt, he beginneth to ſhrincke, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth to be excuſed, he reuerenceth (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) the Mother of God as he ought, if you will beleeue him, but he would faine be thought a zealous preſeruer of Gods honour; and holdeth that the termes we vſe in profeſſing our deuotion to her,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19229:10"/>
with the cuſtome which we haue in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting to her our prayers is to carry our ſelues idly, if not impiouſly: and he will needs take vpon him to ground himſelfe vpon holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>It is ſtrang to ſee how theſe yong Prentices will needs be Merchant-ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers in the art of vnderſtanding that diuin booke; to the deep ſea wherof they lanch out in the ſhallow Cock-boats of their owne conceipts, and thinke they are ſailing into ſome ſafe port, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are ſplitting vpon rockes. Stra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g I ſay it is, to ſee how they are blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the deſire they haue to make the Scripturs ſerue their turnes of their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which ſuffereth them not to diſcern the euidence wherewith it eſtabliſheth often tymes the very point in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſy which they contradict. For how could they otherwiſe make themſelus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, as they vſually obiect, that the Scripture authorizeth any leſſening of our Ladyes honour, that it excludeth her Inuocation, and abridgeth her Prayſe, whileſt indeed it doth abundantly teſtify
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19229:11"/>
her excellency, and giue great warrant for all that the Catholike Church doth practiſe concerning her?</p>
               <p>There be holy, &amp; learned men that affirme (&amp; it is full of reaſon) that if the Scripture had ſayd no more of her, but theſe only words, <hi>Maria, de qua natus eſt Ieſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 1.</note> Mary of whome Ieſus was borne, it had ſayd ſufficiently of her, or rather that it had ſayd ſo much, as to which no point of dignity could be added. For to affirme, that the Virgin was the Mother of God, is to giue a title which euidently inuolueth ſupreme excellency; &amp; which is ſo great in regard of the alliance, and coniunction it hath with God himſelfe, as that no power of mind created, no man, no Saint, no Angell, nor they all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather are able entierly, and exactly to comprehend what dignity it is to be the Mother of God. If therfore we are ſo far from being able to conceiue the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the glorious Virgin; ſhall we feare to expreſſe it in ſuch poore faſhion, and with ſuch ſhort termes as we are able to vſe? Or can we be in any danger of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19229:11"/>
exceſſe heerin, ſo that we ſwarue not (as we neuer do) from making her a meer creature, and from imputing the firſt cauſe of her greatnes to the infinite goodnes of Almighty God?</p>
               <p>The Aduerſaryes of her glory might conſider, that the wordes of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are not to be valewed after the rates of number, but of weight: and who hath armes wherwith to weeld the ballance, into which that maſſy quality of being the <hi>Mother of God,</hi> is layd? It goeth not, euen in ordinary Audits, by the great number of figures, but if one be placed before a greater number of cyphers, that alone may ſtand for many others: &amp; ſo this halfe line alone, wherof I ſpake, may &amp; doth import a greater eminency, then could haue beene expreſſed in the whole Bible without it; although both theſe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments, &amp; all thoſe pens of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles had ſpent themſelues in the celebration only of her prayſes.</p>
               <p>But becauſe all their cunning-men and women, though they ſhould be able to write and read the Scriptures, cannot
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19229:12"/>
yet caſt accompt, eſpecially after this manner; and that vulgar eyes are neuer ſatisfyed with the riches of a Iewell, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it conſiſt of many ſtones; I wil ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore endeauour to let them ſee, that in holy Scripture there is no ſcarcity of that which themſelues deſire, or rather of that which I feare they deſire not, which is, the great aduantages, prerogatiues, and priuiledges of the B. Virgin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>IN the firſt place I conceaue that by the way of expreſſe prayſe, as meant for prayſe, there is little ſayd in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of our B. Lady, no more then of our B. Sauiour himſelf. I call that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe prayſe, as meant for prayſe, when a perſon is <hi>ex profeſſo</hi> commended, and extolled for this or that vertue, to this principall end, that he or ſhe may win e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation among men: and in this ſenſe I do not find, that either of them are greatly prayſed: only they teſtify ſome little things of themſelues, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19229:12"/>
the ſelfe ſame vertue, which is Humility. Our Sauiour ſayd, <hi>Learne of me for I am Humble, and Meeke:</hi> and our Lady ſayd; <hi>that God had carryed reſpect to her Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</hi> Many other perſons are particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in both the Teſtaments.<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>22.</hi> Num. <hi>12.</hi> Reg. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> Iob. c. <hi>10.</hi> Reg. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Gen. <hi>6.</hi> Luc. <hi>1.</hi> Matt. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> as the tipe of Fayth; <hi>Moyſes</hi> both of zeale and meeknes; <hi>Dauid,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man after Gods owne hart; <hi>Iob</hi> for patience, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lomon</hi> for wiſedom, <hi>Noë, Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary, S. Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> for being iuſt: But Chriſt our Lord, and our <hi>B.</hi> Lady are not prayſed directly for this or that vertue, though the Apoſtles may ſecondarily, and vpon occaſion be ſayd to comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the life of Chriſt, when they exhort the people to whome they wrote, towards an imitation of his vertues.</p>
               <p>We need not go far to ſeeke a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that may be ſubiect to our capacityes why the holy Ghoſt might thinke good to take this courſe; for to haue expreſly commended them, had beene to imply, after a ſort, that words might haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how much they ought to be comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and a Reader might thereby haue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19229:13"/>
imagined, that their excellency had not ſurpaſſed all humane thought, if it had beene made ſubiect therunto by ſpeach; and therfore they are both ſet out much more to the full, in that their prayſes are couered with the ſacred veyle of ſilence, then they would haue beene, if they had beene expoſed to ſight, by the pen euen of the very Apoſtles themſelues. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as now by ſaying nothing in the way of praiſe, but by deliuering ſo much by way of prerogatiue, there is left a liberty, or rather there is impoſed a neceſſity, for men to conceiue as highly, and nobly as they can; and yet to know, when all is done, that the leaſt part of their excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency is not attayned.</p>
               <p>Hence it is, that for reuerence the Prophet <hi>I ſay</hi> (when he was to deſcribe God himſelfe in a viſion that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued) repreſented him al couered with the wings of <hi>Cherubims.</hi> And this courſe carryeth ſo great proportion, euen with the very nature &amp; mind of man, as that the famous Poets, and Painters of the world, haue graced their arts with this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19229:13"/>
point of Rhetorique, whenſoeuer they haue had occaſion to deſcribe the emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of an vnſpeakable paſſion; for in ſuch caſe they thought they could do it beſt, by not expreſſing it: and ſo in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls of ſuch as were deereſt to the Suruiuers, they ſet forth the ordinary mourners by ſeuerall poſtures, &amp; counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of lamentation; but as for a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of a deere Spouſe, or the Father of an only daughter, they haue no refuge, but to hide the faces of thoſe perſons, in the decyphering of whoſe paſſion they cannot ſatisfy themſelues.</p>
               <p>But though there be no particuler, and expreſſe prayſes mentioned as pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; not as lights, for imitation giuen in holy Scripture to the ſeuerall vertues of our B. Lady, any more then (as I ſayd before) they are to them of our B. Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; yet as the Apoſtles, and Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts recompt thoſe high and heroicall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and the irrefragable teſtimonyes from heauen, wherupon we may inferre the ſupreme vertue and ſanctity of our B. Sauiour: in the ſame manner are their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19229:14"/>
bookes the Chronicles of many paſſages in both thoſe kindes, aforeſayd, from whence the excellency of the B. Virgin may be deduced, which is infinitly infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to that of our B. Sauiour, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably ſuperiour to that of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, and is propounded to vs for the marke of our admiration in ſome things, and of imitation in the reſt.</p>
               <p>By the Genealogy of our B. Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our which is ſet out by the Apoſtles, we vnderſtand what alſo that of our B. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes is; for he hath no Anceſtours but hers. By them we therefore know, that her extraction and bloud hath as much prerogatiue in it, as a meere creature can receaue; for ſhe is deriued from the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of Kings, from the ſanctity of Prieſts, and from the illumination of Prophets.</p>
               <p>The gifts of Nature, and beauty of perſon which ſhe had, are not ſo litterally expreſſed in holy Scripture, otherwiſe then by the Propheticall ſpeach which is vſed of our Sauiour Chriſt; <hi>Specioſus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma prae filijs hominum:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.</note> He was beautifull beyond all the Sonnes of men, whereby
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19229:14"/>
her beauty alſo may be knowne, ſince his holy humanity had no viſible naturall beauty at all, but that which it receaued from her. And howſoeuer among perſons who are begotten by the courſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, we often ſee both that vncomly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents haue handſome children, and the contrary: yet in the preſent caſe there can be no conceipt of that difference, which proceedeth in others from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of originall, &amp; many tymes of other ſinnes, wherof without blaſphemy there can be no queſtion made in the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Sauiour Chriſt, which was wrought in the pure wombe of the B. Virgin by the operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy Ghoſt. And concerning the vnſpeakable digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and maieſty of her preſence to ſuch as beheld it with pure eyes (and euen they who beheld it with other, were altered by a ſinguler priuiledge of hers, whoſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty inſteed of kindling, did quench al vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly appetite in ſuch as ſaw her) I cannot but digreſſe ſo far, as it is from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to one of their diſciples, to wit, S. <hi>Dennis</hi> the <hi>Areopagite,</hi> of whome it is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19229:15"/>
related,<note place="margin">Dionyſ. Carthuſ. comment in c. <hi>3.</hi> l. S. Diony. Areop. de diuin. nom. àrt. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> that hauing the honour and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynes to ſee her, and enioy her preſence, found ſomething in it ſo far exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the ſtamp of dignity &amp; authority, which is wont to be imprinted vpon creatures, as that he proteſted, if he had not knowne by fayth, that Chriſt was God, he had not beene able to detaine himſelfe from adoring her as God. And it is particulerly to be noted, that he through whoſe mind this paſſed, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe name it is left regiſtred to all poſterity, was no Babe, nor old wife, nor ignorant Miniſter, but one of the prime Doctours of <hi>Athens,</hi> afterwardes a diſciple of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> and ſtill accounted for a moſt ſublimely learned, wiſe, and holy Father in the Catholike Church of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THESE external things being ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle eſteemed by the ſeruants of God, and leaſt of all by her (who was ſo much the more his ſeruant, as ſhe was more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19229:15"/>
and honoured by him then all the reſt) I may with the more reaſon paſſe ouer with breuity, though I could not perſwade my ſelf to paſſe ouer any thing entierely in ſilence, which concerneth her excellency any way. But the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all graces which ſhe receaued, and the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonyes of her dignity, which were giuen from heauen, are they which we ought more ſeriouſly to ponder &amp; reflect vpon.</p>
               <p>Her life being ſuch as ſeemed ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, though interiourly it were not ſo, and her vocation being ſo extraordinary as that ſhe was to be made the Mother of God himſelfe (when once he ſhould be made Man) it was agreable to the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the diuine Maieſty, to proclaim and publiſh to the world, the perfection of this creature, by an irrefragable eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 3.</note> Therefore as in the Baptiſme of our B. Sauiour, whereby he might ſeeme to haue contracted ſinne, the Holy Ghoſt himſelfe deſcended vpon him, to witnes the infinite ſanctity of his ſoule: In like manner, when before that tyme, there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19229:16"/>
was queſtion of incarnating and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging forth a Sauiour of the world in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane fleſh, one of the higheſt Angells in heauen was diſpatched in Embaſſage to witnes the eminency,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> and fullnes of her holynes; &amp; that the world might know how that her bringing forth a ſon ſhould not carry with it the leaſt impeachment to the ſpotleſnes of her purity.</p>
               <p>The Arch-angell then did thus ſalute her;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Hayle Mary full of grace, our Lord is with thee.</hi> Our Aduerſaryes, the enemies of our B. Ladyes Honour, will needes tranſlate the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſenſe (of the three ſeueral ones which it hath) whereby they may hope to diſaduantage her moſt; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will not allow it to ſignify <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia plena,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment. in cap. <hi>1.</hi> Luc.</note> full of grace, but <hi>Gratis dilecta,</hi> freely beloued. It is plainely ſhewed by <hi>Tollet</hi> in his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment vpon thoſe words, that S. <hi>Ambroſe, S. Austine, S. Hierome, S. Athanaſius, S. Epiphanius,</hi> and in effect the whole Church hath vſed, &amp; receaued the tranſlation of <hi>Gratia plena;</hi> though yet if it had been otherwiſe, I ſee not greatly why
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19229:16"/>
they ſhould triumph as after a victory: ſince if our B. Lady were as they muſt confeſſe, <hi>Freely beloued,</hi> with ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency aboue all other creatures, as to be made the Mother of God; it doth by neceſſary inference of congruity imply all thoſe perfections, in contemplation wherof the Catholik world doth homag vnto her, with attributes incomparably ſuperiour to them of all other creatures. But ſhe was found <hi>full of grace</hi> whether they will or no; and if then ſhe were <hi>full,</hi> through the beauty of her ſoule (which being firſt adorned by Almighty God, drew his eyes afterward ſo downe vpon her, as euen to be enamoured with her when he was yet to make her the Mother of the Eternal Word;) let them conceaue that can, how ſhe ouerflowed therewith afterward. And the example of the good <hi>Chananaean</hi> who did as it were oblige our Sauiour to beſtow of thoſe crummes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon her (being a Gentile) which fell from the table of the children of God, (who were the Iewes) may inuite vs to begge, that ſome drop of thoſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19229:17"/>
which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not through the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God but deſcend from the ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of that grace, wherewith the B. Virgin was ſo much more then filled, may be applyed to our benefit, and to the making of vs gracious in his ſight in ſom meaſure, which ſhe was beyond all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>It cannot but worke in vs an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme reuerence on the one ſide, when we heare by the voyce of that Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell <hi>Gabriel,</hi> that our Lord euen then was with her in a moſt particuler, and plentifull manner,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> ſaying <hi>Dominus tecum,</hi> Our Lord is with thee: as if he had ſayd, He is indeed with all his creatures, and eſpecially withall his ſeruants; but yet he is ſo with thee <hi>per excellentiam,</hi> as if he were with no body els: and on the other ſide they are miſerable, who be not drawne to affect this Sacred Virgin with vnſpeakable dearneſſe &amp; tendernes, for the infinite benefite which they receaue by her, ſince they are capable of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the myſtery of the Incarnation, which (hauing beene decreed in that high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19229:17"/>
of the Holy Trinity) did receaue effect and execution in the immaculate wombe of the B. Virgin by her free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. And as in the Paſſion of our B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour (when he came to make a ful point vpon the periode of his life) he did as it were reſigne his Mother to mankind in the perſon of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 19.</note> when he ſayd to him, <hi>Fili ecce Mater tua,</hi> Sonne behould thy Mother: ſo in this Incarnation of his ſhe may be ſayd after a ſort, to haue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the propriety which ſhe had in Almighty God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> who was with her <hi>(Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus tecum)</hi> to the protection, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, and ſanctification, &amp; redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all mankind; for immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, he grew to be called not, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus tecum,</hi> Our Lord is with thee,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 1.</note> but <hi>Emanuel,</hi> which is, God with vs.</p>
               <p>The Angell proceedeth (vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion giuen by the ſacred Virgin) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the manner how the myſtery of the Incarnation of the Sonne of God, was to be accompliſhed in her ſacred wombe; &amp; he declareth to her, that ſhe had no cauſe to feare the leaſt ſpot in her purity, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19229:18"/>
ſhe had found grace with God, that in her wombe ſhe ſhould conceaue &amp; bring forth a Sonne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> and ſhould call his name IESVS, that he ſhould be great, and be called the <hi>Sonne of the moſt High,</hi> that our Lord God would giue him the ſeat of his forefather <hi>Dauid,</hi> that he ſhould raigne in the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> for euer, that his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhould know no end, that the Holy Ghoſt ſhould deſcend from aboue into her, and the Vertue or Power of the moſt High ſhould ouerſhaddow her, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that he who was to be borne of her ſhould be called the Sonne of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quis ſurdus ſicut populus meus?</hi> ſayth the Holy Ghoſt by the Prophet:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.</note> Who is ſo deafe as my people, that wil not heare? And in this caſe it may be ſayd, who is ſo blind as he that will not ſee, what a clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of heauenly grapes may heere be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of Holy Scripture, diſtilling in abundance the wine of Grace &amp; Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vpon the imaculate Virgin, by deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the nature &amp; quality of that Sonne, of which ſhe was to be the ſo happy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? What doubling, and redoubling is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19229:18"/>
there made heere of her felicity, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity? For notwithſtanding that former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe was full of grace; we ſee heere ſhe hath found more grace, her Sonne was to be the Sauiour of the world; he was to haue an Eternall Kingdome; the Holy Ghoſt was yet more plentifully to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vpon her; and the vertue or power of the moſt High was to enuirone, and ouerſhaddow her, whereby ſhe might be enabled to encloſe, and as it were againe to ouerſhaddow the Sonne of God.</p>
               <p>The conſideration heerof made the ancient &amp; holy Fathers fly vp, as if they had beene in Extaſies, when they entred vpon the prayſes of this Bleſſed Virgin (which afterward I ſhall with better o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity relate:) and in the meane tyme they who cannot ſee the high titles of Honour that are imparted to the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in Holy Scripture, are in a miſerable obſcurity of mind, which they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruedly fallen into, through the paynes they take to beare no tendernes of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards her. I thinke I ſay well, in affirming, that they take paynes to this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19229:19"/>
purpoſe; for otherwiſe it ſeemeth impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that men who profeſſe themſelues Chriſtians, and who take vpon them to vnderſtand ſo well what is recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Holy Scripture, ſhould carry ſuch an auerſion, as it is certayne they doe (howſoeuer ſometymes they profeſſe the contrary for very ſhame) from the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that Sonne, by whome they ſay they hope for their ſaluation, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the Holy Ghoſt hath taken pleaſure, to expreſſe al the circumſtances that belong to her; and that he did not only imploy the Euangeliſts thereabout when Chriſt was to be Incarnate, but the Prophets alſo ſo many hundreds of yeares before, who fortold what kind of creature ſhe was to be. To which purpoſe theſe are the wordes of <hi>S. Bernard; The generation of our B. Lady is knowne to haue beene graunted from heauen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernar. ſer. in c. <hi>12.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc.</note> 
                  <hi>for the ſingular priuiledge of ſanctity which ſhe had. Her birth was forepromiſed by the auncient Fathers, it was prefigured by myſticall miracles, it was inſinuated by propheticall Oracles, the Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotall Rod which floriſhed without a roote, the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19229:19"/>
Fleece of</hi> Gedeon <hi>which grew moſt in the middeſt of a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y floore, the Orientall gate ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the viſion of</hi> Ezechiel, <hi>which was neuer open to the acceſſe of any, did deſigne, &amp; prediſcouer this Virgin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <p>THE next Publication of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable priuiledges of our B. Lady was in the <hi>Viſitation</hi> which ſhe made of <hi>S. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> at which tyme our B. Sauiour (being then incarnate in her ſacred wombe) did alſo viſit S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> whome S. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had conceaued in hers, ſome monethes before. The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of our B. Lady appeareth in liuely colours by the happy change which was wrought in S. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by her preſence.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> For <hi>S. Elizabeth</hi> had no ſooner heard her ſalutation, then (by the teſtimony of the ſacred Text) the infant in her wombe did euen ſpring which ioy; <hi>S. Elizabeth</hi> her ſelf was repleniſhed with the holy Ghoſt, ſhe cryed out with a loud voyce, &amp; ſayd to the Virgin to this effect; <hi>Bleſſed art thou
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19229:20"/>
among women,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and bleſſed is the fruit of thy wombe: and how come I to receaue this honour that the Mother of my Lord ſhould viſite me? for behould</hi> (ſayth ſhe) <hi>as ſoone as euer the voyce of thy ſalutation did approach mine ears, the Infant in my wombe did ſpring with ioy; and happy art thou who didſt beleeue, for thoſe thinges ſhallbe performed which were tould thee by our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ſtupendious priuiledges, &amp; prerogatiues are heere expreſſed by the Holy Ghoſt, to haue beene imparted to the glorious and immaculate Virgin? V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the firſt approach of her preſence, and the leaſt ſound of her voyce, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant in the wombe of his Mother did ſpring with ioy:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> which ioy ſuppoſeth, &amp; taketh for graunted that he was already then indued with the vſe of reaſon: for ſuch creatures as are not reaſonable, are not capable of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceauing ioy. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the working of this miracle may principally be imputed to the preſence of our B. Sauiour, as to the cauſe, yet who ſeeth not, that he was not pleaſed to impart ſuch an vnheard of benefit, but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19229:20"/>
by the condition of his ſacred Mothers preſence, to which alſo ſhe did ſo nobly concurre? and in conformity heerof, it is plaine, that <hi>S. Elizabeth</hi> her ſelfe refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vpon her, as a great meanes therof.</p>
               <p>Againe, the Mother was for her part, immediatly vpon the hearing of the Virgins ſalutation, repleniſhed with the Holy Ghoſt, in the ſtrength whereof, ſhe did with a loud and Propheticall voyce, proclaime the bleſſednes of that Mother and Sonne, and confound her ſelfe with the mercy which was vouchſafed her, in that the Mother of our Lord would deſcend ſo low, as to viſit her.</p>
               <p>This heape alone of miracles, which did as it were ouerwhelme S. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the acknowledgement ſhe made of her own extrem vnworthines to receaue ſuch graces from the mother of our Lord may iuſtly kindle an vnwonted ardour of deuotion in the hearts of Catholikes towards the Bleſſed Virgin; and as iuſtly humble the proudeſt Caluiniſts hart in the world with ſhame inough, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how ſtraitely at leaſt they conceaue
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19229:21"/>
of the glorious Queene of Heauen, who raigneth and ſhineth with immortal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, when they ſee a <hi>S. Elizabeth,</hi> a neere kinſwoman of Chriſt himſelfe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently deriued from the loynes of ſo many Kinges, a Saint in ſo eminent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, a Propheteſſe, and the Mother of the greateſt among the children of Men, who was the very Precurſour, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt of Chriſt our Lord, ſo looſe her ſelfe as it were with admiration, which ſhe diſcouereth by thoſe interiections of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, to ſee that the Mother of God whileſt yet ſhe was but mortall, and the Sauiour of the world not yet borne of her ſhould diminiſh her ſelfe ſo much, as to vouchſafe her a viſit. But I ſhal afterward reſume this point, by occaſion of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and fearefull blaſphemy of ſome Caluiniſts, when I compare the baſe mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they tremble not to make of her, with the moſt honourable memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which the lights, &amp; ornaments of the Catholike Church, the holy Fathers, haue euery where expreſſed. And in the mean tyme ſuch as loue the Sonne (as no man
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19229:21"/>
doth indeed who will not giue all due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Mother) muſt riſe to more then ordinary veneration and deuotion towardes this perpetuall Virgin, to the end, that the viſits which ſhe vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth to impart, not once, but often by her motions to vs, &amp; her prayers for vs, may make the ſpirituall fruit of our harts which is our actions, ſpring vp with ioy, vpon the preſence, &amp; approach of Chriſt in the Holy Sacrament; and that we may keep ſuch accompt of the inſpirations, which ſhe procureth for vs, and ſendeth ſo often into the eares of our ſoule, as may make it proue a fit houſe for the holy Ghoſt to inhabite.</p>
               <p>Well may we ſay with S. <hi>Auguſtine;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. li <hi>1.</hi> Confeſſ. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anguſta eſt domus animae meae, dilata eam; ruinoſa eſt, refice eam.</hi> He confeſſeth to God that the houſe of his ſoule is ſtrait, and he beſeecheth him to enlarge it; he confeſſeth that it is ruinous, and he beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth of him that he wil repaire it: and by what better meanes can we as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage Almighty God to beſtow thoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes on vs, through Chriſt our Lord,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19229:22"/>
then when we preſent, and put him in mind of this Soueraigne Virgin, who was enabled by his omnipotent hand to make roome in her ſacred wombe, not only for the reception, but euen for the regaling and delighting of him, whome Heauen cannot containe; according to that ſalutation which the Church vſeth to the B. Virgin; <hi>Quem Caeli capere non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terant, tuo gremio contuliſti:</hi> So alſo will ſhe know how to aſſiſt vs in the reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe our ſpirituall houſes, as well as in the enlarging of them; ſhe I ſay who hath concurred more then all the whole world togeather, vnder God (by the fayth ſhe bare, and conſent ſhe gaue) to the Incarnation of the Word, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to the reparation, and redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the World. This may then be our contemplation, who are Catholiks: and before this diſcourſe be at an end, euen ſome of the Caluiniſts, I hope, will ſee, that they haue not wholy ſuch reaſon to diſſent heerein, as hitherto they haue i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined.</p>
               <p>To my vnderſtanding there is no
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19229:22"/>
one circumſtance that more ſetteth out the vnſpeakable excellency of our B. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy then that which now I ſhall expreſſe. As ſoone as <hi>S. Elizabeth</hi> had ended that holy ſpeach of hers, our B. Lady being alſo the much more plentifully inſpired with propheſy, did enter into that diuin Hymne of the <hi>Magnificat,</hi> whereof the Church doth euery day ſerue it ſelfe in offering vp her prayſes to God. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that the humbleſt pure creature, without all exception, that euer was, or will be, was the B. Virgin In ſo much as that although the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al thoſe vertues (which afterward are to be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) did floriſh and fructify beyond al humane imagination in her ſacred hart, yet in compariſon of that height, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther depth of humility, which reigned in her, ſhe may be accounted to haue ſcarce excelled in thoſe other vertues: or rather to ſpeake both more ſafely, and moſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as in the other vertues ſhe without all compariſon excelled all other creatures, ſo in this ſhe excelled her ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Such as hunt after prayſe (and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19229:23"/>
whoſoeuer doth not, hath reaſon to giue God thankes, for he hath beene enriched by him with a great treaſure) do know that there is not in the world a greater thirſt, then they haue to obtain their end, and that they find no torment more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable then if they be vnderualued &amp; contemned. And yet this other truth is as certaine, that the perſon who is ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of prayſe, doth not more abhorre to be deſpiſed, then the ſoule which is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humble, doth apprehend and hate to be applauded. And if it indure not to be prayſed by others, how well, and how worthily ſoeuer it may deſerue it; how much would men be aſhamed to prayſe themſelues, which not only the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vertue, but euen modeſty and ciuility ſo far diſſwadeth, as that whoſoeuer (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of piety and diſcretion) doth it, we muſt ſuppoſe both ſome vnqueſtionable and knowne truth of the thing itſelfe, &amp; ſome moſt neceſſary and iuſt motiue or myſtery which vrgeth him to it.</p>
               <p>Heereby it may eaſily be inferred, what auerſion our B. Lady muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19229:23"/>
to haue had from making honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mention of her ſelfe vpon any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; and ſo it appeares how that at the inſtant wherein ſhe grew the Mother of God (and by that meanes became ſo far ſuperiour to all the creaturs both of earth and heauen) ſhe would know herſelfe by no other title, but of a bondſlaue. Yet neuertheles the Holy Ghoſt entring at that tyme into her, in a moſt particuler, and abundant manner, did ſo poſſeſſe all the powers of her ſoule and ſo as it were inebriate, and tranſport her with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of vnſpeakable ioy, as that ſhe fell, in this Canticle (as ſoone as ſhe had firſt done her homage to Almighty God, in acknowledging, and adoring him as the Authour of all the Graces that had beene powred vpon her) to declare and auow to the world, how humble and abiect ſhe was in her owne eyes: but that yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſhe was ſo gracious in the ſight of God as ſhe ſayd, would not only ſerue to mak her <hi>Bleſſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but that <hi>all generations ſhould profeſſe, and publiſh her to be ſuch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Happy were the man, that could
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19229:24"/>
but feele the leaſt part of that which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in her pure ſoule, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſpake thoſe words; in heauen we may hope to haue ſome notice therof, and at the preſent it may ſerue vs for an inuincible demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of her being inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parably prayſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, the paradiſe of whoſe hart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hedged in with ſo much humility, was yet content to celebrate her owne praiſe, or rather which was ouer wrought by the Holy Ghoſt himſelfe, to profeſſe how ſhe was to be honoured, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all eternity; to the confuſion of al ſuch as repine thereat, and to the entire comfort of deuout Catholiks, ſince they, and they alone, are the men who dayly ſtriue to accompliſh the propheſy of her glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>BVT how much ſoeuer we ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour heerein, it will neuer come to that height which it deſerueth; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if we conſider what ſucceeded in the perſon of our B. Lady, to whome the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19229:24"/>
Scripture ſayth, the Sonne of God and her, was ſubiect. This teſtimony was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon the returne he made with her from diſputing in the Temple amongſt the Doctors. And as it is euident inough that in all his life till that time (which were twelue years) he had beene ſubiect, and obedient to her; ſo it is yet more eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that in the reſidue thereof, (which continued for the ſpace of eighteen years till he came to preach &amp; publiſh himſelf) he continued to be ſo. The Scripture ſayth, <hi>Et erat ſubditus illis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 2.</note> and he was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto them: That is, both to the B. Virgin, and S. <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and if to <hi>S. Ioſeph,</hi> who was but his ſuppoſed Father, how much more to the B. Virgin, who was (for as much as concerned his ſacred Humanity,) all the parents of fleſh and bloud that he had. To S. <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> euen for that former reaſon he liued in ſo plaine ſubiection, as that when afterward the Iewes (making reflection vpon his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable doctrine) ſayd, though it were with ſcorne; <hi>Nonne hic eſt faber, &amp; fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us fabri?</hi> Is not this a Carpenter, and the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19229:25"/>
ſonne of a Carpenter? Whereby diuers things are inſinuated, both that in the eyes of all that knew him he appeared as <hi>S. Ioſephs</hi> ſonne, who was a Carpenter (&amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently that they noted in him ſuch a carriage as became the obedience of a Sonne to his Father:) and ſecondly, it is cleare, that the <hi>VViſedome of God</hi> becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fleſh for our ſake, did abaſe it ſelfe ſo farre, as to performe the actions, and office of a Carpenter. And from thence it might come, that he tooke the manner of ſpeach which he often vſed afterward for expreſſing his mind, &amp; declaring his doctrine by Parables and Similitudes (as the ordinary cuſtome of the Iewes did beare) taken from the <hi>Plow,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.</note> &amp; <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and <hi>Tilling,</hi> and <hi>Sowing,</hi> and the like, in which actions the inſtruments that are made by Carpenters be imployed. This laſt I ſay, is moſt probable, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued generally to be true: but in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther point of being ſubiect euen to this ſuppoſed Father of his, there is no place of doubt, without impiety, and hereſy, ſince the Holy Ghoſt himſelf affirmeth it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:19229:25"/>By the way I cannot but heere aske leaue of the Reader, to extoll and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the height of dignity, to which this holy Patriarch <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> was aduanced, who as the B. Virgin was choſen from out of all mankind, to be the Mother of our Sauiour Chriſt, ſo was he deſigned from all eternity, as the fitteſt and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyeſt in the whole world, to be the Guardian both of him, &amp; her. He it was that aſſiſted in the <hi>Natiuity, Adoration, Circumciſion,</hi> and <hi>Preſentation;</hi> He that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the honour of the ſpotles Virgin from ſuſpition; He that defended both him, and her, by his inceſſant labours, and endles cares (though accompanyed with vnſpeakable comforts) from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in that peregrination of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> He that had ſo familiar commerce with Angells, and was as it were the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter of Gods ordinances to them both; He of whome it may be litterally, and in the higheſt degree of truth affirmed, that he was indeed, <hi>Fidelis ſeruus &amp; prudens, quem conſtituit Dominus ſuper familiam ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</note> A faythfull ſeruant and wiſe, whom God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19229:26"/>
did place ouer his family. O bleſſed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily! or rather O Empire of Heauen v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Earth, which conſiſted of the Sonne of God, who was, and is God, and of the Mother of God, who was and is an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Virgin.</p>
               <p>But it is no diſparagement to S. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> yea it is honour to him, that the B. Virgin be infinitly preferred before him, both in dignity otherwiſe, and in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation as it were of duty, wherby our Sauiour Chriſt was more tyed to her, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him. So as ſince our externall actions are qualifyed, and ought to be denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by our intentions; how much more was our Sauiour Chriſt to be accounted ſubiect to our B. Lady, then to <hi>S. Ioſeph,</hi> and conſequently how much greater was the ſuperiority which ſhe had ouer him, then <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> had?</p>
               <p>Let vs conſider then, what a ſea, or rather what a world of excellency is heereby inferred, to haue been in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our B Lady, of whome the Sonne of God was not only borne for our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, but to whome he continued (du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19229:26"/>
very many years) ſo truely ſubiect for her exaltation, and for our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Let vs conſider what prudence, and power to gouerne, had beene infuſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that ſoule of hers, which the <hi>VViſedome of God,</hi> the <hi>Word Incarnate</hi> was appointed to obey? And now if you will looke a little vpon the miſlike which is taken, that we accompt her for the Queene of Angells, and Saints; conſider both how impiouſly, and how childiſhly withal ſhe is denyed to be ſo, they being but ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and ſonnes adopted; whereas ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without blaſphemy be denyed to haue beene ſo many yeares Superiour to the true, only, &amp; begotten Sonne of God, who is the Lord both of Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells. Let others who haue not the light of fayth play the Hyprocrits in ſaying they feare to exceed in honour to our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, leaſt thereby they ſhould derogate from that which they owe to our B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: but let vs haue ſcruples of offend God, and let vs continue to know that he receaueth a moſt acceptable honour at our hands by our profeſſing deuotion,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19229:27"/>
and profound ſubiection to this ſacred Virgin, to whome the Lord of life was not only ſubiect, but the notice of it is left to vs vpon record, that we might learne therby how to carry our ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Mother by this example, and that ſo much the more, becauſe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhe was to become alſo ours.</p>
               <p>And indeed though Chriſt had not beene ſubiect to her, but that only ſhe had receaued the happynes to cohabite with him ſo long, vnder the ſame roofe; euen from thence a great reaſon might be drawn for the proofe of her vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſanctity. Therefore was the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo carefull, to keep wicked perſons out of his houſe, becauſe he knew that, <hi>Cum Sancto ſanctus eris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reg.</hi> 1.22.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; cum peruerſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerteris.</hi> The company of wicked perſons will peruert thee, but the ſociety of Saints will ſanctify thee. What then muſt be our B. Ladyes caſe, through her continuall conuerſation with this Saint of Saints, but that her Vnderſtanding ſhould be ineſtimably illuminated by the preſence of that <hi>Sunne of Iuſtice,</hi> which to her ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19229:27"/>
ſet, &amp; her Will be inflamed with the neighbourhood which ſhe had to thoſe exceſſiue ardours of that ſphere of Fire, whoſe very countenance hath ſerued to heate frozen hearts, though it found in the B. Virgin no ſuch matter, as that to worke vpon. And (to conclude) that from the ſea of perfection, vpon the top whereof ſhe was ſo long ſayling with a full &amp; proſperous gale of the holy Ghoſt, ſhe muſt needs be adorned and enriched with inualuable treaſures, which by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is caſt vp into her lappe.</p>
               <p>The Scripture is not therefore ſo barren in deſcription of the excellency of our B Lady, as they who enuy her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour would fayne make themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, but in diuers parts thereof it poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out ſundry thinges with their circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, whereby we may, (and muſt if we will not be as bad as beaſts) acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge her to be of ſo incomparable an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, as whereof the leaſt part cannot be arriued to, by our higheſt thoughts. Nor were the flowers which grew in that delicious garden of her heart without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19229:28"/>
of fruit, nor were thoſe cauſes, I meane the priuiledges, &amp; great prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues which ſhe had, without the effect of moſt Heroicall vertuous actions, which may partly appeare by the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of her proceeding in al things, but through the depth and maſſines therof, cannot by any created vnderſtanding be penetrated, and admired as they deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue.</p>
               <p>There is nothing which ſerueth more to humble men, then to imploy themſelues in reading and pondering well the liues of Saints; for thereby we are taught to thinke our ſelues to be thoſe poore creatures that indeed we are. But whoſoeuer ſhall meditate vpon the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our B. Lady, will find that in compariſon of her, euen eminent Saints do fal much more ſhort, then we of them. And indeed they deſerue to be thought of in the way of meditation, which a kind of <hi>Conſtructio loci,</hi> as they call it, which may repreſent to our imagination, as well the circumſtances as the ſubſtance thereof. They are innumerable amongſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19229:28"/>
our writers, who haue at large diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed heerupon: as for me I am ſo mindful both of my diſability and of breuity, that I will but touch and go, like thoſe dogs vpon the bankes of <hi>Nilus,</hi> one of which might yet more eaſily drinke that deep Riuer drye, then any man can with the ſtuddy of his whole life, expreſſe the leaſt perfection of her leaſt Vertue.</p>
               <p>For by way of Parentheſis, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by way of a ſhort Preface, two pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations are to be made. Firſt that our B Lady did whatſoeuer ſhe did with perfect liberty of will, though preuented and aſſiſted by the rich grace of God, to the very laſt point whereof, ſhe did moſt eminently cooperate as a moſt eleuated, actiue, and liuely inſtrument; and was not of no more vſe vnto her ſelfe then a very ſtocke, or ſtone could be, according to that <hi>Manichaean,</hi> or <hi>Mahometan</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to which I would to God the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our age did not approach ſo neer. But as ſhe was Bleſſed who beleeued and conſented to the meſſage of the Angell, by the teſtimony of S. <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> ſo could
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19229:29"/>
ſhe not haue been ſo in <hi>beleeuing</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting,</hi> if ſhe could not haue choſen but <hi>beleeue</hi> &amp; <hi>conſent,</hi> and with the ſelfe ſame eleuated &amp; entire liberty ſhe performed all the reſt of her incomprehenſible acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The ſecond point to be pondered, and well imprinted in our minds, is the intenſe perfection, with al her actions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued from the great degree of hergrace and the ſublime quality of her perſon ſhe being the Mother of God, who perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them; and the eminency wherwith ſhe did them, being anſwerable to the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of a moſt worthy Mother.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>FIRST then let it be weighed with how great humility and charity (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after that ſhe was made the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God) ſhe went vp with haſt, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the mountaynous part of that Countrey, to viſit and ſalute S. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> It was no walke of recreation, but a long and laborious iourney of foureſcore and fifteene miles after the Engliſh account,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19229:29"/>
from <hi>Nazareth</hi> to <hi>Hebron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is already ſhewed by the excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of <hi>S. Elizabeth,</hi> how far it is from the power of proud fleſh and bloud, to fall into a due conſideration of ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, as this was for the Mother of God, and the bearer of him then in her ſacred wombe, to honour thus her ould kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, with a viſite that coſt her ſo much paynes. But as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayd after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>Charitas Chriſti vrget nos,</hi> we are vrged to theſe thinges by the loue which Chriſt hath borne vs:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> ſo did ſhe find her ſelfe more deeply wounded with the loue of God, for the Incarnation of his Sonne (the Myſtery wherof was then wrought) nor could ſhe find any reſt, till ſhe had made others happy by knowing of it, &amp; eſpecially ſuch as would be well diſpoſed for the receauing of ſuch glorious newes. And it may ſerue vs both for an endles cauſe of conſolation, and for an inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſon of encouragement to hope for great bleſſings at the hands of God by her meanes, ſince the firſt action that we find her to haue performed (after her being
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19229:30"/>
made the Mother of God) was to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate her ſelf to his creatures, before whome, vpon that occaſion, ſo many wonders were inſtantly wrought in that houſe of S. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For my part I can hardly meet with any thing in the life of our B. Lady which I find more admirably ſtrang, then the contempt ſhe ſhewed of reputation, in not diſcharging the ſuſpition of <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> by ſome little proteſtation of her inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, when he reflected vpon her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great with child. She could not but know that he muſt needs obſerue in what ſtate ſhe was, and it can hardly be imagined, but that the little countenance which peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture he caſt towards her, might giue her aſſurance of how ill he tooke it; wherein he went ſo far, as that the ſcripture ſpeaketh of a deſigne in him to diſmiſſe her ſecretly.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 1.</note> Yet do we not find, that ſhe did euer ſo much as open her mouth towards her owne iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. She knew that Tyme would be his Teacher of Truth; ſhe knew that ſhe had already giuen her ſelfe away wholy to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19229:30"/>
God; ſhe knew it was a defect to ſeeke or care for comfort at the hand of creaturs; and choſe rather to be ill vnderſtood, and miſtake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then ſhe would diſcouer a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which might ſo far make to her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and aduantage, as to haue declared her ſelfe to haue beene made the Mother of Chriſt, by the ouerſhaddowing of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>When the tyme was come, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe was to bring forth the Bleſſed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant that ſhe had borne, who is able to comprehend the merit that ſhe (being then the Mother of God, as much as ſhe is now) ſhould vouchſafe to go in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of winter as far as <hi>Bethleem</hi> from <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth,</hi> that being the ſpace of fourſcore and ſixteen miles, to haue her name en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled, and her head taxed by the Officers of a prophane Emperour; and at that iourneyes end to content her ſelfe with a Stable for want of better commodity, and with clouts inſteed of robes, wherin to lodge, and wherewith to cloath the King of Glory. Which though it do infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly more weigh in the perſon of Chriſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19229:31"/>
then of hers, he being God, and ſhe being but a pure creature; yet ſo far is that from diminiſhing her excellency, as that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is it ſublimed. For without him that patience &amp; pouerty had not been exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a Mother of God, but only by her as ſhe was otherwiſe, though euen other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhe was the moſt excellent creature in the whole world, the moſt perfectly, and highly vertuous, the moſt beautifull and the moſt nobly borne.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt was not only her Sonne, but her Sauiour, her God, her Father, and her Maiſter, and there was neuer any diſciple who followed on ſo neere in imitation as ſhe did of him. And therfore, becauſe afterward he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be circumciſed, wherby he ſtiched a badge of ſinne vpon his ſleeue (not that he was bound therto, but that he might leaue an example of Obedience to vs) ſhe thought it would become her alſo to be purified according to the ordinary cuſtome of women, whereby it was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that ſhe was vncleane, and had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſeeke ſuch remedyes as were reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19229:31"/>
vnto by others; whereas indeed ſhe had no more need of <hi>Purification,</hi> then Chriſt had of <hi>Circumciſion:</hi> for as he was without ſinne, ſo had ſhe euer been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the commerce of any other ſpouſe then the Holy Ghoſt: but the imitation of our Sauiour, &amp; the holy zeale ſhe had to giue high examples of vertue, made her glory in nothing, but that which might ſerue to make her inglorious.</p>
               <p>Her flight to <hi>Aegypt</hi> gaue her not only ſhame, but paine, which yet ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into, and accepted with that proofe of vnſpeakable humility, which gaue moſt bright luſtre to all her actions. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diſcourſe of fleſh &amp; bloud ſhe might haue made anſwere to S. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> when he declared the Angells meſſage, that in all liklyhood he was miſtaken: That it became not the Sonne of God, &amp; God himſelfe to flye from the face of an angry Tyrant: That if any ſuch thing had beene ordayned, it was rather for her to haue receaued the Order then for him: That the warning was to ſhort, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too ſtrait, the iourney too long, the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19229:32"/>
way too dangerous, the countrey too I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous, and Barbarous, themſelues without attendance, and without lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and ſuch other cogitations of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane prudence, or pride might eaſily haue occurred to any creature, her ſelfe only excepted. But ſhe who had dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her ſelfe already to the ſeruice of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, by the name of <hi>Ancilla,</hi> that is a <hi>Bondſlaue,</hi> or <hi>Handmayd,</hi> meant nothing leſſe then to reſume her graunt; but did that which King <hi>Dauid</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth in the Pſalme;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Sicut oculi ancillae in manibus dominae ſuae &amp;c.</hi> As the eyes of the handmayd are vpon the hands of her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, ſo were her eyes vpon the handes of her Lord, and Maiſter. She expected not that he ſhould reueale any thing to her (as he had done to <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi>) by his owne, or by an Angells voyce, but ſhe contented her ſelfe with <hi>Beckes</hi> or <hi>Signes,</hi> that is, with the leaſt ſignification of his diuine pleaſure. In conformity whereof, this being at midnight, ſhe inſtantly put herſelfe vpon the departure, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently vpon the ſuſtayning (for the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19229:32"/>
ſpace of tyme to which there was no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit put) of more incommodityes then we are able to imagine; not feeling or rather not weighing (for that delicate conſtitution could not choſe but feele to the extreme offence of fleſh and bloud) the ardour of that intemperate Climate, through the much more exceſſiue inward heate of loue, to the ſacred humanity of our B. Sauiour, which did both conſume, and yet withall incredibly comfort her deare and tender hart.</p>
               <p>They had not beene long returned from thence into <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> but that euery yeare at Eaſter, they began to performe a pilgrimage from their poore Home (which was then in <hi>Galilie</hi>) to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> being foureſcore and ten miles forward, and as much backeward, that ſo they might aſſiſt at the Ceremonyes &amp; Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of that holy tyme and place. In this ſhe continued till the very death &amp; Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our B. Sauiour. Two other feaſts there were beſides that of Eaſter, one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hebdomadarum</hi> of the <hi>VVeekes,</hi> or of <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi> the other <hi>Tabernaculorum,</hi> of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19229:33"/>
                  <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> wherupon men were tyed to go to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> by obligation, though women were not obliged otherwiſe then by voluntary deuotion. But our B. Lady, whoſe buſines was to fill the world with the odour of a moſt excellent example, did in all likelihood put her ſelfe to the payn of both theſe other iourneys, as well as we are certainly tould by Scripture, that ſhe performed this of Eaſter. And as a man had need be a great Saint, who would enable himſelf fully to conceaue &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the leaſt degree of that ſanctity wherwith our B. Lady (hauing euer the Sonne of God in her eye, and the will of God in her heart) made ſo many millions of moſt holy paſes: ſo he is no Chriſtian, yea and not ſo much as a reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that ſhall not carry a kind of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, to a perſon euery way ſo condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned as ſhe was, who meaſured ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand miles with her ſacred, but weary feet, although there had beene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it, but the very labour, which yet in her caſe was the leaſt.</p>
               <p>How good cheap do our Goſſips
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19229:33"/>
ſpeake impiouſly, by ſpeaking meanely of this ſacred Virgin? But their muddy ſouls are far from conſidering, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding hers was full, not only of innocency, but abſolute perfection, yet her body was neuer free from being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed vpon penall actions of faſting, watching, praying, paſſing through the heates, and colds of moſt tedious and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious iourneys, with that obiect for her eyes to look continually vpon, which ould <hi>Simeon</hi> had ſet before her;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> 
                  <hi>Et tuam ipſius animam doloris gladius pertranſibit.</hi> And the ſword of ſorrow ſhall euen paſſe and pierce thy very ſoule. Our Sauiour Chriſt had the chalice of his bitter Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwayes in his ſight, and the B. Virgin had the ſword of ſorrow in hers, which was ſpiritually indeed, but moſt truly, and really to ſtrike her through.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>THE height and perfection of her owne condition, made her not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend the leſſe towards the feeble, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19229:34"/>
frayle ſtate of others, as the manner often is with the men &amp; women of this world to do. A proofe heerof may be taken from her gracious proceeding at the marriage of <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galiley,</hi> where ſhe found her ſelfe, &amp; that for the preſent, without her Sonne. For the Text affirmeth, That he was inuited afterward, togeather with his diſciples; and it is moſt probable that ſhe was the cauſe thereof, as ſhe is now incomparably more the occaſion of the comming of our B. Sauiour, I ſay not, to the marriage of others but to eſpouſe himſelfe to the ſoules of ſuch as deſire it by her meanes.</p>
               <p>It was much for our B. Lady to let her ſelfe fal ſo low, as to be preſent at the celebrating of a marriage: Which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be an honourable, and lawfull ſtate, yet is it far from the purity &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Virginity; as al Virginity of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers is incomparably inferiour to that of our B. Lady; and the obiects thereof are ſuch as yield no pleaſure to a ſoule that meaneth inuiolably to be chaſt. It ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to haue beene made amongſt the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19229:34"/>
poorer ſort of people, whoſe conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe chiefly, and only loued, when ſhe ſaw the King of heauen ſo impoueriſhed for our ſakes, that he wanted a cradle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was borne, a houſe wherin to liue, and a bed wheron to dye.</p>
               <p>Her eyes gaue her to vnderſtand, that at the wedding dinner the wine had fayled, &amp; ſhe who had thoſe very bowels of compaſſion about her, wherein Mercy it ſelfe had taken the nature of man, could not choſe but declare their neceſſity to him who was beſt able to relieue it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Vinum non habent,</hi> They haue no wine. And howſoeuer the late Aduerſaries of our B. Ladyes Honour, taxe her of preſumption in ſo doing, vnder the colour of I know not what Pedanticall, or Grammaticall interpretation of ſome words in the text (which afterward I ſhall haue occaſion to mention) yet the effect which inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followed (namely the working of the miracle, and that as ſhe deſired, &amp; which our Sauiour did rather ſhew that he had no inclination of his owne to worke at that tyme, if his B. Mother had not, as a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19229:35"/>
man may ſay, euen induced him a little to breake his paſe) giueth ſufficient aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that her memoriall, which he ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed ſo eaſily, was gratefull to him, and that it was to be no ill way for vs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne any thing at the hands of Chriſt, if we ſhould make his B. Mother our inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour.</p>
               <p>If ſhe had found that they had been in want of bread, which is the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſuſtena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of mans life, it ſeemeth that in charity ſhe had euen been obliged to begge, and procure reliefe for them, but ſince ſhe had ſo much compaſſion for their only want of wine, which is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that ſerueth rather for recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then for neceſſary refection; we are taught heereby how deare a Mother ſhe is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her children; &amp; that her piety ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth not only to the obtayning of ſuch thinges without which we cannot liue at all, but of ſuch others alſo as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which we cannot liue with comfort. That wine was good, and for ſuch it was prayſed in the Ghoſpell;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.</note> but <hi>meliora ſunt vbera tua vino,</hi> thy breſts, o Bleſſed Lady,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19229:35"/>
are better then the beſt wine, that is, the dearneſſe of affection and fauour wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou doſt obtayne helpes for vs, is no leſſe eſtimable and honourable often tymes, then are the very helps themſelues.</p>
               <p>Out of theſe degrees of Humility, Purity, Patience, and Charity grew that height of Fortitude which ſhe expreſſed at the Paſſion of our B. Sauiour, at which tyme in effect there was nothing els a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the creatures to content the eyes of Almighty God. The Synagogue was corrupt, the Apoſtls were fled all but one who was there to receaue (as it were by letter of Atturney, from al mankind) the rich legacy of the B. Virgin for his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in his perſon for ours,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. lib. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> in Lucam.</note> as S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> doth teach vs. One of his Apoſtles had out of frailty denyed him, another with prodigious malice, auarice, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy betrayed him, the reſt forſooke him: but the B. Virgin fayled not there to preſent her ſelfe to receaue the fullfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of that Propheſy, which ould <hi>Simeon</hi> made at the tyme of her <hi>Purification,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſword of ſorrow to pierce &amp;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19229:36"/>
paſſe through her hart, wherof I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken. This ſword did ſhe receaue into her, not ſo as to be defeated of her ſenſes by it, as ſome bould or ſilly Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters haue repreſented; but ſhe did it <hi>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> faſt by the Croſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 19.</note> to ſhew that ſtill ſhe was full Miſtreſſe of her ſelfe, &amp; that her ſorrow though it were without limits (vpon the ſight of ſuch affliction layd v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that ſacred Humanity of her Sonne) was yet ouerwrought by a perfect reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all, into the hands of God, and an entiere approbation of al that Paſſion for the redemption of the world, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Action on the Crucifiers part did highly offend her, though our Sauiour felt not the leaſt offence in his body which did not ſlice as it were her very ſoule in ſunder.</p>
               <p>There was nothing in our B. Lady which deſerueth not to be eſteemed, as <hi>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gè ſuperioris ordinis,</hi> &amp; therfore when after the Paſſion, the Reſurrection of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour was by ſome, in ſome ſort, expected (among whom the mirrour of Pennance the holy enamoured Saint <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:19229:36"/>
was one, who with incredible affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction rather then fayth (becauſe it was compounded of hope and feare) ran to the ſepulcher to ſee what there had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened) it is not read of the glorious Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin (the rocke of whoſe ſayth was not only not to be battered, but euen not ſo much as touched with the lighteſt waue of infidelity, or doubt) that ſhe ſo much as once ſtirred from thoſe contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wherin ſhe was imploying her high thoughts; but ſhe attended the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of that whereof ſhe was alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more certaine without ſeeing, then her eyes could make her. Though we doubt not, but that both our B. Sauiour appeared inſtantly to her after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and that the cauſe why ſhe forbare to record her appearance at the Sepulcher, was not for want of thirſt to enioy the firſt moment of our B. Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours preſence, but to ſhew both what her fayth was, and what kind of thing ours ought to be.</p>
               <p>The Holy Scripture indeed ſayth, that firſt our Sauiour appeared to S.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19229:37"/>
                  <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and of the truth thereof no Chriſtian doubteth; but ſo yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all we vnderſtand thoſe wordes to be meant of ordinary perſons, &amp; who were need to haue their fayth confirmed, and euer with exception to our B. Lady, of whome S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who wel had weighed the afornamed place of Scripture, doth yet affirme, that ſhe was <hi>teſtis prima Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectionis Dominicae,</hi> our Bleſſed Lady was the firſt witnes of the Reſurrection of our Lord.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the moſt expreſſe Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buts, Excellencies and actions of our B. Lady, whereof the Holy Ghoſt in the Ghoſpell maketh mention in few, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely maſſy words; for there is not one of them which concerneth her, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth not Myſteries beyond mans ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity. And as in humane knowledge it is the faſhion for Profeſſours to hid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their ignorance when they cannot gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of hard thinges by turning it ouer to certayne ſympathies, and ſecret proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes: ſo in the vnderſtanding of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is as ordinary on the other ſide,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19229:37"/>
with me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that would be thought to know all, to make a poore Paraphraſe vpon a Text, and to ſay bouldly that no other thing is meant by it, then the little which they haue beene able to expreſſe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as yet in truth there is no doubt, but that the paſſages of holy Scripture, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they ſpeake of our Sauiour Chriſt, and that which concerned him ſo neere as doth his holy Mother, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine infinite miſteryes. They looke both vpward and downeward, forward and backward, and on all ſides, as I ſhall ſhew afterward; &amp; are not to be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any one, till we may ſee as we ſhalbe ſeene in the next life. And as for many other prerogatiues and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes of our B. Lady which appeare to ſuch as peruſe the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, both concerning her moſt deuout educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually in the Temple from three years of age, till immediatly before the Annunciation, of her diuine life af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Paſſion in the ſociety of the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued diſciple of Chriſt, then her Sonne S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> and of her miraculous Aſſumption
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19229:38"/>
into heauen, which is recorded (to omit others) by <hi>S. Iohn Damaſcen,</hi> that great Saint, and great Scholler, &amp; great Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of our B. Ladyes, to haue beene at that tyme (which is almoſt nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares ago) beleeued and receaued in the Church by a Tradition, which then he ſayd was Ancient. Theſe things, I ſay, with many others I paſſe ouer, partly, becauſe with Catholikes they would be needles, as being already ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly knowne, and by them ſo piouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imbraced, and partly becauſe for the inſtruction of Caluiniſts they will not be of much weight, becauſe forſooth they are not regiſtred in Holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>I proceed further, and will ſhew in few wordes how little reaſon they haue, who laying aſide ſo many and expreſſe paſſages of holy Scripture as I haue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, which do highly honour our B. Lady (both in the Attributes it giueth, &amp; by the actions which it deſcribeth) do catch greedily at three or foure others, which when they haue conſtrued like Schoole-maiſters rather then Deuines,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19229:38"/>
they hope the excellency of our B. Lady (which in their harts they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not endure) may be obſcured thereby: wheras if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grace or reaſon did preuaile, it wold teach them rather to rule doubtfull, and obſcure paſſages by plaine ones; then on the contrary ſide ſuch as are expreſſe, by others that are obſcure; and in true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, conclude nothing but by way of inference made without booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>I Will therefore in this place by way of concluſion, for as much as concerneth Scripture in relation to our B. Lady, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract a few periodes, which I haue found in effect togeather in that holy man <hi>Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> writing of this admirable ſubiect, where he ſetteth downe in a cluſter, that which is found in Scripture but in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral paſſages, as ſo many diſtinct grapes of the old Teſtament, being ſo interpreted by the Fathers and Doctours of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church; and thoſe others alſo of the new, being expreſſed plainly without
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19229:39"/>
figure as my ſelfe haue heere already rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, but in a more ſcattered ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner. and now to make a faire full point, I thought good, to ſee if by drawing all theſe ſeuerall beames into one burning glaſſe, I might inflame the Reader to more deuotion. He ſheweth then in his firſt booke of the B. Virgin, and 2. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, how ſhe was the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Bern. hom. <hi>2.</hi> ſuper miſſuseſt.</note> 
                  <hi>woman whoſe ſeed was promiſed in Paradiſe; She was</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Bern. ſerm. de B. Virg.</note> 
                  <hi>the true Rebecca; The true</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Hier. ad Salui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudith; The true</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Lyra ſupra Eſther.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſther; The true</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert. in Cantic.</note> 
                  <hi>temple and Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary of God propheſied by</hi> Ezechiel, <hi>and the very way of Saints; She was aboundantly ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated in ſpirit by</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Bern. hom. <hi>2.</hi> ſuper m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſuseſt.</note> Salomon; <hi>She was that which</hi> Moyſes <hi>ſaw in the</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>buſh and fire; That which</hi> Aaron<note n="(h)" place="margin">Bern. ſer. ſignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magnum</note> 
                  <hi>ſaw in the rod and flower; The Orientall gate of</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel; <hi>The fleece and dew forſhewed to</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Bern. hom. <hi>1.</hi> ſuper miſſuseſt.</note> Gedeon; <hi>The ſtarre which roſe out of</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">Amb. ſerm. <hi>80.</hi>
                  </note> Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <hi>and from whence that beame proceeded which did illustrate the whole world; She was the myſticall Arke of the</hi>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">Ber. de aſſum. B. Virg.</note> 
                  <hi>Testament, which conteyned the bread both of men and Angells; She was the golden propitiatory; The throne of that true</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">Bern. ibidem.</note> Salomon; <hi>The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19229:39"/>
Court; The</hi>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">Bern. ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>bed of honour, wherein the Lord, and King of heauen did moſt delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully repoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in the new Teſtament, behold that vnited which before you ſaw ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and conſider the weight of thoſe wordes of the Ghoſpell ſpoken, either to her, or by her, or of her. <hi>All hayle, O thou full of grace, Our Lord is with thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caniſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> de B. Virgin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt found fauour or grace with God, He hath done great thinges to me who is powerfull, All gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ſhall call me Bleſſed, Bleſſed is the wombe which bare thee, Bleſſed are the breſts that gaue thee ſuck. How commeth it to paſſe that the mother of my Lord ſhould viſite me; Bleſſed art thou among women, and bleſſed is the fruite of thy wombe; She alone it is of whome the world doth ioyfully profeſſe, that it is of the holy Ghoſt which is borne in her; She alone vnto whom the Angell did promiſe, that the Holy, which was to be borne of her, ſhould be called the Sonne of God; She alone to whome the Archangell who was ſent from heauen, and S.</hi> Elizabeth <hi>vpon earth did ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate with ſuch ſublime prayſes.</hi> Thus ſayth <hi>Caniſius,</hi> and this he ſheweth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19229:40"/>In fine I do much deſire, that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes for their comfort, &amp; Caluiniſts for the conuerſion of their ſoules to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, &amp; tendernes towards this ſacred Virgin, may reſort to this excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t work of <hi>Caniſius,</hi> where they ſhall ſee, beſides the euidence of theſe things whatſoeuer they can expect from any man, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the greatnes of our B. Lady, moſt excellently deliuered, &amp; clearely proued not only by the Scripturs of both Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but by the authority of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church in al ages, &amp; of theſe Fathers I will in due place vſe a few teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes, before I end this diſcourſe, &amp; by thoſe few, the ſpirit of the reſt may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued. Therfore it is great peruerſnes, and a ſinne euen againſt common ſenſe, that ſince there are ſo many places of Scripture, which teſtify our B. Ladyes perfections, thoſe few others which they imagine to be in her preiudice, muſt yet be rather oppoſed vnto thoſe former by theſe men, then any way reconciled, or ranged vnder them.</p>
               <p>Yet indeed what can they argue out
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19229:40"/>
of thoſe very places? They ſay, that the words of our Sauiour; <hi>Quid mihi, &amp; tibi mulier,</hi> which he vſed at the marriage of <hi>Cana,</hi> in anſwere of her ſuite, concerning their want of wine, do ſhew that ſhe was worthy of reprehenſion, and that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked her. They tranſlate thoſe wordes, <hi>Woman what haue I to do with thee?</hi> and they inferre thereby, that our B. Sauiour gaue therein a great checke to his ſacred Mother; whereas it is plaine, that they were only ſpoken for the inſtruction of them that heard, &amp; of vs that read them; to ſhew that he was not to manifeſt himſelf as God by working of Miracles, till the tyme appointed by his Father, &amp; therfore it is that he ſayd alſo further; <hi>Nondum venit hora mea,</hi> My houre is not yet com, as alſo to make the world know that we are more to reſpect the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and knowne ordinance of God, then the ſuite of friends, though neuer ſo pious and meritorious.</p>
               <p>I omit to ſhew that thoſe wordes do more naturally ſignify to this effect; <hi>Quid mihi, &amp; tibi?</hi> What haue thou,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2.</note> &amp; I
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19229:41"/>
to do with their want of wine. As if he had ſayd; <hi>This is not ſuch neceſſity as ought to vrge me toward the working of miracles ſo ſoone.</hi> But whatſoeuer the words crudely taken may ſeeme in ſome conſtruction to ſay; certayne it is, that when our Sauiour had made vs know by them, that which he intended we ſhould learne, he not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed himſelf inwardly to ſhew that mercy by meanes of our B. Ladyes pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers (euen as it were before his own tyme appointed) but by the manner he held in ſpeaking the words, and by the gracious countenance which he vſed, he gaue her puidently to vnderſtand that he would graunt her ſuite. For otherwiſe, it would not haue become her diſcretion to haue ſo inſtantly required them that ſerued at the dinner to be punctuall in performing of whatſoeuer her Sonne ſhould require of them. Yea, and by the circumſtances of the Text (which deſcribe the action ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding after a moſt particuler manner, in ſuch ſort, as if they had not beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned, it is morally certaine that they would haue made ſome fault) it is moſt
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19229:41"/>
probable that our B. Sauiour did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let her know that he would do the thing, but in what manner alſo he would do it And this at leaſt is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed, that the miracle was wrought, immediatly after our Ladyes ſuite was preſented: which is a reall proofe of her greatnes, and the acceptablenes of her prayers in the ſight of God: and this truth deſerueth to put to eternall ſilence whatſoeuer conceipt is framed out of thoſe wordes te her diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage.</p>
               <p>In like manner do they vrge, how our Sauiour Chriſt (being ſought by our B. Lady, and <hi>S. Ioſeph,</hi> and found at laſt in the Temple, &amp; made acquainted with the much care which they had vſed in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him) anſwered thus;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid eſt quod me quaerebatis, an neſciebatis quia in his quae Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris mei ſunt oportet me eſſe?</hi> Why did you ſeek me, knew you not that I was to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy my ſelf in thoſe things which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the ſeruice of my Father? But as in the former caſe, ſo in this alſo it is cleare, that when he had taught the world by thoſe wordes, that men were to preferre their
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19229:42"/>
obligations to God before any tendernes towards their fleſh and bloud, to be ſure that they ſhould haue no colour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelues, vpon this occaſion, that he would diſparage, or diſcontent his holy Mother, the text immediatly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyns, that he went away with them who ſought &amp; found him, and that he came to <hi>Nazareth, Et erat ſubditus illis,</hi> and he there liued vnder them in ſubiection: whereby if men were not wholy blinde, they would both be content to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this truth, That it is infinitly a greater dignity to haue God for her Son, and her ſubiect, then to be the Superiour and Empreſſe of all things created; and conſider alſo heere, as ſoon as he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the office of a Doctour, he made haſt to reſtore the B. Virgin to her poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of him againe as his Mother.</p>
               <p>Another offer there is made to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach the excellency of our B. Lady v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this occaſion.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 3.</note> Our B. Sauiour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wrought a miracle in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, was ſought by the Phariſyes to be deſtroyed, he retyred himſelfe to the ſea
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19229:42"/>
ſide, and on ſhipbord he preached to the people in huge multitudes, he wrought there innumerable miracles, he retyred himſelfe but was yet ſo preſſed by the people, as that they gaue him not ſo much as tyme to eate. Out of the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of loue, both in regard of his hunger, and of his danger, his B. Mother, and ſome of their kinred were ſollicitous, &amp; they of the people who were next, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted his ſpeach with ſaying, thus; <hi>Ecce Mater tua, &amp; fratres tui foris quaerunt te.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 3.</note> Behould thy Mother, and thy Brethren (that is thy kinsfolks) ſtand without &amp; ſeeke thee; and he anſwearing ſayd, <hi>Quae eſt mater mea, &amp; fratres mei?</hi> Who is my Mother, and my brethren? <hi>and behoulding them that ſate about him he ſayd, Behould my Mother, and my brethren; for he that doth the will of God he is my brother, my ſiſter, and my Mother.</hi> This place is much in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of ſome, as if it were indiminution of our B. Ladyes eminency, which yet yieldeth ſo little ground for an obiection, as that, euen for this very reaſon, it is hardly capable of an anſwere. The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19229:43"/>
of that ſpeach was this. Our B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour was moſt wickedly and fooliſhly ſlaundred by the Scribes that came down thither from <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> that he was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe poſſeſſed with <hi>Beelſebub,</hi> and that in the ſtrength of that maiſter-diuell, he did caſt out others of inferiour rancke. Our Sauiour did not only demonſtrate the falſhood, and the extreme abſurdity of that allegation, but he did withal inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, that euen they knew as much; and that of meere &amp; perfect malice they had layd that imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon him againſt the dictamen of their own conſcience. With all he denounced againſt them the finall danger that they were in, by ſaying <hi>that all other ſinnes ſhould be forgiuen to the ſonnes of men, only that the ſinnes and blaſphemyes againſt the Holy Ghoſt</hi> (wherby the ſinnes of deſperate &amp; confirmed malice which impugneth a knowne truth, are vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) <hi>ſhould neuer be forgiuen, but puniſhed with eternity of hell fire.</hi> The repreſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of which verity being made by our B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, with ſo great liberty, in the very teeth of them whom it concerned as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19229:43"/>
and who did ſo viperouſly deſire to bite him to death, might reaſonably moue his friendes, to retyre him out of thoſe dangers, wherein they vnderſtood him to be, and to aske for audience. But our Sauiour deſyring not to ſecure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but to ſaue thoſe people, ſeemed to lay aſide that petition, and ſtill to attend to their inſtruction. So as this exception taken by the Caluiniſts can proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no other cauſe, then a great ingratitude to God, a great oppoſition to our B. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and a great contrariety to common ſenſe, that the ſpeaches which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vſed to make it apparant to the world how infinitely, dearly and tenderly he would loue both all them and vs, who would performe the will of God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by ſaying that he would reckon of them no worſe then if they were his own fleſh and bloud, ſhould ſerue to no other end with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but only to derogate from that ſame fleſh and bloud, yea from his B. Mother her ſelfe, who was the only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious creature from whome he fetched al his ſacred humanity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:19229:44"/>Another like this laſt is, the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is taken from a like ſpeach of our B. Sauiours, which he vttered vpon a like occaſion. He was inſtructing his diſciples both in what manner, and in what wordes, they were to make their prayers to God; and at the end therof, he was alſo conuincing ſome of the Iewes, by prouing, that he did not caſt out one diuell by another, but by the power of God. The multitude admired, though ſome few calumniated him; and whileſt he was deliuering moſt profitable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, a woman in the company (being as it were rapt into an Extaſy of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to ſee both his diuine preſence, &amp; his ſupernaturall workes, and to heare withall thoſe wordes of Eternall Life, which were deliuered by his heauenly mouth) could not containe her ſelfe from exclayming thus; <hi>Beatus venter quite por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; vbera quae ſuxiſti:</hi> Bleſſed is the wombe that bare thee, and the breaſts that gaue thee ſucke. Wherupon he ſayd; <hi>Quinimo beati, qui audiunt verbum Dei, &amp; cuſtodiunt illud.</hi> Yea, bleſſed are they who
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19229:44"/>
heare the word of God, and keep it. Theſe men (who are ſo wiſely zealous of the Sonnes honour, as that they cannot forbeare to be carping at his Mother v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon all occaſions) would inferre alſo by this paſſage, as if our Lady were no better then one of vs, if we ſhall procure to be the ſeruants of God; drawing (as I ſayd before) a reaſon of honouring her leſſe from that which miniſtreth none at all, but giueth vs only cauſe thereby to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the dignity of our owne vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>But indeed, it is not our B. Lady, who is immediatly and principally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the good woman of this Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, but it is our B. Sauiour; and ſhe is prayſed there, but vpon the reaſon of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing brought him into the world, and for being the choyce cabinet of ſuch a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Iewell as ſhe eſteemed him; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſo much the more abſurdly done, to inferre by the declining which our B. Sauiour made from his own prayſes, that he meant any way to diminiſh the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Mother. And yet abſtracting
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19229:45"/>
this conſideration for the anſwere of our Sauiour, it is it ſelfe ſo pregnant in the proofe of what I ſay, as that it needeth not to be much inforced.</p>
               <p>For firſt it may be conſidered, that he was in a great multitude of people, That he was treating about the ſtate of their ſoules, That he was in the act of working a miracle, at the end whereof the people were already drawne into ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, and whileſt he might expect to reap the fruit of their conuerſion (which was to be ripened by driuing away out of their minds thoſe clouds of ignorance and obſcurity, and thoſe ſtormes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and enuy; this paſſionatly affection at &amp; deuout woman with more feruour of louing zeale, then exact conſideration of all due circumſtances, brake off by her exclamation that profitable diſcourſe of our B. Sauiour, to which he with diuine wiſedome made the aforeſayd anſwere: Wherby they might vnderſtand how true it was, that as his Mother was incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably happy, ſo ſhould they alſo be, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their meaſure, if they would
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19229:45"/>
make their benefite of thoſe inſtructions, that from tyme to tyme he gaue them; &amp; about which he was in a particuler en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour at that inſtant, and therfore it it is no meruaile if he did not cheriſh the diſtraction which ſpeach had cauſed in the hearers.</p>
               <p>But leaſt of all other places doth this decreaſe the extent of our B. Ladyes fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, for by it we learne that ſhe was doubly happy. Happy ſhe was, becauſe her wombe had borne the Sauiour of the world, and becauſe her breaſts had giuen him ſucke; for our Sauiour Chriſt did not reuerſe this ſentence of the holy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced vpon her which though it were not then ſo ſeaſonable, was yet in it ſelf moſt highly true. Nor could he who was Truth it ſelfe ſay that to be vntrue, which the holy Ghoſt by the B. Virgins owne ſacred mouth, had formerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced concerning her being Bleſſed, in that diuine Canticle of the <hi>Magnificat.</hi> And happy againe we find that ſhe was, ſince by the teſtimony of our B Sauiour they all are happy, who heare the word
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19229:46"/>
the word of God and keep it; for what creature did euer come ſo cloſe to the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the word of God, as ſhe who had in her ſacred wombe kept God himſelfe, who was, and is the <hi>VVord,</hi> to which ſhe communicated all the <hi>Humanity</hi> that it had, whoſe preſence afterward ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually enioyed, during the whole tyme of his aboad on earth? whoſe perfections ſhe imitated, whoſe Church whileſt ſhe ſuruiued ſhe inſtructed, and whoſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, now that ſhe is aſſumed into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſhe hath beautifyed. And al this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Almighty God who made her the Mother of God, made her in all reſpect to be as worthy of that incomprehenſible vocation, as the ſtate of a creature could be capable, and with which alſo ſhe did concurre after an vnconceuable ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner. Now to be a Mother, and a Mother wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of God himſelfe implyeth ſuch mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes of perfection, as euen fill, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the world, and from which the leaſt graine cannot be taken in any diſcourſe of reaſon vnder the pretence either of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, or common ſenſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:19229:46"/>But it were well (ſince it is ſo ill) that it were no worſe,<note place="margin">Melanc. ad c. <hi>2.</hi> Ioan. Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Copron. apud Theo. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. in S. Niceta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Melchior Hoffma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum non ſuſcepiſſe carnem ex Maria Virgine apud Bulling. aduerſ. Anabap. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> in euang. Domin. <hi>2.</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. Caluin. harm. in Luc. <hi>2.35.</hi> edit. Gal. Caluin. harm. in Matt. <hi>12.48.</hi>
                  </note> but that our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaryes would only diminiſh the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Bleſſed Lady by ſeeking to proue, that ſhe was leſſe excellent, and not expreſly to affirme thinges of her, which make her to haue beene an vnworthy and ſinnefull creature. In the ſtrength of which ſpirit of giddines, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſay, That ſhe was but like to other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vertue; others, That ſhe was but as a ſaffron bagge, wherby they inferre that hauing loſt the ſpice, ſhe was no more to be eſteemed; others, That ſhe was but as a <hi>Channell,</hi> or <hi>Conduct of water,</hi> inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereby, as if Chriſt had ſcarce taken fleſh of her, or els that at the beſt hand he infuſed not any vertue into her. <hi>Luther</hi> is often diſgracing her, and ranking her with the reſt of creatures in generall, &amp; <hi>Caluin</hi> doth as good as deduce that propo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition into particulers, and draw Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions out of thoſe principles: now ſaying, <hi>That the Virgin was at least inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, That ſhe was importune, and did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterouſly endeauour to breake off the courſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19229:47"/>
of her Sonnes doctrine;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caluin. harm. in Ioan. c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That ſhe ſinned by exceeding her boundes, and by intruding her ſelfe ſo far, as that ſhe might chance to haue obſcured the glory of Chriſt thereby;</hi> and, <hi>that our Sauiour made in a manner no accompt of that which the woman in the Ghoſpell did on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extoll, which was her being his owne Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> as alſo when the Angel announceth the Incarnation of the Sonne of God, he findeth,<note place="margin">Caluin. harm. in Luc. <hi>1.34.</hi> edit. Latin.</note> 
                  <hi>That ſhe had want of fayth,</hi> he ſayth, <hi>That ſhe did not with leſſe malignity reſtraine the power of God, then</hi> Zacharias <hi>had done before vpon another occaſion,</hi> and when he hath done, the blaſphemous He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike concludeth, <hi>Quod non ſit magnoperè laborandum &amp;c.</hi> That there is no cauſe why he ſhould take much paines in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing the Virgin from not hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome fault.<note place="margin">Iouin. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. haer. <hi>82.</hi> Petr. Martyr. ad c. <hi>4.</hi> epiſt. ad Rom. Apud Can. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial.</note>
               </p>
               <p>To this let it be added, that they thinke, &amp; often ſay, <hi>That ſhe was deliuered of our Sauiour after the ſame laborious, vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and vncomly manner to which other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are ſubiect by their deſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from Eue.</hi> Some againe, <hi>That ſhe liued afterward with Ioſeph, to all purpoſes as women vſe to do with
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19229:47"/>
their husbands:</hi> With a thouſand ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beaſtly blaſphemyes, and hereſies as theſe. For <hi>Heluidius</hi> by the teſtimony of <hi>S. Hierome</hi> was condemned as an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike within foure ages after Chriſt, for only houlding that our B. Lady did not continue in virginity after the birth of our B. Sauiour vntill the end of her mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life: and I would to Chriſt that our poore Countrey did not ſwarme with theſe vile, and far worſe opinions. But as the ſoule is infinitly to be more eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med then the body, ſo may ſhe be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to haue receaued more offence by <hi>Caluins</hi> tongue who wounded her in her ſoule, by his charging her thus with ſin, then by theſe others who haue ſubiected her ſacred body to ſo much ſhame: &amp; yet euen in that kind,<note place="margin">In the Preface to the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> 
                  <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelfe hath hardly gone ſo far as our Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Bunny,</hi> who imputeth to her, with a moſt blaſphemous mouth, the hauing committed no leſſe then foure mortall ſinnes, in the ſhort tyme of our Sauiours Paſſion.</p>
               <p>And thoſe famous, or rather infamous
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19229:48"/>
                  <hi>Magdeburgians,</hi> who are called <hi>Centuria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours,</hi> being certaine <hi>Lutheran</hi> Doctours, who in corps and by publique Authority pretended to draw downe an hiſtoricall narration of the Church from age to age ſpeaking in the firſt booke of the firſt Century, of the life of our B. Sauiour, tooke occaſion therby to taxe moſt bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; blaſphemouſly the immaculate Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God, &amp; to ſay, that when ſhe loſt her Sonne in the Temple, ſhe committed ſo great a ſinne, as that they tremble not to compare it with that firſt moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinne of <hi>Eue,</hi> and ſo doubt which of the two ſinnes were the worſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>THE beliefe and practiſe of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholike, Apoſtolike, Roman Church is very different from that of theſe men, and hath beene moſt expreſſe in this point; for it hath, throughout the whole courſe of ſo many ages, decerned, and applyed the higheſt honours, vnder God, to our B. Lady, by giuing her moſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19229:48"/>
glorious titles by erecting in memory of her moſt ſumptuous Temples, by enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſtians to keep in contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her moſt ſolemne feſtiuityes; and by powring out before her continuall ſupplications and prayers, that by her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of meditation, the interceſſion of Redemption which was performed by Chriſt our Lord, and could only be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by him, may be applyed to the ſauing of mans ſoule.</p>
               <p>When I name the Catholike, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike, Roman Church, I meane not, by Roman, that Congregation of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans only, which is comprehended with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the walls or dioceſſe of the Citty, or Sea of Rome (as ſome would fayne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vpon vs, and thereby inferre an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity vpon that propoſition, as if the ſame Church whereof we ſpeake, were both vniuerſall in being Catholike, and particuler in being but of the Citty of Rome:) but when I ſay the Catholike, Roman Church, I meane the Church of Chriſt which is ſpread into all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the earth, but yet communicating
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19229:49"/>
euery where in the ſame fayth, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, doth acknowledge the Biſhop of Rome for the viſible &amp; ſupreme Head therof vnder Chriſt. The dignity and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency whereof if it be conſidered, &amp; be weighed withall, how deuout it hath euer beene in tenderly honouring, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly praying to our B. Lady. I think there is no man of modeſty, and euen common ſenſe, who will not be induced not only to an excuſe, but euen to an imitation thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. confeſſ. l. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Non vacat, non estinane, quod tam e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minens culmen authoritatis Christianae fidei toto orbe diffunditur.</hi> It is no trifle, it is no matter of ſmal importance that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian fayth hath obtayned ouer the whole world ſuch a ſublime top of authority. Theſe are the wordes of <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> which he ſpake being yet no Chriſtian; and the ſame weight which that kind of diſcourſe had againſt Paganiſme, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicheiſme in his tyme, the ſame hath it, at the leaſt in fauour of Catholike Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, concerning the honour and inuocation of our B. Lady, amongſt and aboue all
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19229:49"/>
the other Saints of God, againſt Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, or whatſouer other ſuch Innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Non vacat, non eſt inane,</hi> it is no toy, it is no contemptible thing, which the whole Body of Catholikes, hath ſo long, and ſo deuoutly practiſed, concerning the honour of our B. Lady, and the need which it findeth mankind to haue of her helping hand. Yea, and a Proteſtant, that is either morally wiſe, or diſcreetly modeſt, as <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> was before he was a Catholike Chriſtian, will thinke and ſpeake reuerently of this Church, though he ſhall abſtract from this beliefe, That it is the only true Church of Chriſt, and do but confeſſe (which no body in his wits will deny) that it is a congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of great Order, Wiſedome, Vertue, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Extent, and Continuance.</p>
               <p>Though indeed (whatſoeuer may be pretended by our oppoſits) it is both more true, and more euident then the Sunne is bright, That either Chriſt hath no Church at all, That the propheſyes of the old Teſtament were falſe, and, That the promiſes of the new Teſtament were
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19229:50"/>
feigned, or els that this church is the true and only true Church of Chriſt, ſince all thoſe markes, and plaine tokens, which were deliuered as belonging thereunto, do clearly apply the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to this Church and to no other. For what other but this can (without the impudent face of an harlot) pretend,<note place="margin">Tertull. l depraeſ. haer. Vita B. Bern. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> Beda in <hi>6.</hi> Cant. Ambr. epiſt. 13. Oſe. <hi>2. 1.</hi> Tim. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>To haue conuerted Nations, To haue beene foſtered and nurſed by a longe ſeries of Kinges and Queenes, To haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced euen the very ends of the world, To haue beene eſpouſed to the</hi> Meſſias <hi>with an indiſſoluble bound of Matrimony,</hi> as was fortould by thoſe men of God in the old Teſtament? Or what other then this, can with any colour affirme, <hi>That it is the piller, and ground of Truth,</hi> as S. Paul did witnes, That it is but <hi>one,</hi> That it is, and hath euer beene, and is to be euer <hi>Viſible,</hi> That it hath beene, and euer muſt be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible,</hi> as is clearely to be conuinced by that one direction which our B. Sauiour gaue, <hi>Dic Eccleſiae,</hi> Tell the Church: And <hi>Si Eccleſiam non audierit, ſit tibi tamquam Ethnicus &amp; Publicanus,</hi> let him be to thee as a Pagan, and Publican, if he obey not
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19229:50"/>
the orders of this Church. For vnles this Church were euer to be indued with <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> with <hi>Viſibility,</hi> and with <hi>Infallibility,</hi> impoſſible it were either for that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of our Sauiours to be followed (and this were to impute folly to him) or els though it were followed, it would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for men to be ſaued by meanes therof, and that were to lay a worſe note if worſe may be, vpon the fountaine of all Wiſedome, and goodnes? Or what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church then this,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</note> can apply to it ſelfe, that Legacy, which <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> affirmed to haue beene giuen to mankind by our Sauiour Chriſt, when he aſcended vp to heauen, namely Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, and Paſtours to continue from that tyme till the end of the world, that ſo the body of Chriſt might be built vp, and Chriſtian ſoules be kept by the anc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of true fayth, from floating (after the faſhion of Heretikes) by the windes, or waues of phantaſticall and fooliſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
               <p>No other congregation then the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik, will ſo much as pretend to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19229:51"/>
of theſe true marks of the Church; at leaſt none but ſhe can proue that they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way belong to theirs or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by a miſerable neceſſity are conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to hide themſelues in certaine caſtles of the aire whilſt they talke of Scripture, wherby they meane nothing els but that interpretation or conceipt of their own which the intereſt either of their profits or paſſion doth ſuggeſt. By al which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that ſince we make ſo faire a claime to be the true, &amp; neuer erring Church of Chriſt, which euen our moderate Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes will confeſſe to be of great appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; that doctrine which it teacheth, &amp; from whence the honour &amp; inuocation of our B. Lady proceedeth, ought not in any reaſon to be ſo blaſphemed, euen by them who will not yet imbrace it.</p>
               <p>This Church hath alſo further (being inſpired and guided by the Holy Ghoſt) framed an Office of our B. Lady, that is to ſay, it hath compoſed a Seruice out of the Pſalmes, and other Scriptures, togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the writings of the Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which it commandeth to be recited
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19229:51"/>
at ſuch tyme as her feſtiuall dayes are ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated; and now and then it interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth certaine affectuous verſicles, to ſhew the admiration wherein it hath her ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme dignity, through the vouchſafing which God Almighty hath pleaſed to vſe with her, in making her a fit Mother for himſelfe. Sometymes it exclameth thus, <hi>Faelix nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> es ſacra virgo Maria, &amp; omni laude digniſsima: quia ex te ortus eſt ſol iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae Chriſtus Deus noſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againe; <hi>Sancta &amp; immaculata virginitas, quibus te laudibus efferam neſcio: quia quem caelicapere non poterant, tuo gremio contuliſti! Beata es Virgo Maria quae Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> portasti Creatorem mundi: Genuiſti qui te fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, &amp; in aeternum permanes Virgo. Beata ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; intacta virgo glorioſa Regina mundi, intercede pro nobis ad Dominum.</hi> Happy art thou, O ſacred Virgin Mary, and moſt worthy of all prayſe; for the Sonne of Iuſtice Chriſt our Lord is borne of thee. O thou holy and immaculate virginity. with what prayſes ſhal I extoll thee, ſince thou haſt contayned him in thy wombe, whom the heauens themſelues could not
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19229:52"/>
comprehend! Bleſſed art thou, O Virgin Mary, who haſt borne our Lord the Creatour of the world: thou haſt borne him that made thee, and thou eternally remayneſt a Virgin. O bleſſed Mother and immaculate Virgin, O thou glorious Queene of the world, pray for vs vnto our Lord. In this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner doth the Church performe to her all due honour. And in other parts of the ſame office it applyeth many other places of Scripture, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially out of the Canticles, the book of <hi>VViſedome,</hi> and the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> towardes the dignifying, &amp; celebrating the praiſes of our B. Lady, veſting, as it were, her perſon, with all thoſe appellations, and other termes of honour which are there to be found in full meaſure, and among others theſe; <hi>Veni columba mea, veni ſponſa mea, veni electa mea, veni coronaberis, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chra vt Luna, electa vt Sol, terribilis vt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorum actes ordinata, mulier amicta ſole, &amp; Luna ſub pedibus eius. Aſtitit Regina à dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris tuis circumdata varietate:</hi> and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſuch paſſages as theſe are ſung by the Holy Church, in honour of our B.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19229:52"/>
Lady, as being <hi>the Doue, the Spouſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vide Auguſt, de ſymb, ad Catec. c. <hi>1.</hi> Epipha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ſerm. de laudibus Mariae. Bernard. ſerm. in eundem locum. Apoc. <hi>12.1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the eiect of the King of heauen, one clad, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed with the Sunne, ſupported by the Moone, a Queene all clad with variety of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſtanding at the right hand of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which ſentences of Holy Scripture howſoeuer they are alſo applyed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as ſometymes to a Soule in grace, ſometymes to <hi>Heauenly Wiſedome,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes to the celeſtiall <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> yet this is no impediment why they may not alſo truly, and moſt properly be applyed to the perſon of our B. Lady, ſince the ſame Scripture hath ſeuerall ſenſes, and all of them may be true, ſo that they be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory to one another. And the Holy ſpirit of God deliuering them by the pen of the Prophets, and Apoſtles, had ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall regards and aymes at ſeuerall things to be expreſſed by the ſame words, which the Holy Fathers, and Interpretours (as children of the Catholike Church) were directed, and enabled by the ſame ſpirit to declare. Which howſoeuer it may ſeem ſtrang, to ſuch as in themſelues are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the truth of that which paſſeth in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19229:53"/>
this particuler, yet it muſt be confeſſed to be, as I ſay, by ſuch as will not generally taxe the Holy Fathers, both of folly, and falſhood, ſince they haue expounded the Holy Scriptures according to foure ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſenſes, namely the <hi>Litterall,</hi> the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> the <hi>Anagogicall,</hi> and the <hi>Allegoricall.</hi> Nay it is certayne, how ſtrange ſoeuer it may ſeeme, that the ſame Scripture hath ſometymes diuers ſenſes euen <hi>Litterall:</hi> and ſo hath that of, <hi>Expedit nobis vt vnus homo moriatur pro populo, ne tota gens pereat, Filius</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Cyril. in pſal. <hi>2.</hi> de huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Auguſt. de aetern.</note> 
                  <hi>meus es tu, ego hodie genuite. Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. <hi>8.</hi> Aug. de natur. human. &amp; Chryſ. peculia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter de Chriſto orat. <hi>4.</hi> in ep. ad Haebr. c. <hi>2.</hi> Auguſt. confeſſ l. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> &amp; <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſubiecisti ſub pedibus eius:</hi> and the authority of <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> alone may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to ſhew, that out of the ſame words of Scripture may be drawne, <hi>magna copia veriſsimarum ſententiarum,</hi> great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance or variety of ſenſes, which be all true. This he ſayth by occaſion of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thoſe only words, <hi>In principio fecit Deus caelum &amp; terram:</hi> In the beginning God made the heauen, and earth. And he ſheweth afterwards, why <hi>Moyſes</hi> may be conceiued to haue forſeen al thoſe true ſeueral ſenſes of thoſe words
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19229:53"/>
which ſhould afterwardes be gathered, <hi>Per quem Deus vnus ſacras literas vera, &amp; diuerſa viſuris multorum ſenſibus temperauit.</hi> God did by the pen of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> ſo temper and dictate thoſe dimme bookes, which he wrote, as that all the ſenſes might be true, and yet differing from one another, according to the variety of interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which diuers men ſhould make ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>BVT to returne to the aforſaid Office of the Church, there are further brought in vpon occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers paſſages of many ancient and Holy Fathers (for I will not touch vpon them of the later times) which may excite the Readers to beare all due deuotion to our B. Lady, through the pathetical and tender ſpeach which they deliuer of her. And I will accompany them which are taken out of the Breuiary with ſom others of the ſame authority &amp; tyme. Hearken then a while whoſoeuer you be, who are ſo miſerable
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19229:54"/>
as not to be deuoted to the B. Virgin, that you may perceaue how dangerous and differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a way you take from thoſe lights and ornaments of God Church, who are ready if you will to be your guides. And note that except <hi>S. Iohn Damaſcen, S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme,</hi> and <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> there is none of this full Iury but aboue a thouſand yeares old.</p>
               <p>And to beginne with the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, <hi>S. Irenaeus</hi> in his third book againſt hereſyes 33. Chapter, hath theſe words, <hi>Sicut Eua inobediens &amp;c.</hi> As Eue by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience was made the cauſe of death; ſo <hi>Mary</hi> was made a cauſe of ſaluation, both to her ſelfe, and to all mankind.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctetus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Athan. epiſt. ad Epict.</note> ſayth thus: <hi>Idcirco gratia plena &amp;c.</hi> Therefore is the B. Virgin called by the name of <hi>full of grace,</hi> becauſe ſhe did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with all graces by the filling of the Holy Ghoſt, and was ouerſhaddowed by the vertue of the moſt high.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cyrill. Alexan. hom. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Neſtor.</note>S. <hi>Cyrill</hi> of <hi>Alexadria</hi> being aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with other Biſhops vpon a tyme of ſolemnity, ſpake thus in a ſermon made
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19229:54"/>
againſt the Heretike <hi>Nestorius; Hilarem video coetum fidelium omnium &amp;c.</hi> I ſee this Congregation of all the faythfull to be full of alacrity, who are come togeather with cheerefull mindes, being called by the holy Mother of God, &amp; yet euer Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary.</hi> Prayſe &amp; glory be to thee, O Holy Trinity, who haſt conducted vs all to this ſolemnity. Praiſe alſo to thee, O thou Holy Mother of God. For thou art that precious pearle of the whole world; Thou art a lampe neuer to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed; The crowne of virginity; The ſcepter of true fayth; A temple not to be diſſolued, conteyning him who could within no place be contayned; A Mother and a Virgin. Bleſſed art thou amongſt women, being the parent of him, who being bleſſed came in the name of our Lord. By thee the Trinity is glorifyed; By thee the precious Croſſe is celebrated, &amp; adored throughout the whole world. By thee heauen triumpheth, Angells and Archangells reioyce, Diuells are driuen away, and man himſelfe is recalled to heauen. By thee all creatures (once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19229:55"/>
in the errour of Idolatry) are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the knowledg of the truth. The faythfull are come to Holy Baptiſme, &amp; Temples are built throughout the whole world. By thee do the Nations come to pennance. What ſhal I ſay more? By thee the only begotten Sonne of God, that true light did ſhine to ſuch as ſate in dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes; By thee the Prophets did foreſhew ſaluation to the Gentils; And by thee did the Apoſtles preach it. Who can vnfold the eminency of thy prayſe, O thou Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and virgin <hi>Mary?</hi> Let vs celebrate her, moſt beloued Brethren, adoring her Sonne the immaculate ſpouſe of the Church, to whome be honour and glory for all Eternityes. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Ephrem</hi> in an Oration of the prayſes of the moſt Holy Mother of God,<note place="margin">Ephr. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. de laudibus SS. Dei Matris.</note> 
                  <hi>Intemerata prorſus<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pura &amp;c.</hi> The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toucht and entierely pure virgin the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God; The Queen of all men; The hope of ſuch as deſpaire; My moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and beſt Queene; More ſublime then the celeſtiall ſpirits; More pure then the Sunne beames and ſplendours; More
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19229:55"/>
honourable then the Cherubim, &amp; more holy then the Seraphim.</p>
               <p>Heare what the holy and learned S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayth in his booke of the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Virgins. <hi>Christi lilia &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambr. de Inſtit. Virgin. cap. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> The lillyes of Chriſt are eſpecially virgines, whoſe virginity is bright &amp; immaculate; for that Virginall wombe was the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and roote, and perpetually ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging fountaine, from whence by that moſt powerfull example of the Mother of God, all the Quires of Virgins did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Maria &amp;c.</hi> (ſayth S. <hi>Epiphanius</hi>) of the Virgin Mary,<note place="margin">Epiph. l. <hi>3.</hi> hareſ. <hi>73.</hi> poſt med.</note> life was borne vnto the world ſo that ſhe gaue life to him that liueth and Mary was made the Mother of ſuch as liue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Hierome</hi> vpon the eleuenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Iſay, Virgam de radice &amp;c.</hi> Let vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the holy Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> to be the Rod that ſpringes out of the roote of <hi>Ieſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Theodoret</hi> vpon the Canticles, <hi>Inter tot animas omnium hominum &amp;c.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſoules of all the men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19229:56"/>
that ſhallbe ſaued, that only one is as the elected doue, who brought forth Chriſt, a virgin, a Mother, a mayd, who doubtles did excell in purity both the Cherubim and the Seraphim.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. l. de natur. &amp; grat.</note>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his booke of <hi>Nature</hi> &amp; <hi>Grace: Cum de peccatis agitur &amp;c.</hi> When there is any ſpeach of ſinne, I will make no queſtion of the Bleſſed Virgin, for we know that more grace was giuen to her for the totall ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of ſinne, who deſerued to conceaue, and to bring him forth, of whome it is euident that he had no ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. tract. de ſymb. ad Cach. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> tom. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note>The ſame holy Father in a Treatiſe of the <hi>Creed</hi> vnto Catholikes, the third booke, and 4. Chapter, in few but maſſy words ſpeaketh thus of the B. Virgin, <hi>Per feminam &amp;c.</hi> death came by a woman, and life alſo by a woman. By <hi>Eue</hi> came deſtruction, and ſaluation by <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. in <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. Reg.</note>
                  <hi>S. Gregory</hi> the great vpon the firſt booke and Chapter of Kinges <hi>Poteſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius montis nomine &amp;c.</hi> The euer moſt B. Virgin Mary Mother of God, may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by the name of this mountaine.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19229:56"/>
For ſhe was a mountaine who by the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of her election did tranſcend the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of elected creaturs. Was not <hi>Mary</hi> a high mountaine, who that ſhe might arriue to the conception of the Eeternall <hi>Word,</hi> did raiſe the top of her merits aboue all the Quires of Angells, till ſhe came vnto the throne of the Deity: for of the moſt excellent dignity of this mountaine the Prophet <hi>I ſay</hi> doth ſay;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>In the laſt dayes there ſhallbe a mountaine of our Lord prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the top of the mountaines.</hi> For ſhe was a mountaine in the top of mountaines, becauſe the height of <hi>Mary</hi> doth ſhine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Saints. And ſhe is aptly called both a mountaine, and houſe, who being illuſtrated with incomparable merits, did prepare her ſacred wombe wherein the only Sonne of God might repoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Iohn Damaſcen</hi> in his booke of <hi>Catholike fayth,</hi> affirmeth of our B. Lady, that <hi>reuera Domina facta eſt &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Damaſc. de fide or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoxa.</note> She was indeed made the Lady with dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all creatures when ſhe was made the Mother of the Creatour. And in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond oration of the death of the Mother
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19229:57"/>
of God: <hi>Clamemus cum Gabriele &amp;c.</hi> Let vs crye out with the Angell Gabriell, All hayle, O thou full of grace, All hayle O thou inexhauſted ſea of ioy, Al hayle, o thou eſpecial lightner of our burthens; All hayle, O thou medicine of all the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of our harts, All hayle, O thou holy Virgin, by whome death was bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and life introduced.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſelm. de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cep. Virg. &amp; peccat. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig. c. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>S. Anſelme</hi> in his Treatiſe of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne Chapter 18. <hi>Decebat vt illius &amp;c.</hi> It was fit that the Conception of that man (he ſpeaketh there of Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) ſhould be made of the moſt pure Virgin, and therefore it was fit, that this virgin ſhould moſt ſweetly ſhine with ſo great purity then which a greater cannot be imagined vnder God, to whome God the Father reſolued to giue his only Son.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> in his ſermon vpon the corporall Aſſumption of the B. Virgin into heauen ſayth thus; <hi>Quis cogitare ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiat &amp;c.</hi> Who is able to conceaue how gloriouſly the Queene of the world went forward as vpon this day, and with how great entiernes of tender deuotion the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19229:57"/>
whole multitude of thoſe celeſtiall legio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s came forth to meete her? With what canticles ſhe was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducted to the throne of glory? With how ſerene a face, with how deare a countenance, with how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine imbracements ſhe was receaued by her Sonne, &amp; with that glory which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſuch a Sonne.</p>
               <p>In his fourth Sermon vpon the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, after he had with this proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Non eſt quod me magis delectet &amp;c.</hi> There is nothing wherein I take more ioy, &amp; ſo yet there is alſo nothing which putteth me into a greater trembling of feare, then to diſcourſe vpon the glory of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> &amp;c. he proceedeth ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after to ſay this; <hi>Quae enim vel Angelica puritas &amp;c.</hi> What purity though Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall will preſume to compare it ſelfe to this virginity, which was made worthy to become the ſacred repoſe of the Holy Ghoſt? But how great and how precious was the vertue of thy humility with ſo great purity, with ſo great innocency, with a conſcience wholy free from ſin, yea with the fullnes of ſo much grace?
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19229:58"/>
Whence hadſt thou humility, &amp; ſo great humility, O thou bleſſed Creature? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed thou wert worthy whom our Lord ſhould regard, whoſe beauty the King ſhould deſire, by whoſe fragrant odour he might be drawne from that eternall reſting place of his Fathers boſome. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould, O B. Virgin, we accompany thee a far off, as we may, with theſe acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whileſt thou art aſcending to thy throne. Let it be an effect of thy piety to make knowne vnto the world that grace which thou foundſt with God, by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning through thy holy prayers pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſuch as are faulty, cure for the ſicke, ſtrength of mind for the weake, comfort for the afflicted, and help and liberty for ſuch as are in danger. And now in this day of thy ſolemnity &amp; ioy, by thee, O gracious Queen, let thy Sonne Chriſt Ieſus our Lord (who is God for euer bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed aboue all thinges) beſtow the giftes of his grace vpon vs his poore ſeruants, who with prayſe are calling vpon the ſweet name of <hi>Maria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are ſome of thoſe paſſages,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19229:58"/>
which I find recorded amongſt many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of ſome few Fathers, who partely ſpeake, though but compendiouſly, in the Roman Office or Breuiary, and ſome other few which I take out of their own vndoubted workes, whereby the Reader may ſee not only the iudgement of the Church, but how expreſſe, and earneſt the moſt excellent members thereof haue beene, and how deuoutly they haue not only celebrated the praiſes, but recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to our B. Ladyes pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers And there would neuer be an end if I ſhould ſtriue to deliuer the almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite attributes of excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy which they haue giuen to her, which ſome of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout ſeruants, hauing gathered out of their works, they grow euen to fil whole bookes. Among others the <hi>Margarita,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hebdomada Mariana</hi> may be conſidered, where the Reader ſhall find <hi>S. Irenaeus, S. Cyprian, S. Athanaſius, S. Ephrem, S. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius, S. Ambroſe, S. Chryſoſtome, S. Auguſtine,</hi> S. <hi>Gregory, S. Iohn Damaſcen, S. Anſelme, S. Bernard</hi> with the reſt of theſe later ages, who haue al ſtriued to expreſſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19229:59"/>
themſelues, as there you may find parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly cyted, in calling her; The win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of heauen; The treaſure of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity; The ſolace of the world; The woman which transfuſed grace into vs; The enſigne of fayth; A cauſe of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mankind; The throne of the Diuinity; The Captaine Generall; The fountaine of all Conſolation; The ioy of Saints; The Queene of Angells; The Mother of Mercy; The mother of the liuing; The ſuccour of ſuch as are in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger; A Queen aſſiſting, and raigning at the right hand of her Sonne; The vnlocker of Heauen gates; The ſcepter which commandeth all; The roote of glory; The roſe which hath perfumed all thinges with heauenly odours; A temple beautifyed by the holy Ghoſt; She who confoundeth all hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call prauity; The ſcepter of orthodoxall Fayth; A mountaine of our Lord prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the top of the mountaines.</p>
               <p>Innumerable I ſay are the Attributes of honour which the Holy Fathers haue giuen to this ſacred Virgin, and many of them haue beene deliuered, though with
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19229:59"/>
great profit, and piety, yet in ſuch affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuous tearmes, as the Catholikes at this day dare ſcarcely vſe, through the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme malignity of our Aduerſaryes and hers: becauſe as there is no word which may not haue diuers ſignifications; ſo they will be ſure to interprete them euer in the worſt ſenſe: whereas Charity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth iuſt the contrary. And if they proceeded according to the rule thereof, they would neuer charge, either the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathers, or vs their children with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating any thing from Almighty God, by the honour we do to our B. Lady. But whenſoeuer they find vs to aſcribe any quality or title to her, which to a weake, or wrong iudgment may ſeeme only to belong to him; they may know once for all, that we impute ſuch thinges to God as to the Tree, from which ſhe tooke her growth; he is the fountaine, ſhe is the ſtreame; he is the great Artificer and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary cauſe, and ſhe a moſt eleuated In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument; he is the Sunne, and ſhe the Beame, whereby he hath communicated his light, and heat to this darke &amp; frozen
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19229:60"/>
world of ours.</p>
               <p>So that they need not thus peruerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continue to aske vs what it is, that we can ſay more in honour of Chriſt, then we ſay in honour of our B. Lady? For we can ſay, and we do ſay according to theſe moſt true profeſſions, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations following, which may for euer ſerue to the iuſtification of our whole practiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heerein, and for the diſcouery of their either folly, or malice that oppoſe it.</p>
               <p>We profeſſe this difference between the excellency of Chriſt our Lord, and that of the B. Virgin, That the B. Virgin is no more but a pure creature, but that Chriſt is God, and ſo there is no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon at all betweene the excellency of God, and her; That in reſpect of God ſhe is infinitely leſſe then the leaſt graine of duſt is leſſe then the whole world; That it was the only goodnes of God, that choſe her firſt out of all mankind to be his Mother; That all her greatnes, and perfection dependeth vpon the firſt grace that God gaue her. This I ſay, is that we
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19229:60"/>
all profeſſe, and this being ſuppoſed and kept inuiolable, it is euident that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer honour or excellency we aſcribe to her, ſo far we are from robbing God Almighty of his honour by it, as that on the contrary ſide we highly honour him, in acknowledging his vnſpeakable beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity and bounty towardes mankind, a part whereof he hath ſo much enobled, as to make it the Mother, and the ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Mother of Chriſt our Lord, who is alſo God.</p>
               <p>Now, ſince the honour we do to the moſt ſacred Virgin, proceedeth only from this roote, &amp; the dependance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon: let it be conſidered what a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous propoſition this is? That we diſhonour Chriſt by the exceſſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which we do to the Mother of God, whome yet we chiefly honour, becauſe ſhe was his Mother, and whome we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour not at all beyond the capacity of a pure creature. Theſe propoſitions being then ſuppoſed, it wll be leudly done heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, by ſuch as ſhall take exceptions at the termes wherewith the Catholike
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19229:61"/>
Church, or her children, haue thought fit to celebrate our B. Ladyes memory. For if they be not rather ſchoole boyes, then ſchoole men, if they be not ſuch as had rather find a knot in a ruſh, then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye it, they will follow the counſaile of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his booke <hi>de vtilitate credendi cap.</hi> 7. That whenſoeuer any phraſe, or ſpeach is vſed by Catholikes which may ſound leſſe plauſible, men are to trauaile vp and downe ouer a whole world, if need be, for the finding of an excuſable interpretation therof, rather then to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre therby that the doctrine or practiſe of the Catholike Church is impure.</p>
               <p>And ſo much the rather are they bound to do it, becauſe there is no word which hath not in this reſpect, the nature of a Medall, that is, it hath a right ſide, and a wrong; and ſo hath euery garment which they weare. And as he were a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſeruant that would apparell his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter with the wrong ſide outward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are two ſides: ſo they are to be contemned, and caſt out as wranglers who wil needs take the words of another
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19229:61"/>
man in the ill ſenſe, eſpecially when he proteſteth to meane them in the good; &amp; moſt certaine it is that by the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure whereby they would take honour from our B. Lady, vnder the pretence which they make of our vſing termes that are ſubiect to the miſconſtruction of malice, a man may as well take credit from the holy Scripture it ſelfe which ſayth; That God Almighty hath armes, and leggs, and paſſions of the mind like mortall and ſinnefull creatures.</p>
               <p>For if thoſe wordes be not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by a Religious diſcretion, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpeach will proue as vnſafe at leaſt as any other that we vſe, when there is queſtion of doing honour to our B. Lady. But as our caſe ſtandeth, we need not, that our Aduerſaryes ſhould put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ouer much paynes, ſince by the profeſſions that are already made it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, how all titles of honour vnder God may agree to the B. Virgin, and not only that they may be giuen without ſin, but that it is both piety in them that do it, and impiety in them that oppoſe to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:19229:62"/>What diſhonour is it to an earthly King, if his Mother be called the Queen of his Countrey: the kingdom is known to belong in right of propriety to the King and ſhe leaueth not to be a ſubiect though ſhe haue the honour to be called, &amp; to be the Queen? Or what diſhonour were it to a King, if that Queene were called the Queen of his ſubiects, of whoſe perſons howſoeuer the King alone can diſpoſe in rigour, yet who among them (being indeed a loyall, &amp; louing ſubiect to the King) would not hould himſelfe for happy, in being able to execute any iuſt commandment of his Mothers?</p>
               <p>Thus thinges do paſſe euen heere on earth, and it is well that they paſſe ſo; for theſe are not apiſh cuſtomes, nor hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous inuentions, nor effects of ſeruile flattery, but they flow from reaſon, and nature, and they are warrantable by all lawes, both diuine and humane. And when any thing is ſo warrantable, a man may well inferre, that in the ſpirituall Kingdome of Chriſt ſuch thinges are practiſed with much more eminency, &amp;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19229:62"/>
perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nor doth it by infinite degrees ſo well become an earthly Monarch, that his Mother be acknowledged for the Queene of his Countrey, and of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, as it becometh the Humanity of Chriſt our Lord, that the ſacred Virgin (from whome he tooke all the humanity that he had, vniting it hypoſtatically to the God-head) ſhould haue the honour to be the Queene of heauen which is his Contrey, and the Queene of Angells &amp; Saints who are his ſubiects; and who are glorious, and immortall by the merits of that bloud which he tooke from her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and vnited it to himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>THvs ſtandeth the caſe concerning the Attributes of honour, which Catholikes are glad they haue the grace to giue our B. Lady: and touching the other point of her inuocation, which is alſo both auowed, &amp; deuoutly practiſed by the Fathers, whome I haue alleadged, and with whom, and in whoſe company
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:19229:63"/>
I might cyte the reſt,<note place="margin">Concil. Calced. act. <hi>1.</hi> Dionyſ. Areop. <hi>2.</hi> Eccleſ. hierarch. Ambr. l. de viduis vltra me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium. Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>84.</hi> in Ioan. Athan. ſerm. de annunt. Deiparae circa fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baſil. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. in <hi>40.</hi> Mar. &amp;c.</note> I will leaue for the preſent to preſſe our Aduerſaryes with their authority, remitting the more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Reader to whome he will of an hundred Catholike Writers, who haue clearely euicted this point of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy: &amp; for my part (who could not paſſe it ouer wholy in ſilence) I will in very few words debate how the caſe ſtandeth with them in reaſon, according to the grounds of their Religion.</p>
               <p>If inuocation of the Saints in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and in particuler of the glorious Virgin be reiected, our Aduerſaryes muſt doe it firſt (if they will be true to their own grounds) for reaſons drawne from Holy Scripture. When they preſſe vs to proue it by teſtimony therof, they are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly tould, that they proceed impertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For they are the men who ſhould proue it to be forbidden by Scripture, &amp; not we that it is expreſly enioyned. For vnles it be forbidden, they cannot vpon that reaſon diſclaime from the vſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, who doe themſelues practiſe diuers things, whereof there is no expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19229:63"/>
in Holy Scripture, as namely they <hi>baptize Infants,</hi> and they <hi>obſerue the Sabbaoth vpon the Sunday &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20</note> The later of which points is ſo far from being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that it rather ſeemeth to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> when the Saturday is clearely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for that purpoſe. Nay <hi>the eating of bloud, and ſtrangled meats,</hi> was prohibited to the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Primitiue Church which yet the Caluiniſts make no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to eate as well as we, which in vs is no offence, who obey the Church, which telleth vs that <hi>the tyme of keeping the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth was ceremoniall,</hi> and conſequently abrogated by the comming of Chriſt, &amp; that the <hi>Precept</hi> about abſtaining from thoſe meats was but temporary, and that now the date therof is expired. But our Aduerſaryes, who ſay they are only gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by that which is deliuered to them in Scripture, are conuinced by their owne practiſe to be Hypocrits; and may iuſtly, be doubly accompted ſo, if whileſt they practiſe thoſe thinges which are expreſly againſt the Commandment of Holy Scripture, they do yet reiect the Inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19229:64"/>
of Saints, only becauſe we do not ſhew as they ſay, that it is expreſly inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Scripture.</p>
               <p>Two reaſons they vſe to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, the former whereof pretendeth to ſhew, that it is not lawfull, the latter that it is not conuenient. But whoſoeuer marketh their proceeding well, ſhall find the weaknes of their cauſe by this, that howſoeuer theſe reaſons be of very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent nature, and independent of one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; yet if they be well encountred, they neuer ſticke to either of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences a part, but are euer hopping, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther halting from one to the other. The former of them is, That (forſooth) inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints is both derogatory to the honour of God, and iniurious to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of Chriſt; and then they diſplay their colours (for they are but colours) <hi>Gloriam meam alteri non dabo: Vnus eſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator Chriſtus Ieſus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>Matt.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Venite ad me omnes qui laboratis &amp;c.</hi> I will not giue my glory to any other: There is one mediatour Chriſt Ieſus: Come vnto me all you that labour, and the like. But what of all this?
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19229:64"/>
Therefore Chriſtians may not pray to Saints? Who ſeeth not the childiſhnes of this conſequence? And when once we conuince them, that it is of not diſhonour to God, they haue nothing to ſay, but that the Saints cannot heare vs; and when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine we proue that the Saints do heare vs, they returne to their impertinency of telling vs, that we diſhonour God.</p>
               <p>But howſoeuer to the firſt place of Scripture it is truly anſwered, that the <hi>Glory</hi> which there is ſpoken of, is the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> incommunicable, and only due, and proper vnto God himſelfe; but that the <hi>Glory</hi> giuen by vs to Saints in beſeeching them to pray for vs, is both ſo far of an inferiour nature, as that we impart it to ſinnefull men and women, as often as we recommend our ſelues to their prayers; and we alſo giue by them, a particuler in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of honour to God, in acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the mercy he ſheweth to his creaturs whileſt he enableth his better ſeruants to aſſiſt vs.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond, no more occurreth to be ſayd, but that Chriſt our Lord is the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19229:65"/>
only mediatour of Redemption, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in that place; but if he were alſo the only mediatour of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion betweene God and man, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould all the Children in England be ill brought vp, when they are appointed to aske their Parents bleſſing, but the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtle himſelfe when he commended the neceſſity of his ſoule to the prayers of the <hi>Romans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.</note> had committed a moſt iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious act againſt the Sauiour of the world whoſe fayth he preached.</p>
               <p>The third place breedeth ſo little dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, as that it ſcarce deſerueth an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. For our B. Sauiour therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth all men who were either ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthned with the obligations of the old Law, or frighted with the horrour of their ould conſciences, that they would reſort to him, as to one that would deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them from both. But he was far from diuerting the members of his body from participating with the reſt of their owne communion, and from approaching to his mercy, by the meanes of his deereſt ſeruants, whether they liued ſtill in this
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19229:65"/>
earthly pilgrimage, or were tranſplanted into that Garden of Eternall glory. And if the meaning of theſe paſſages of Holy Scripture had been ſuch as the Caluiniſts pretend, it were ſtrang that no one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Church in any age ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete them towards the impugnation of the inuocation of Saints.</p>
               <p>Nay euen by the Scripture it ſelfe which cannot be contrary to Scripture, we are taught that this place doth contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute nothing to the Caluiniſts opinion; ſince we find diuers inſtances of men, that came to God by meanes of the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of other men, who yet were ſo farre from derogating therby, either from the glory of God, or their owne good other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as that therby they obtayned their iuſt deſires. There was a tyme when Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God made the children of <hi>Iſraë</hi> know, that he would not pardon them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.</note> but by the meanes of ſuch prayers as his ſeruant <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſhould make in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe And the irreuerend friends of <hi>Iob</hi> were inſtructed by God himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 42.</note> that if they would obtaine remiſſion of their
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19229:66"/>
ſinnes, they ſhould make interceſſion to <hi>Iob</hi> that he might pray for them, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing plainly that for his ſake, and at his ſuite, they ſhould find ſuch fauour as would haue beene denyed them for their owne. Nor hath any reaſon beene euer yet alleadged, why it ſhould be of diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Almighty God, that men ſhould recommend themſelues to the prayers of Angells and Saints, &amp; that it ſhould not be more diſhonourable to him, that we ſhould inuocate and pray ſinnefull men to intercede for vs.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon which they bring againſt the inuocation of Saints, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſay, <hi>they cannot heare vs.</hi> Let this therfore be conſidered of, and let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> talke no more of the former, ſince theſe depend not vpon one another. It is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the hiſtory of <hi>Tobias,</hi> by the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Archangell <hi>Raphael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tob.</hi> 12.</note> that he offred vp the ould mans deuotions of prayers and almes to the acceptance of Almighty God: But this Booke forſooth muſt be Apocriphall. If they meane not alſo to caſt Chriſt out of the Canon,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19229:66"/>
what anſwere can be made to that amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſpeach of his, which telleth vs, <hi>that the Angells of heauen do ſo reioyce at the conuerſion of ſinners?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 15.</note> Or what to the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the beloued diſciple, to whome this amongſt other thinges was reuealed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Angells were ſtill offering vp their prayers which were made vpon earth?</hi> We are taught alſo by <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.</note> that the Saints are as the Angells of heauen: and to conuince the Caluiniſts in one, is to do it in both. But can either of them offer vp our prayers, vnleſſe they know them to be ſuch? Or can they reioyce at my conuerſion vnles they ſee the acts of my contrition, and of the fayth wherby I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the promiſes of Chriſt in generall; and of hope whereby I apprehend, and apply them in particuler; and of the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity whereby I am grafted as a liuing branch into that true vine, and in a moſt particuler manner of the deſires I haue of their prayers for me? It is the part of a mad man to call theſe thinges in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
               <p>Againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.</note> the Patriarch <hi>Iacob</hi> when
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:19229:67"/>
he was vpon the point to leaue this world bequeathed his children to the protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his good Angell, beſeeching him that as he had preſerued him, ſo he would alſo bleſſe them. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt in the very entrance of th <hi>Apocalyps</hi> in theſe words,<note place="margin">Apoc. c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gratia vobis &amp; pax ab eo quieſt, &amp; qui erat, &amp; qui venturus eſt, &amp; à ſeptem ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritibus,</hi> beſeecheth God and the ſeauen ſpirits reigning with him to be gracious to them.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 15.</note> And though <hi>Diues</hi> in the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell were a damned ſoule, yet he was not condemned for praying to <hi>Abraham</hi> after he was dead; and much leſſe can it be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, but that <hi>Abraham</hi> heard his prayer though it were not graunted. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells therefore and the Saints may euen out of Scripture be proued to heare our prayers, ſince we find thereby that men prayed to Saints without any note of that folly, which would haue beene done to them, if the Saints had not heard their prayers.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Mach.</hi> 15.</note>Moreouer ſince the Scripture tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs otherwiſe, that <hi>Onias, Ieremias,</hi> and other Saints, after they had departed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19229:67"/>
out of this life, did inſtanily, and inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly make their prayers for the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this world; what inconuenience can be imputed by our Aduerſaryes to the beliefe we haue, that in his face who ſeeth all things, they ſee alſo the prayers we make to him by their meanes? And ſince we all profeſſe that the Saints of heauen are completely happy, how enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſerue they to be accompted who would abridge them of all power to help &amp; heare miſerable creatures, who ranke themſelues vnder their patronage, and recommend themſelues earneſtly to their aſſiſtance? Not as they would do to God vpon whome their good originally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth, and from whome all grace and glory floweth; but as to his friends, and fauorits, who on the one ſide haue had experimentall knowledg of our miſeryes and on the other ſide haue beene aſſumed to the reward of eternall happynes, and are as ſo many conueyances, and rich conducts of celeſtiall graces to the ſoules of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:19229:68"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>THERE is no article of our Religion which is more impugned by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of mankind, then this of Saints: &amp; I could name a great Caluiniſt, and a great man that liued not long agoe, who could patiently inough be tould that he was not truly called to the place he held, who yet when there was ſpeach of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation of the B. Virgin, grew abruptly into ſuch a paſſion, or rather fury, as that he ſeemed to be little better then poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed. And as all of them are extremely auerſe in the generality of praying to Saints, ſo particulerly it hath place when there is no queſtion of honouring, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring the ayde of our B. Lady. But it hath pleaſed Almighty God in his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that after the rate of their malice who impugne this article; ſo is the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whereby they are to be conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, plaine, and teſtifyed not only by the practiſe of the Church, the expreſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Holy Scripture, the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19229:68"/>
with nature and reaſon, but with infinite arguments of miracles which God hath ſet as ſo many ſeales vpon this Truth.</p>
               <p>It is ſtrang (and would be incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if we were tould by leſſe then expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience it ſelfe) that there ſhould be ſuch a deale of infidelity in the world, as to make men doubt, and of impudence as to make them deny, that the power and gift of miracles is ſtill in the Church, &amp; that they haue beene abundantly wrought by the prouidence and power of God, in proofe of inuocation of Saints, &amp; aboue all of the glorious, and immaculate Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the <hi>Mother,</hi> the <hi>Daughter,</hi> and the <hi>Spouſe</hi> of God. There is no corner of the Chriſtian Catholike world, which is not full of them; but no tyme or place will be able more redily to riſe vp in iudgment againſt our Caluiniſts, then the mercy of this kind which God hath ſhewed, in honour of the ſacred Virgin, in theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dayes of ours, and euen in the next confines of our Country.</p>
               <p>For they are great numbers of moſt
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:19229:69"/>
certaine miracles which haue beene wrought in <hi>Brabant</hi> neere to <hi>Sichem,</hi> in a Chappell there deuoted to our B. Lady. The ſtoryes of the men, and women that haue receaued miraculous cure by the prayers of the B. Virgin, to whome they recommended themſelues, after exact, and ſeuere examination of the parties themſelues, of the perſons who knew them both before and after, of whole Colledges of Phiſitians &amp; Surgeons who had been formerly priuy to their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mityes, haue been proued and inrolled in the records of principall Cittyes. Yea &amp; the prouidence of God hath beene ſuch, as to make ſome one of theſe miracles, fall vpon the moſt known begging crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a whole Country,<note place="margin">Iohn Clement.</note> and of whome for his notorious deformity from his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, togeather with the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of his begging, all the ſtates of the Court, and Towne from the <hi>Archduke,</hi> and <hi>Infanta</hi> themſelues, to the meaneſt Tradeſman in <hi>Bruxells</hi> haue taken preciſe and perfect knowledge. There was I ſay a moſt impotent lame creature, who
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19229:69"/>
came deformed out of his mothers womb (and by occaſion thereof he was her death) whoſe knees by continuall clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to his breaſt, had made deep holes therein, whoſe leggs hung downe like a couple of drum-ſtickes, and who in his life had neuer made one paſe, but on his hands and hipps; this man, if he was not rather a monſter, they all ſaw when he was thus, and within a fortnight after (when he had beene miraculouſly, and in an inſtant cured by the prayers of the moſt gracious, and glorious Queene of heauen in that Chappell deuoted to her ſelfe) they ſaw him againe of a good ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of good proportion, of good health and ſtrength. And not only he was ſeen by them, but many of thoſe noble Engliſh Gentlemen who accompanyed the Earle of <hi>Hartford</hi> in his Embaſſage to that Court, did alſo ſee him, and ſpeake with him, and ſo may yet as many more as wil in <hi>Bruxells,</hi> where he continueth to this day, and his name is <hi>Iohn Clement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are wont to tell vs, I know not what of counterfaited miracles; and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19229:70"/>
I doubt not but diuers may haue beene counterfaited, and that euen in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes, as well as ours: but ſo far off is that from prouing that ther are no true miracles, as this would be a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous inference: The Kings hand is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited, therfore the King knoweth not how to write his name. It would rather hould on the otherſide, That becauſe ſometims either for pride, or profit ſome men are ſo wicked as to counterfeite mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, it is an euident ſigne that true mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles are wrought ſometymes, which no man would els be ſo ſottiſh as to counter faite, as no man would counterfeite the Kings hand if the King could not write.</p>
               <p>But howſoeuer, I aſſure the Reader in the word of a Chriſtian, and as in the preſence of God, who needeth not that any man ſhould tell a lye in his behalfe, and who will grieuouſly puniſh ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures whereſoeuer he findeth them, That the Church our Mother deteſteth all ſuch impotent, &amp; impure proceeding; and excommunicateth ſuch as concurre to the countenancing therof. And as by
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19229:70"/>
occaſion of the freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t miracles wrought lately in diuers parts of <hi>Brabant,</hi> there haue beene ſome found ſo wicked, as to the vttermoſt of their power, to make ſome very few falſe miracles paſſe for true ones; ſo (the prouidence of God working by the prudence of ſuch as haue the office of looking into thoſe matters) they haue beene detected, and grieuouſly puniſhed with whipping, hauing their tongues bored through, and being bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out their Countrey, as appeareth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon record in <hi>Bruxells.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in thoſe parts where miracles haue beene ſo frequently ſeen in theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tymes, the examination of the truth of them doth not (as God would haue it) lye there in the handes of Eccleſiaſticall perſons (whome the rage of hereſy is wont to charge with at leaſt conniuency in this point, if not colluſion) but the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome hath beene of many yeares, for the ſecular Magiſtrates to take knowledge thereof, who will not be pretended euen by our Aduerſaryes to be ſo partiall as thoſe others.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:19229:71"/>Now, for aſmuch as concerneth the truth, or falſhood of our miracles, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſhould be true that the moſt part of them are wholy falſe (which yet is no more poſſible then that the whole world except our Aduerſaryes, ſhould be all growne fooles or knaues) yet if all that were graunted, and that yet either they ſhall confeſſe, or it may be iuſtifyed that any one miracle was euer wrought by God vpon the prayers made to our B. Lady, with the inuocation of her ayde, (which truth the Diuell himſelfe is not ſo dogged, or ſo damned as to deny) one of theſe two thinges will follow, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Almighty God hath cooperated ſo far to a falſe doctrine, as to credit it by ſupernaturall meanes (which cannot be conceiued without blaſphemy) or els that the inuocation of Saints, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler of the immaculate and moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Virgin, cannot be impugned, or denyed without hereticall impiety.</p>
               <p>And if the infere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of one true miracle be ſo pregnant, what will that be which may be made from ſo many hundreds,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:19229:71"/>
which howſoeuer they be moſt euidently true, and moſt eaſily knowne to be ſo, we are the leſſe to wonder at the incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity of our Aduerſaryes, through the doctrine which is deliuered in the perſon of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and recorded by the Euangeliſt S. <hi>Luke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.</note> where he ſayth that the friends of <hi>Diues,</hi> who then ſuruiued, <hi>had Moyſes among them and the Prophets, and if they refuſed to heare them, neither would they beleeue though one ſhould riſe to them from the dead.</hi> By changing only the termes it falleth out to be the Caluiniſts caſe, who hauing the Church of Chriſt in ſuch a viſible, and vndoubted manner before their eyes, do yet conteſt, yea and deteſt the authority thereof; for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of which peruerſnes, the moſt vndoubted miracles which are wrought by God, in confirmation of the doctrine which ſhe teacheth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.</note> are denyed to be true by them who haue eyes, and ſee not, who haue harts, and vnderſtand not, but are vncapable of all inſtruction; and which dayly ripen towardes damnation if they free them not from ſinning thus againſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:19229:72"/>
their conſcience, as the Iewes did not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the infinite miracles of our Sauiour Chriſt, which yet they would neuer be drawn to acknowledge but did impute thoſe arguments of his Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency either to colluſion with the parties who were cured, or to the vſe of Sorcery in caſting out ſome Diuels by the help of others.</p>
               <p>The corporall miracles wrought by God at the interceſſion of our B Lady are in a manner innumerable; yet are they few in compariſon of the ſpirituall miracles, which are dayly ſeene by the conuerſion of ſoules to Gods ſeruice, through the prayers of the Mother of God and vs. It is moſt certainely true and knowne to be ſo, that innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinners haue beene reduced to pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance before their death, to which grace they were neuer knowne to haue had any other diſpoſition, but by ſome tendernes of deuotion, though imperfect, which in their harts they euer carryed to our B. Lady. Innumerable they are who only comming into thoſe Sanctuaryes, where
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:19229:72"/>
God hath been moſt honoured in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion borne to his B Mother (as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly in that holy houſe of <hi>Loretto</hi>) and there hauing recommended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (though vnworthily inough) to our B Lady, they haue yet found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſometymes ſtrocken downe with the horrible feare of Gods iudgmentes, ſometymes raiſed vp with an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary hope of mercy ſometymes ſtrocken through with reflecting vpon the vglines and baſenes of ſinne as that in the ſame very inſtant they haue reſolued vpon a whole change of their liues, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any longer tyme then of ſo many minutes as might conduct them, and caſt them at the feet of a Ghoſtly Father, for the making of entire Reſtitutions, the quitting of ſenſuall conuerſations, the depoſing of mortall or rather immortall emnityes, and the performing of ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heroicall, and high acts of mind; which as they cannot be purchaſed but by the infinite merit of Chriſts paſſion, ſo that is neuer more comfortable, and effectually applyed, then by the meanes
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:19229:73"/>
of our B. Ladyes ſacred protection, and deare prayers. And although the acts &amp; records of theſe ſpirituall miracles be not ſo well kept in parchment as are the corporall; yet I appeale to the conſcience of obſeruing and curious Catholikes, which cannot faile to beare witnes with me of this truth, that the bowels of our B. Ladyes compaſſion do by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God extend themſelues as much more frequently to the ſtrang cure of ſoules then of bodyes, as the body is leſſe conſiderable then the ſoule: in ſo much as a whole Citty in <hi>Italy</hi> hath been found vpon ſome deuotion which it hath taken to our B. Lady,<note place="margin">Luca.</note> to make within the ſpace of a few years ſuch a totall change from vice to vertue and piety, as there is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene a diſorderly Tauerne, and a deuout Church.</p>
               <p>In the ſame manner if the State of <hi>Brabant,</hi> and the Prouinces adioyning (for as much as concerneth Morality or Religion) be conſidered, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence well weighed concerning the great example of vertue, and manners, and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:19229:73"/>
the integrity of Fayth, to the contrary in both theſe reſpects, whereby thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes were indangered vntill the miracles (wrought by the interceſſion of our B. Lady, neere <hi>Sichem,</hi> and other places) made them caſt a quicker eye of humble deuotion towardes her: If it be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red I ſay, how all the ſtates of people are admirably improued ſince that tyme, all ſuch, as togeather with common ſenſe haue not the poyſon of preiudicate paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their harts, and heades, will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the powerfull and gracious hand of our B. Lady in this heauenly worke, and will not faile to eſteeme it for a ſpirituall miracle.</p>
               <p>It is tyme that I grow to a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and I will procure to tye it vp in as ſtraite a compaſſe as I can. I haue endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to ſhew, how highly our B. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is honoured by the teſtimony of holy Scripture, and to remoue ſuch obiections as her Aduerſaryes take from thence, whereby to do her diſparagement. I haue ſhewed her Genealogy, her Beauty, her perfection of vertue which filled the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:19229:74"/>
whole world with heroicall actions. I haue accompanyed that diſcourſe, with ſhewing how the whole Church hath imployed it ſelfe in her deuotion, &amp; how the ancient, moſt holy, and moſt learned Fathers haue endeauoured to excell one another in piety towardes her, wherein the Sectaryes of our tyme are as wholly vnlike them as in other thinges. I haue offered to the Readers conſideration the authority both of corporall, and ſpiritual miracles, wherby Almighty God hath as it were laboriouſly concurred, in this age of ours, towardes the planting of a Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phey to our B. Lady in the harts of all men. Happy are they who meane to take occaſion heereby, either to begin, or to increaſe in a moſt reuerend, and filiall affection towardes her: and moſt happy ſhould I accompt my ſelfe, if the little which I haue beene able to ſay, or doe, might cauſe ſome few mites, after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this of myne, to be caſt into the rich Treaſury of her Prayſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:19229:74"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <p>BVT it is to be conſidered (for now I chiefly ſpeake to my fellow-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes) that the knowledge of our B. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes greatnes, and goodnes muſt not go for a ſpeculatiue, but for a practical kind of knowledge, becauſe it doth <hi>excitare animum ad amorem,</hi> excite the mind of man to loue, as alſo it muſt be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that true loue is not idle, but opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and doth ſhew it ſelfe by a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the will towardes that of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie beloued. And therfore as in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this diſcourſe, I moued my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract friendſhip with the Queen of Angells (for as her Humility holp to make her ſo, ſo her greatnes maketh her not yet the leſſe humble, or depriueth her of vouchſafing to contract an indiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble league of amity with the meaneſt of thoſe ſoules, for which the Son of God and her was pleaſed to dye) ſo now in the end of it, I can aduiſe nothing more to purpoſe, then that the law of true friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:19229:75"/>
towardes her may be performed, which is <hi>idem velle,</hi> and <hi>idem nolle,</hi> to will, and not will the ſame thinge. We haue already ſeene how ſhe ſtood affected in this life, al which was ſpent with extrem ioy of hart in Pouerty, Chaſtity, Recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, Mortification, Humility, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Charity. The thinges that ſhe cared not for, were the contrary of all thoſe vertues, &amp; now that ſhe is aſſumed both in body and ſoule, into that height of glory which exceedeth the capacity of all the reſt of Creatures put togeather, what other thing can ſhe will, in reſpect of her ſelfe, but the good Will of God; and what other thing can ſhe wil concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs, but that euery one in his ſeueral calling ſhould adore with her the ſame Will of God, &amp; procure to ariue at that iourneys end, by thoſe wayes which ſhe hath traced out for our wandring ſteps-</p>
               <p>It will not become me to deliuer any opinion, or to giue any aduiſe of the particuler deuotions, which men ſhould do wel to nouriſh in themſelues, towards this B. Lady. The natures, &amp; affections,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:19229:75"/>
and ſpirits of men are different, and it would be hard for a wiſer man then my ſelfe to chance faire, in the giuing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch addreſſe. The moſt generally imbraced deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which are performed to her be two. The former whereof is the reciting of the Roſary, which was caſt into that method by that great Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch <hi>S. Dominicke,</hi> the Founder of a moſt floriſhing Order. It is a moſt excellent kind of prayer, compounded both of mentall &amp; vocall. The Vocall conſiſting all of <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and <hi>Aue Maria's</hi> (which are alſo of that kind the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent prayers) and the Mentall part, hauing no leſſe matter for the ſubiect, then all the principall Myſteryes of our B. Sauiours incomprehenſible Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his moſt admirable life, his moſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous Paſſion, and moſt glorious Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and Aſcenſion.</p>
               <p>The other is of the <hi>Sodality</hi> of our B. Lady, ſo called by the ſociety which men haue one with another, in doing her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſeruice, and conſequently in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing happy by her aſſiſtance. It was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:19229:76"/>
inſtituted in remembrance of her moſt glorious <hi>Aſſumption.</hi> The practiſe thereof conſiſteth in mens reſoluing at their firſt entrance, vpon a renouation of their life, by making then a generall confeſſion, and by growing afterwardes in ſpirit through the frequenting of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments at certaine tymes, vnder the happy conduct and direction of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Society of <hi>Ieſus.</hi> And in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler, beſides the faſting vpon the eues of all our B. Ladyes feaſts, and the recy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of thoſe Pſalmes, and Prayers euery day whereof her Office is compoſed, it doth recommend a carefull and dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the conſcience, eſpecially for the getting and keeping of that puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which maketh the ſoule ſo gratefull in the ſight of God. They meet togeather at leaſt once a weeke, and then they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue light and help towards the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming both of that which hath beene ſayd already, as alſo for the exerciſing of ſuch workes of charity, whether they be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall or ſpirituall, as in their ſeuerall callinges they can reach vnto, namely
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:19229:76"/>
viſiting the ſicke, burying of the dead, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſing of priſoners, reconciling of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the like. And both to this <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dality,</hi> and to that other company of the Roſary, great Indulgences are applyed by the Sea Apoſtolike, and the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers aſwell of priuiledge as obligation, may eaſily be learnt, by ſuch as will, of their Ghoſtly Father.</p>
               <p>As for priuate deuotions ſome exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe themſelues in ſaying their Beades, in contemplation of the moſt holy actions of our B. Lady: Others ſay the holy Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce before mentioned, which the Church hath compoſed in her prayſe of Pſalmes, and Leſſons taken out of Holy Scripture for that purpoſe: Others recite her Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes, wherby ſhe is both highly prayſed, and by her principall attributes prayed vnto: Some faſt vpon the Saturday, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that day is particulerly dedicated to her ſeruice: Some take a diſcipline or weare a haircloth in vnion of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Martyrdome that ſhe ſuffered: Some make a vow of Chaſtity in conformity with her more then Angelicall puri y:
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:19229:77"/>
And ſome there be who giue often almes for her ſake with as good a will as if it were for the reliefe of her wonted pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>Theſe deuotions with many others are performed by good Chriſtians in the Catholike Church, wherwith to honour the Mother of God. Let euery man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in that, wherin he findeth himſelfe moſt to profit; for there is none of them which procureth not, to the reuerend v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers thereof, extraordinary comforts in this life, and which layeth not vp incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable rewards for the next. I only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire leaue, that I may expreſſe a poore thought of myne. It is, that for as much as our B. Lady hath the office of aſſiſting our ſoules when they are to depart out of this life (as doth euidently appeare by the practiſe of the Church which comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth her children to call dayly &amp; hourely vpon her for that purpoſe) I thinke it would be profitable, and nothing paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (for ſuch as haue the means) to giue dayly (by way of addition to their other deuotions) ſome little almes, though it
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:19229:77"/>
were but a penny (or euen leſſe rather then nothing, where leſſe coyne is to be found) in honour of the immaculate Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of our B. Lady, to which miſery Engliſh Catholiks haue reaſon to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly deuoted (becauſe in <hi>England</hi> it grew ſooneſt to be moſt declared) &amp; this to be offered to the end that ſhe may be pleaſed in particuler manner to aſſiſt, &amp; comfort their ſoules in that fearefull paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</p>
               <p>Such as will not charge their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moryes to call this to mind, or will not trouble their handes in diſpoſing of ſo miſerable an almes, ſhall do wel (though yet leſſe well) in commanding ſome very honeſt ſeruant to do that duty; but with this further caution, that if by negligence the almes of one day ſhould be forgotten, the next day it muſt not faile to be doubled; and they who are ſo poore as to want this meanes, whether they be Religious perſons or ſecular may inſteed of that litle almes make ſome litle prayer in honour of our B Lady, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the ſame Myſtery, and in
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:19229:78"/>
expectation of the ſame benefite: I haue not heard of a ſhorter, or a ſweeter prayer then this which was vſed by that holy Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury S. Anſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lme,</hi> and may in this caſe be thrice repeated, <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Domine Ieſu, parce ſeruo Matris tuae. Amen.</hi> O deare Lord Ieſus, forgiue the ſeruant of thy Mother. Amen. And I haue alſo knowne this other, vſed by ſome great ſeruants of God, and with admirable ſucceſſe in their neceſſityes, <hi>Maria Ieſu, ſponſa Ioſeph, per immaculata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Conceptionem tuam, &amp; puriſsimam Virginitatem tuam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuua me.</hi> O Mary the Mother of Ieſu, &amp; the ſpouſe of Ioſeph, by thy immaculate conception: and thy pure virginity I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to aſſiſt me. For as we cannot better expreſſe our loue to Chriſt our Lord, then by giuing honour to our B. Lady; ſo neither can we more obligingly honour her, then by reuerently remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring her only Sonne, and her deare Spouſe S. <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> as heere is done.</p>
               <p>But to make either of theſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with good hope of grace, a man muſt indeed be her <hi>Seruant,</hi> as is expreſſed in
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:19229:78"/>
the former of them; and though I do but point out the other particuler deuotion, without daring to aduiſe in the election, I muſt needes aduenture to recommend two generall conſiderations, wherof the one will facilitate the other. The firſt of them may be, to accuſtome ones ſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an eaſy, and liberall manner, and without ouer paineful reflection, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in the eyes of his mind, the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall preſence of our B. Lady, &amp; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Nobility, and Solidity, togeather with the extreme Facility wherewith ſhe performed all her actions: and the ſecond to breed, and cheriſh a kind of tender, &amp; ſweet affection to her name, to her prayſe to her feſtiuityes, to her deuoted ſeruants, and to be frequent in giuing God entiere thankes for the infinite graces which he imparted to her, and wherewith ſhe did ſo diuinely cooperate.</p>
               <p>This practiſe of this deuotion, need not diſtract any man from others, it need not diſplace his temporal buſines, the vſe of it rather may be to fill vp vacant tyms; and I know no cauſe, why a man may
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:19229:79"/>
not hope from hence to find ſuch helpes, as may ſerue to make him runne with pleaſure through the cariere of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, and diſtaſtfull life. For whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer be the authour of this conceipt, to me it ſeemeth no ill one: That as the ſtrength of a ſpiritual mans life muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to him from the bloud and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Paſſion of our B. Sauiour: ſo his comfort, and delight in God is the vſuall effect of the ſacred milke, and the contemplation of the life of our B. Lady. Of whoſe goodnes to mankind let vs heare and ponder what S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth, <hi>Sileat miſericordiam tuam Virgo beata &amp;c.</hi> Let him,<note place="margin">Bernard. hom. <hi>4.</hi> ſuper miſſus eſt</note> O bleſſed Virgin, conceale the prayſes of thy mercy <hi>(if any ſuch there be)</hi> who can remember that thou didſt euer fayle him, when he inuoked thyne ayde in his neceſſity; but as for vs thy poore ſeruants, when we conſider the reſt of thy vertues, we reioyce rather in reſpect of thee; but in this of thy mercy we are glad in regard of our ſelues. We prayſe thy Virginity, we admire thy Humility, but yet thy Mercy is to vs of a ſweet taſt.
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:19229:79"/>
We imbrace thy Mercy more dearely, we remember it more frequently, and we inuoke it more feruently. Thus he. And whoſoeuer ſhall conſider the life of Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> one of the moſt deuout ſeruants of our B. Lady that ſhe euer had, and ſee how full it was on the one ſide of extrem auſterity, &amp; ſicknes, &amp; yet on the other how his ſoule did euen regorge againe with the exceſſe, and ſatiety of ſpirituall comfort, will eaſily find in the paſſages of it, that our B. Lady is a Miſtreſſe well worth the ſeruing, and that ſhe did caſt ſome ſuch ingredient into the bundle of myrrh, that S. <hi>Bernard</hi> would needs lay next his heart, as made him euen languiſh and halfe dye with loue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <p>HOvv fit then it were, that ſince the Caluiniſts will not follow the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of this moſt holy Father, in giuing high honour to our B. Lady, they ſhould at leaſt heare the voyce of the very <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans</hi> themſelues, who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:19229:80"/>
that they beleeue not our B. Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to haue been the Sonne of God, but only that he was an holy man, and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Prophet, yet after the rate of the Mother of ſuch a Prophet, they fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely yield ſo high honour to our B Lady, and they mention her purity and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency vpon al occaſions with ſuch tender and entiere reſpect, as no Caluiniſt in the whole world hath beene euer knowne to do. For howſoeuer when a Catholike ſhall ioyne iſſue with a Caluiniſt in the hearing of moderate men of his own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, concerning the excellencyes of our Lady, he wil be drawn to ſay (though duly inough) that ſhe was a moſt happy creature, a bleſſed Virgin, and in fine our Sauiours Mother: yet as it is euident that they do not penetrate and ponder the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable dignity which the being of his Mother doth inuolue; ſo they are neuer carryed to do her honour with any wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnes and cheerefullnes, but only as it were by conſtraint, and violence. Some of them wil prayſe her faintly, when they ſee that they muſt diſpraiſe themſelues if
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:19229:80"/>
they do it not; but otherwiſe if a man leaue them to the worke of Nature, and of the principles which indeed they hold concerning her, a man may liue amongſt them ſo many yeares as to make euen <hi>Matthuſalem</hi> ſeeme yong, before he find them once enter voluntarily into any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuous ſpeach in honour of her, <hi>expro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the proofe heere of I might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to euery mans particuler experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and to the conſcience of my Reader at large. But to ſhew it yet better, as vpon Record, let it be conſidered, that ſince Caluiniſme was ſet on foot, there hath not beene (for ought that euer I could learne) any one diſcourſe or book writen by any one of that profeſſion in honour, and admiration of this B. Virgin, either to publiſh her prerogatiues, or to reflect vpon her vertues, or to make contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations vpon her moſt holy and happy actions; and much leſſe to exhort the world to imitate that moſt excellent O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall of piety, which ſhe did ſet before vs by her life and conuerſation. Nay in
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:19229:81"/>
all my dayes I haue not beene able to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that euer they beſtowed ſo much as one expreſſe ſermon in honour of her, wherein howſoeuer they might (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their erroneous beliefe) haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credited the doctrine of her inuocation, yet withall they might at leaſt haue larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribed, &amp; praiſed her vertues, they might haue magnifyed her prerogatiues, they might haue perſwaded men to the imitation of her examples, if in their harts they had proſecuted her with true affection and admiration.</p>
               <p>For could this omiſſion peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture come from want of matter worthy to be obſerued in the B. Virgin? Or be theſe thinges but fables which haue been brought out of Scripture, and layd heere before your eyes? No. But the true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, that there is ſomething in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of etrour, which is not compatible with a true, and tender, and filiall reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of affection to the ſacred Virgin, which maketh them all carry a kind of tooth towardes her: ſome grinne, and ſhew it, others beare it with more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:19229:81"/>
of modeſty, but with no leſſe malice, and generally all of them haue ſome kind of antipathy (whereof ſome of themſelues do ſcarſe know the roote) againſt her. By whome although their ſoules may be aſſiſted and fauoured as ſoone, and ſometymes before they haue the grace to deſire ſo great a bleſſing; yet their opinions are hated by her who brought him forth, that hath beene the deſtruction of all former, and will be ſo of all future hereſyes. And it ſhould ſeem that the enemy of mankind finding the wound to be ſo deadly which he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued in great part by her meanes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth to reuenge himſelf in a particuler manner, by arming ſuch as he hath drawn into errour, towardes an auerſion from her.</p>
               <p>For whereas Catholikes are taught to know that they do not honour her too much in giuing her whatſoeuer a pure creature is capable of, and in beleeuing her to haue been preſerued by the ſpeciall prerogatiue of Almighty God, from thoſe ſhames, and ſinnes to which all the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:19229:82"/>
reſt of mankind is ſubiect; and euen the <hi>Mahometans</hi> though they do not ſo much as beleeue in the diuinity of our Sauiour Chriſt, yet do they admire, and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy her out of the very hiſtoricall relation that they haue of her life: Theſe other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaryes of Gods Truth, and Church (whereof they once were, though now they are departed from thence) ſuch as are only Iewes, and Heretikes be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two races of men, that can be found vnder the cope of heauen (for the Pagans know little of her) to haue lift vp their hands, and opened their mouths to the reproach and blaſphemy of this ſacred, and immaculate Virgin.</p>
               <p>But I would beſeech them euen by the bowells of Chriſt Ieſus our Lord (if they care indeed for thoſe bowells of his, who carry no more reuerence to theſe bowels of hers which brought him forth) that if they will not be as pious towardes her as they ought, they will at leaſt not be ſo dangerouſly imprudent as they are to themſelues. Let them take heed how they continue to arme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues towards
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:19229:82"/>
the aſſault of this Tower of ſtrength:<note place="margin">Hier. in Ierem. <hi>31.</hi> &amp; Zach. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> Chriſt himſelfe is the corner ſtone, and our B. Lady is the Quarry, or rather the Mine of ſpotles marble, out of which he would be taken, without the help of any other handes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe of the Holy Ghoſt. Our Sauiour hath ſayd of himſelfe, in the ſimilitude of this ſtone,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>He that ſtumbleth vpon it ſhall fall, and he vpon whom the ſtone falleth, ſhallbe driuen to powder:</hi> which howſoeuer it be principally, &amp; litterally true of him, in regard of them who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him firſt, and afterward prouoke him to take vengeance of them for their other ſinnes; yet experience telleth vs, that it carryeth ſome proportion towards ſuch others as oppoſe themſelues, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the honour of our B. Lady, who haue come, after liues led in extreme ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity of mind and miſery, to end wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly in deſpayre.</p>
               <p>I remit my ſelfe to good obſeruers, whether ſome ſuch as hauing beene Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, and comming after to looſe (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with their Religion) the very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation both of Chriſtianity, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:19229:83"/>
honeſty, haue not beene formerly knowne to carry a ſecret, and ſubtile ſpite to the honour of our Lady: and on the other ſide, I could for a need name ſome Caluiniſts, who being in a faire way to obtaine both temporall, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicity by finding themſelues to be moued internally to grow into ſome ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes of deuotion towards our B. Lady, vpon an expreſſe reſiſtance of thoſe good motions, and a fortifying themſelues in the contrary purpoſe, haue fallen into ſuch pouerty, and miſery, and diſreputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and confuſion, as that, at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant wherein now I ſpeake, they are growne to be the very By-wordes, and Prouerbs of the places wherein they liue.</p>
               <p>And as for ſuch as are, and by the grace of God are to continue of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, whether they be of England, or any other Countrey (as there is a lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the natures, and inclinations of men) and ſome euen amongſt vs are much more deuoted to our B. Lady then ſome others (yet ſo that none of vs doe
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:19229:83"/>
not take ioy in giuing her gladly all her rights, none of vs that do not extoll her, none of vs that do not deſire her prayers, that God Almighty may be mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs through Chriſt our Lord:) ſo I can proteſt, as in the diuine preſence, that whoſoeuer they be amongſt vs, that are, and appeare to be the moſt tenderly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted towards the honouring, and louing of this ſacred Virgin, are alſo found to be the men who in other reſpects deſerue to be acknowledged as moſt eminent in all kind of Angelicall vertue. So that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion to her, is not only a diſtinct ſigne between good and bad, that is, between Catholikes and no Catholikes, but it is in like manner a ſigne of difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene good, and better, that is between ordinary Catholikes and ſuch others, as are the beſt amongſt vs. And though ſome may haue their mouths and pens ful of her prayſes, whileſt their harts are voyde of her vertues (and I beſeech Ieſus from my very ſoule that my ſelfe may not be found the foremoſt of that ranke) yet in the generality, that proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which I
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:19229:84"/>
firſt deliuered is moſt certainely true.</p>
               <p>Towards the further building vp of her greatnes, in the iudgment of any reaſonable man, I will deſire him yet to let one only other ſtone be added, by remembring that Parable of the <hi>Penny,</hi> which was giuen for the dayes worke in the Ghoſpell, and by conſidering that ſpeach of our Sauiour which he vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe enuious old labourers: <hi>Is it not lawfull for me to do what I will with my owne?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.</note> and, <hi>Is your eye therfore euill becauſe I am good?</hi> For heereby he may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that Almighty God is not any bodyes <hi>Ward,</hi> that he diſpoſeth of his treaſures according to the latitude of his owne heart; and that he would haue the world rather enlarge it ſelfe towards the admiration of his vnſpeakable bounty, powred forth vpon his creatures, then be accuſtomed, through certaine mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and enuious little thoughts, to paint him out, as if he were ſome miſerable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Prince, that were in feare of being depoſed, if he ſhould raiſe his fauorits to any extraordinary degree of greatnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:19229:84"/>But the caſe ſtandeth far otherwiſe; for as God is infinite in all thinges, ſo is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e moſt eminently infinite in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and effuſion of himſelfe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon all ſuch ſoules as do nobly ſerue him, and eſpecially ſuch as do it with greateſt perfection, and are enabled by him to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, and diſcharge the higheſt fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. The Patriarkes were made won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully fit for their offices, the Apoſtles for theirs, the Precurſour of Chriſt for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his, his ſuppoſed Father <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> (who really was his conductour, guide, &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour) for his. And ſo the immacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, pure, moſt gracious, and moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mother of God, was aboue all made moſt fit for hers. But we may firſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend a great deale lower, &amp; yet not looſe the ſight of her greatnes. For there is not the meaneſt of vs all who ſhall not at the day of iudgment, if he dye in the ſtate of Grace, haue a body which ſhall then be knit to the Soule, more glorious then the Sunne, as impaſſible as the Angells, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably more ſubtile then lightning; and we cannot now ſo eaſily tranſlate a
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:19229:85"/>
thought from one end of the world to another, as then we ſhallbe able to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port our ſelues, as it were in an inſtant. We ſhall be immortall, we ſhallbe Heires of the kingdome of heauen, we ſhallbe Coheirs with Chriſt, and if he be a King, we ſhall all be alſo kings of heauen. Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in poſſeſſing of that kingdome doth not weaken, or leſſen the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of dominion, as it would do heere on earth: but it doth highly beautify and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it through the vnion of will, which reigneth in thoſe happy ſoules.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour ſpeaking to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and diſciples, and in their perſons to ſuch as would keep his commandments, entreth ſo far by words of tendernes as to deſpoyle them of ſeruitude, and to cloath them with the precious robes of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Vos amici mei eſtis &amp;c.</hi> as if he had ſayd, No longer will I accompt you now my ſeruants, but I will aduance you to the ranke of being my friendes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 13.</note> He had formerly auowed to the Apoſtles, that he diſpoſed of his kingdome to their vſe as his Father had diſpoſed thereof to his,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:19229:85"/>
Againe he aſſumeth them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.</note> that they who had left all, and followed him, ſhould ſit vpon twelue ſeats, and iudge the twelue Tribes of Iſraell, whereby the whole world is ſignifyed.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> And S. <hi>Paul</hi> taketh vpon him to warrant, that Chriſtians ſhall iudge euen very Angells at the laſt day. Now this Iudicature is an act, and exerciſe of a Kings royalty, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why earthly Kings do it not in their own perſon, is becauſe, either they want knowledge, or induſtry, or for that they cannot be in ſo many places in ſo ſhort a tyme as were conuenient: but none of theſe thinges can be ſayd of Chriſt, and therefore when he maketh his Apoſtles iudges, it is not to excuſe himſelfe, but to impart to them a kind of ſupreme ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and authority ouer the reſt his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>We ſee then the vnſpeakable bounty of Almighty God towards all ſuch as are to prayſe and ſerue him in the Court of heauen for all eternity; we ſee that ſome of vs ſhall iudge the world; That we ſhal iudge Angells; That we ſhall be Kings of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:19229:86"/>
heauen, heires to God, and coheirs with Chriſt; yea and, That euen in this life ſuch as keep his Commandements are already intituled by the name of <hi>Friends,</hi> or <hi>Fauorits</hi> of Chriſt Ieſus. And is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any Chriſtian to haue ſo little, and ſo poore a ſoule, as to thinke that the Mother of God is not to be honoured in a manner much ſuperiour to all this? Is it poſſible that ſince God doth not make Officers as earthly Kings make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (who take ſuch as they find, whether they be good or bad, &amp; ſo they continue) but he firſt maketh men fit for the places to which he calleth them? Is it poſſible, ſince the dignity of the Mother of God, doth vnſpeakably exceed the dignity of Patriarchs, Prophets, Precurſours, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and whatſoeuer imployment wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a pure creature is capable, that any man ſhould be ſo voyd of natural Logick as not to draw an argument from the leſſe to the greater: That if the leſſe hath much excellency, the greater hath much more? Or rather that he ſhould haue ſo little wit, or common ſenſe, as not to ſee,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:19229:86"/>
That as in numbers the more do exceed the fewer, ſo our B. Lady doth outſtrip all the other creatures of God in greatnes in grace, in authority, and in Maieſty.</p>
               <p>Let not therefore our Aduerſaryes, (for ſo in reſpect of their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s they wil needs deſerue to be called) deceaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.<note place="margin">Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> They may thinke it is zeale which they haue in abaſing the honour of our B, Lady, whereas indeed it is but igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the moſt innocent of them, and in others either hypocriſy, or enuy.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them who ſaw how <hi>Caiphas</hi> did in that ſolemne aſſembly of Prieſts, &amp; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> caſt vp his eyes to Heauen, and rend his Pontificall gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; exclaime with horrour againſt Chriſt himſelfe, affirming that he had blaſphemed, did doubtles iudge by the appearance of it, that the High Prieſt had ſome reaſon. And ſome couetous, or malicious Iew, who had beene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, when <hi>Iudas</hi> cenſured the matchles enamoured Penitent of our Lord S. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> (as waſting that precious oyntment vpon his head, and crying
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:19229:87"/>
out that it ſhould rather haue beene im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed vpon the poore) would as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, &amp; perhaps with as much reaſon, haue giuen his voyce with <hi>Iudas</hi> againſt Chriſt, as theſe men do eagerly maligne and of whome I haue ſeene ſome grow pale, and euen ſicke through the rage of enuy, when they obſerue how curious, and coſtly we are content to be in our deſire, not only to anoynt as it were, and adorne the head of this ſacred Virgin with our prayſes, but to caſt our ſelues at her pure feet by our Inuocations. Therefore heere the Prouerbe may well come in, <hi>All is not gould that gliſtereth;</hi> and that twinckling Brother, who in the zeale he pretendeth to carry to Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, doth ſecretly repine and ſnarle at that of our Bleſſed Lady, inſteed of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for himſelfe a Crowne in heauen, may then be hammering out eternall chaynes for his ſoule in Hell. This may ſerue to them for a word of aduice, that at leaſt they may vſe modeſty in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if they will not be drawne to vſe pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:19229:87"/>But we Catholikes are farre from needing ſuch aduice as this, who know our dutyes towardes the bleſſed Mother of Almighty God, and who are not, in this reſpect, to be drawn from leſſe wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, but to be incouraged towardes a faſter going. I doe therefore preſume to caſt my ſelfe, with moſt entiere venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at thy pure feet, O thou moſt gracious, and moſt triumphantly glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene of Heauen, the Mother of my Sauiour, &amp; my God, the ſumme and top of all excellency, and perfection vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. I beſeech thee by thoſe thy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate bowells of mercy which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, and incloſed the Lord of life by thoſe ſacred breſts which gaue him ſucke and fed him towardes the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Redemption, looke downe vpon vs with thoſe eyes, which ſince they be thyne, cannot chooſe but be of extreme compaſſion. Looke not only v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs but vpon thoſe others alſo whom before I mentioned who howſoeuer they be our Brethren according to the fleſh, yet they will needes make themſelues
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:19229:88"/>
ſtrangers from the Couenant of thy Sonne, rightly vnderſtood, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly from doing thee the honour that belongs to his moſt worthy, and moſt ſacred Mother,
<q>Tros, Tyrius<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tibi nullo diſcrimine —</q>
Intercede for vs who are now begging thy aſſiſtance; intercede for them, who do not ſo, to the end that they may haue the grace to do it. <hi>Tota pulchra es amica mea, &amp; macula non eſt in te:</hi> Thou art all faire, and ſweet, thou waſt as entierely immaculate in thy Conception, as in thy Aſſumption. There was neuer any ſinne in thee, or any ſad aſpect towardes vs. Then let me reſort to that notion of Friendſhip, wherewith I began this diſcourſe, which I yet am making in thy honour.</p>
               <p>We Catholiks are thy humble, &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious ſeruants, and <hi>Serui</hi> are <hi>humiles amici;</hi> a kind of humble friendes we are in being thy ſeruants: nor wilt thou diſdaine to know vs by the name of Friends ſince Chriſt himſelfe thy Sonne our Sauiour vouchſafed to call, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:19229:88"/>
them his friends, that follow his directions, as hath beene ſayd. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to vs therefore, all thoſe parts of Friendſhip, and protection, which thy State of Glory may affoard, and our State of miſery doth need; and obtaine Grace for vs, that we may neuer fayle of Fayth, and loyalty towardes thee. Thou art the Woman who wert not only cloathed by the Sunne, but thou didſt alſo cloath the Sunne of Iuſtice, whileſt thy immaculate fleſh, and bloud was imparted to the Sonne of thy womb. By him we beg of thee, that thou wilt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede for vs to him, that we may liue in his feare, and dye in his fauour: and that as heere we haue the comfort to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy thee, as our chiefe Mediatrix of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion towards him; ſo with thee &amp; at thy feet, we may prayſe, and glorify him in al eternity, as our only Mediatour of Redemption.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19229:89"/>
            <head>A PRAYER FOR THE LOVE OF GOD, Made in Contemplation of the Paſſion of Chriſt our Sauiour.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>EVEN by the miſt of ſighes that ouergrew</l>
               <l>Thy ſacred face, which was deſignd to be</l>
               <l>The ſpotles mirrour, where al ſouls might view</l>
               <l>The quinteſſence of their felicity:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Eu'n by the Sea of thoſe ſalte teares, wherein</l>
               <l>Thyne eyes like Sunnes did ſet, whoſe only ſight</l>
               <l>Was able to haue made eu'n Hell begin</l>
               <l>To be competitour, with Heau'n, for light:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:19229:90"/>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Eu'n by the ſtorme of bloudy hayle, which fell</l>
               <l>From thy faint limmes, and dide the palid ground</l>
               <l>With Rubies of the Rocke, diſſolued ſo well</l>
               <l>By fire of Loue, as doth mans ſkill confound:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>By that fierce agony, that deep diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>That deſolation, and that bitter woe,</l>
               <l>That feare, that care, that hart-ſicke heauines,</l>
               <l>Which in the Garden did exhauſt thee ſo:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>(To thee no garden, but a bed of thornes,</l>
               <l>Whereon thou wert kept waking, to foreſee,</l>
               <l>And count (togeather with my ſinnes) thoſe ſcornes,</l>
               <l>And payns, which ſoone thou waſt to feele for me.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Deare Sauiour of my ſoule, by all the Story</l>
               <l>Of that nights worke (that night that had no end)</l>
               <l>Lend me thyne eare of mercy, for thy glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>For with what face can I my good pretend?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>They are not Thyne, my ſoueraigne Lord, but Thee</l>
               <l>Which I affect, with reſtles appetite:</l>
               <l>Thy creatures all (though Heauen included be)</l>
               <l>Fall ſhort of giuing me complete delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:19229:90"/>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Giue me thy ſelfe, and (if a begger may</l>
               <l>Become a chooſer) giue thy ſelfe iuſt ſo,</l>
               <l>As in thy Paſſion thou didſt go to pay</l>
               <l>That huge Rent-charge, which I, not Thou didſt owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>Thy Paſſion, which alone doth make me know,</l>
               <l>That as in other thinges thou doſt ſurpaſſe</l>
               <l>Angells and men: ſo heere thou doſt outgo</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe, as farre as Diamondes do Glaſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10.</head>
               <l>For thee, to do all that thou canſt conceaue,</l>
               <l>Is nothing, for thou art Omnipotent:</l>
               <l>But for a God to ſuffer, and bereaue</l>
               <l>Himſelfe of power, ſhewes power of more extent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>11.</head>
               <l>For thee to gouerne ſuch a world as this,</l>
               <l>Declares thy wiſedome to be infinite:</l>
               <l>But to reforme a world, that runnes amiſſe,</l>
               <l>By dying on a Croſſe, ſhewes more inſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>12.</head>
               <l>T'was matchles goodnes, that thou wouldſt inſpire</l>
               <l>This poore darke body, with a ſoule diuine:</l>
               <l>But t'was much greater, that thou didſt deſire</l>
               <l>To ſaue it, with ſuch preiudice of thyne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:19229:91"/>
               <head>13.</head>
               <l>I graunt that all thy life a Paſſion was,</l>
               <l>And as it were one act of ſuffering payne;</l>
               <l>In the firſt turne of thy liues houre-glaſſe,</l>
               <l>I thinke thou didſt, &amp; know thou mightſt complaine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>14.</head>
               <l>Of bitter cold, and ſo great pouerty,</l>
               <l>As that in a whole world, which thou haſt framd,</l>
               <l>Eu'n for thy birth, there was but on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hole free,</l>
               <l>Lent thee by beaſts, of mans hard hart aſhamd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>15.</head>
               <l>From thence thou wentſt to Circumciſion,</l>
               <l>Learning as ſoone as borne, to ſhed thy bloud,</l>
               <l>Which firſt in drops, and then in ſhowrs ranne on</l>
               <l>So faſt, that at the Croſſe they made a floud.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>16.</head>
               <l>Then didſt thou in the Virgins boſome range</l>
               <l>To Aegypt, where thy beauty was dide blacke,</l>
               <l>And forcd (being growne at thy returne) didſt chang</l>
               <l>Thy mothers boſome, for thy Fathers backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>17.</head>
               <l>Thy reſt of life was full of care, and payne,</l>
               <l>Spent in obedience; thou diſt pray, and faſt,</l>
               <l>And preach, and trauaile, and receaue diſdayne</l>
               <l>From ſuch, as of thy bounty moſt did taſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:19229:91"/>
               <head>18.</head>
               <l>All this, I ſay, I graunt; but yet in this</l>
               <l>Thou hadſt ſome comforts, thou didſt heare &amp; ſee</l>
               <l>Thy ſacred Mother, that full Sea of bliſſe,</l>
               <l>And thyne Apoſtles, rude, yet louing thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <head>19.</head>
               <l>But in that later part of thy ſad age,</l>
               <l>Which we moſt properly thy Paſſion call;</l>
               <l>I ſee thou art ſold ouer, to the rage</l>
               <l>Of men moſt diuelliſhly tyrannicall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>20.</head>
               <l>There were few comforts, there few blubbered eyes,</l>
               <l>Few bleeding harts, few hands held vp on high</l>
               <l>In wonder of thoſe vaſt impietyes,</l>
               <l>Wherewith they chargd thy deare humanity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <head>21.</head>
               <l>How did they rend that venerable hayre</l>
               <l>From thoſe rich Temples of thy royall head;</l>
               <l>And thus vnſeeled the roofe, that they might teare</l>
               <l>The walles, ſo low as to be buryed?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>22.</head>
               <l>Theſe walls they firſt vnhung, and off did take</l>
               <l>Thy coate, which once thoſe virgin hands did frame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>But now their ſordid eyes, a prey did make</l>
               <l>Vpon thy nakednes. O ſinne, O ſhame!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:19229:92"/>
               <head>23.</head>
               <l>Prodigious ſinne in them, and ſhame to thee;</l>
               <l>Sauing that inſtantly thoſe ſcourges came,</l>
               <l>Which veyld thy fleſh, with an imbrodery</l>
               <l>So thicke, as then it did not ſeeme the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <head>24.</head>
               <l>A purple garment did they caſt with ſcorne</l>
               <l>About thy backe: t'was ſingle, but did grow</l>
               <l>Soone after double; for thy ſkinne was torne</l>
               <l>All off with it, and ſerud to line it ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <head>25.</head>
               <l>How did they, vnder colour of a Crowne</l>
               <l>Pierce thy fayre brow, the caſket of that brayne,</l>
               <l>Wherein the wiſedome eu'n of God came downe</l>
               <l>To ranſome vs from Hells eternall payne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <head>26.</head>
               <l>Then tooke they vp a Cane, more hate to ſhow,</l>
               <l>And often beating it about thy head</l>
               <l>With ſkillfull rage, each thorne, by euery blow,</l>
               <l>Made a new wound, and they all inward bled.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
               <head>27.</head>
               <l>Thy face ſo bruizd, and ſwolne, did make thyne eyes</l>
               <l>As hollow, as their harts that lookt on thee,</l>
               <l>Harts hugely hollow, that could ſo comprize</l>
               <l>The NON PLVS VLTRA of Iniquity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:19229:92"/>
               <head>28.</head>
               <l>Thyne Eyes I ſay, by ſwelling of thy face,</l>
               <l>Became the ſinckes of that foule houſe of thyne,</l>
               <l>Or like two durty valleyes, which haue place</l>
               <l>Between high Mountaines, where no Sunne can ſhine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <head>29.</head>
               <l>So gaſtly didſt thou looke, and let me ſay</l>
               <l>So vgly (for thou wouldſt deſerue that name)</l>
               <l>Their malice did find meanes, to make away</l>
               <l>The higheſt beauty, that eu'n God could frame,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
               <head>30.</head>
               <l>Yea thou a God in ſubſtance, yet in ſhow</l>
               <l>Wert ſcarſe a man, but rather a poore worme;</l>
               <l>A leaper, nay an vlcer, which did flow</l>
               <l>So faſt, as eu'n to drowne thee in that ſtorme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
               <head>31.</head>
               <l>Thy Noſe, thy ſacred Eares, were ſprings of bloud,</l>
               <l>Thy pores of ſweat, but that which paind thee more,</l>
               <l>Was thy deare cheeke, where ſtill engraued ſtood</l>
               <l>The kiſſe which Iudas gaue not long before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <head>32.</head>
               <l>Thy Beard, which neuer raſour durſt offend,</l>
               <l>Their hands and harts, more hard then hardeſt ſteele,</l>
               <l>And in ſome kind more ſharp, did ſtriue to rend:</l>
               <l>Nor is there torment which thou didſt not feele.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:19229:93"/>
               <head>33.</head>
               <l>For where the winged Angells vſe to build</l>
               <l>Their neaſt of pleaſure, and of ſweet repoſe,</l>
               <l>They all with filthy durt, and ſpittle fild,</l>
               <l>Incorporated to thy mouth with blows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
               <head>34.</head>
               <l>Thus dreſt, thou wert led forth, to act thy part</l>
               <l>Of bitter ſorrow; thus they hid thy backe</l>
               <l>Vnder that Croſſe, which did ſuch weight impart,</l>
               <l>And payne withall, as made thy ſhoulders cracke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <head>35.</head>
               <l>And as a building, which top-heauy is</l>
               <l>Vpon a weake foundation, ruines all;</l>
               <l>So thou thus feeble, with ſuch weight as this,</l>
               <l>Wert forc't to ſtumble oft, and oft to fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36">
               <head>36.</head>
               <l>There firſt thy Mother moſt diſconſolate,</l>
               <l>Thy Paſſion ſaw, and through her eyes downe came</l>
               <l>Thine Image to her ſoule, which did create</l>
               <l>Sharp ſwords of ſorrow, that tranſpierſt the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37">
               <head>37.</head>
               <l>But what ſhe felt in ſoule, did backe rebound</l>
               <l>Vpon thy body, and that ſeru'd alone</l>
               <l>Thy ſenſe with greater anguiſh to confound,</l>
               <l>For now one paine, to be two paynes was growne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:19229:93"/>
               <head>38.</head>
               <l>Paine which thou likd'ſt ſo well, as not t'indure</l>
               <l>That thoſe good women ſhould once pitty thee:</l>
               <l>Thou car'dſt for nothing, ſo thou mightſt be ſure</l>
               <l>By ſuffering much, to ſhew more loue to me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="39">
               <head>39.</head>
               <l>At laſt thou leftſt the Citty gates behind,</l>
               <l>And crawling vp (for then thou couldſt not goe)</l>
               <l>That hill which for thy murdering was deſignd,</l>
               <l>Againe they ſtript thee, though eu'n ſhame ſayd no.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
               <head>40.</head>
               <l>Thou didſt not then (becauſe thou wouldſt not)ſue</l>
               <l>A iuſt appeale, againſt their Tyranny,</l>
               <l>Whilſt they, being Captaines of the damned crew,</l>
               <l>Made haſt to hell, in ſpight of God and thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="41">
               <head>41.</head>
               <l>Thine Armes &amp; Thighes they rackt, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> find</l>
               <l>Thoſe holes, which bored through the Croſſe had byn:</l>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought they nayls, which with their points refind</l>
               <l>Wounded thy limmes, but kild their ſoules with ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42">
               <head>42.</head>
               <l>And ſo they reard that Croſſe, halfe diſcontent</l>
               <l>To haue thus freed thee from more crueltyes;</l>
               <l>But what they could they did, that is, torment</l>
               <l>Thy patient eares, with hideous blaſphemyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="43">
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:19229:94"/>
               <head>43.</head>
               <l>With ſome I could more eaſily diſpenſe;</l>
               <l>But for that wretch, that had no paralell,</l>
               <l>And gnaſhing cryed, Vab, come downe from thence,</l>
               <l>I curſe him to the loweſt pitt of Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44">
               <head>44.</head>
               <l>The Rocks could cleaue, the Temples veyle could rent,</l>
               <l>The Sunne could mourne, the very dead could riſe;</l>
               <l>Yet this enraged Impe would not relent,</l>
               <l>But heape high ſcornes, on thy deep miſeryes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="45">
               <head>45.</head>
               <l>Compard with this, thoſe other ſinnes were ſmall</l>
               <l>Of looſing Barabbas, of placing thee</l>
               <l>Betweene two theeues, that ſo thou mightſt haue al</l>
               <l>The markes of Honourable Infamy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="46">
               <head>46.</head>
               <l>Of giuing Vinagre, and Gall to drinke</l>
               <l>In thy laſt deadly thirſt, a ſauage part;</l>
               <l>That reacht thy mouth, but this foule ſcoffe, I thinke,</l>
               <l>Was that which battered, and did breake thy hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="47">
               <head>47.</head>
               <l>And thus deare Lord thou waſt content to dye;</l>
               <l>This is thy ſtory, which in bloud was pend;</l>
               <l>But I miſtooke the Authour, for t'was I,</l>
               <l>Not they, that brought thee to ſo ſad an end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="48">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:19229:94"/>
               <head>48.</head>
               <l>My ſinnes, my grieuous ſinnes, did cauſe all this,</l>
               <l>My ſeruing thee, not ill in outward ſhow,</l>
               <l>Whileſt yet in hart I ſinnd, was Iudas kiſſe</l>
               <l>Which treacherouſly betrayed, and ſold thee ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="49">
               <head>49.</head>
               <l>My Loathnes to amend, were ropes to bind</l>
               <l>Thy handes behind thy backe, my thoughts vnchaſt</l>
               <l>VVere ſpittle, which almoſt did ſtrike thee blind,</l>
               <l>By iſſuing from my feſtered ſoule ſo faſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="50">
               <head>50.</head>
               <l>My pride did make thy Crowne; my ſhameleſnes</l>
               <l>Pluckt off thy cloathes; the pamp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ring of my ſenſe</l>
               <l>Did vrge thoſe hands, which were ſo merciles,</l>
               <l>To ſcourge, and wound thee, with extreme offence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="51">
               <head>51.</head>
               <l>My hart of ſteele did yield thoſe rayles, that paſt</l>
               <l>Thy well deſeruing hands; my Gluttony</l>
               <l>Made thee of vinegar, and gall to taſt,</l>
               <l>And I blaſphem'd thee by myne Hereſy,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="52">
               <head>52.</head>
               <l>All this did I, and yet thou diedſt for me;</l>
               <l>And not content therewith, waſt pleaſ'd to adde</l>
               <l>Such circumſtances of thy Charity,</l>
               <l>As may confound, and make mans reaſon mad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="53">
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:19229:95"/>
               <head>53.</head>
               <l>For when thou waſt vpon thy hard death-bed,</l>
               <l>And ſhouldſt haue thought of making a new Hell</l>
               <l>For lewd mankind, thou wert by goodnes led</l>
               <l>To raine downe treaſures, which no tongue can tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="54">
               <head>54.</head>
               <l>Thou praydſt thy Father to forgiue my ſinne,</l>
               <l>As if ſuch malice were but want of wit;</l>
               <l>I ſee the eager thirſt thy ſoule was in,</l>
               <l>That myne might in thy glorious kingdome ſit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="55">
               <head>55.</head>
               <l>Thou taughtſt me, that I ought to hope for grace,</l>
               <l>By that good theefes example, who was brought</l>
               <l>From ſtate of ſinne to ſee Gods brighteſt face,</l>
               <l>Selling ſo cheape, what thou ſo deare hadſt bought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="56">
               <head>56.</head>
               <l>And, as if wickednes were good deſartes,</l>
               <l>Thou gau'ſt me, in the perſon of Saint Iohn,</l>
               <l>Thy ſacred Mother, the true Queene of Hartes,</l>
               <l>A royall ſtocke to build all bliſſe vpon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="57">
               <head>57.</head>
               <l>If then thou couldſt haue ſpok, thou wouldſt haue ſaid;</l>
               <l>Come ſoule, moſt ſinnefull, yet moſt deare to me:</l>
               <l>Deare, for ſo deare a price as I haue payd;</l>
               <l>And deare, for that deare Loue I beare to thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="58">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:19229:95"/>
               <head>58.</head>
               <l>Thou ſeeſt where I am plaſ't, then ponder well</l>
               <l>VVhat I haue done, and ſuffered for thy ſake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>I who am God, for thee poore Impe of Hell,</l>
               <l>For ſo thou wert, till I did mercy take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="59">
               <head>59.</head>
               <l>Thus doth the Eternall Father treate his Sonne,</l>
               <l>His only Sonne, who could not ſinne at all;</l>
               <l>And if the Suretyes to ſuch ſtreightes become,</l>
               <l>How wilt thou ſcape who art the Principall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="60">
               <head>60.</head>
               <l>O Penetrate my ſhame, my paynes, my teares,</l>
               <l>My wounded body, my disfigured face,</l>
               <l>My ſoule oppreſt with grieuous cares, and feares,</l>
               <l>Leaſt thou ſhouldſt liue, and dye in Gods diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="61">
               <head>61.</head>
               <l>See how my feet are nayld thus to a tree;</l>
               <l>To ſhew that I will neuer ſtir from thence,</l>
               <l>Till thou mayſt be procurd to pitty me,</l>
               <l>VVho ſeeke to ſaue thee, with my liues expence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="62">
               <head>62.</head>
               <l>My head hangs downe, to offer thee a kiſſe</l>
               <l>Of friendſhip, which ſhall neuer be diſſolud;</l>
               <l>Myne armes are ſpred, that ſo thou mayſt not miſſe,</l>
               <l>By chaines of endles loue to be inuolud.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="63">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:19229:96"/>
               <head>63.</head>
               <l>And that thou mayſt be ſure of what I ſay,</l>
               <l>Nor thinke my wordes can be as vayne as thyne;</l>
               <l>A launce ſhall pierce my ſide, and make a way,</l>
               <l>VVherby thou mayſt diſcerne this hart of myne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="64">
               <head>64.</head>
               <l>If Iuſtice cannot winne thee to preſerue</l>
               <l>From ſinne thy ſoule (that ſparke of fire diuine)</l>
               <l>If no reſpect of gratitude can ſerue,</l>
               <l>To make thee his, who is ſo truly thyne:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="65">
               <head>65.</head>
               <l>At leaſt let Intereſt (whoſe raigne of late</l>
               <l>Extends it ſelfe to all but fooles and Saints,</l>
               <l>Neither of which thou art) make thee change ſtate,</l>
               <l>And ceaſe thy miſeryes, with my complaints,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="66">
               <head>66.</head>
               <l>For what canſt thou, poore wretch, preſume, or hope</l>
               <l>To purchaſe of the world, whoſe ſlaue thou art,</l>
               <l>The world, which is but a plaine Pedlers ſhop,</l>
               <l>Of wares (ſmall wares if meaſured with mans hart.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="67">
               <head>67.</head>
               <l>And what are theſe, but Honour, Pleaſure, Riches,</l>
               <l>VVhich it ſets forth, and cryes, See what you lacke,</l>
               <l>And ſo the eyes of ſimple men betwiches,</l>
               <l>VVho do the Nutſhell, for the keruell take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="68">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:19229:96"/>
               <head>68.</head>
               <l>For whome did Honour euer yet content,</l>
               <l>Moſt kind to them to whome it makes reſiſtance;</l>
               <l>For as for thoſe, to whome it giues conſent,</l>
               <l>It fayles them moſt, when moſt they craue aſſiſtance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="69">
               <head>69.</head>
               <l>Looke vpon them, who by the ſteddy launce</l>
               <l>Of furious death, are thruſt eu'n vnder ground;</l>
               <l>VVhome Honour made in that wild Maze to daunce,</l>
               <l>VVhere is much motion, but no meaſure found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="70">
               <head>70.</head>
               <l>Looke vpon them that liue (if they do liue</l>
               <l>VVho all their life do nothing els but dye)</l>
               <l>Seruing in Courts, and who themſelues do giue</l>
               <l>To care, which ſleepeth in their waking eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="71">
               <head>71.</head>
               <l>For when they hope to reſt on bed of eaſe;</l>
               <l>Their tottering mind conuerts it to a racke,</l>
               <l>VVhich windes, and windes it vp, with ſuch diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>As makes their poore, ambitious hart ſtringes cracke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="72">
               <head>72.</head>
               <l>And iuſtly, ſince it is the forge of plots</l>
               <l>How to take Iuſtice priſoner, and the ſpring</l>
               <l>VVhich iſſues out of poyſoned mouth, and rotts</l>
               <l>Thoſe high reports, which glorious vertues bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="73">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:19229:97"/>
               <head>73.</head>
               <l>Infamous mouth; foule hoſt of that foule gueſt</l>
               <l>A double tongue; a ſword with edges twaine;</l>
               <l>A Raſour and a Saw, for with this beſt</l>
               <l>They put their foes, with that, their friends in payne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="74">
               <head>74.</head>
               <l>And neuer ſpeake their thoughts, but their words all</l>
               <l>Are like falſe thruſts which ſeem not what they meane</l>
               <l>Promiſcuouſly deceauing great and ſmall,</l>
               <l>And moſt themſelues, when leaſt therof they dreame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="75">
               <head>75.</head>
               <l>Next after Honour, Pleaſure comes in play;</l>
               <l>Not that which God by his ſweet law permits,</l>
               <l>But the vnlawfull, which preſumes to ſay,</l>
               <l>I am thy God, not he that in heau'n ſits.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="76">
               <head>76.</head>
               <l>Pleaſure, thou ill deſeruſt true Pleaſures name;</l>
               <l>VVho art of woes the Mother, and the Nurſe;</l>
               <l>Thy Roots are plotted, and contriud in ſhame,</l>
               <l>Thy Flower is ſinne, thy Fruite an endles curſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="77">
               <head>77.</head>
               <l>Due curſe, for thou commitſt Adams offence,</l>
               <l>Adam whoſe ſinne was ſeene, though he was hidden;</l>
               <l>Both guilty are of diſobedience,</l>
               <l>Re taſting fruite, thou touching fleſh forbidden</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="78">
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:19229:97"/>
               <head>78.</head>
               <l>VVhich the old Enemy of all mankind</l>
               <l>Keeps in his ſhambles, ſaying: Stolne fleſh is ſweet;</l>
               <l>Yet t'is not ſtolne but bought, and when men find</l>
               <l>At how high rate, their ſweet meates proue vnſweet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="79">
               <head>79.</head>
               <l>For firſt they looſe their ſoules, that ſubſtance rare</l>
               <l>VVhich Gods wiſe hand knew only how to frame,</l>
               <l>And next their ſeruile bodyes hired are</l>
               <l>For baſe delights, more ſhort then is their name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="80">
               <head>80.</head>
               <l>And thoſe, beſiegd and hedgd about with feares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Impatience, dotage, ſicknes, endles coſt,</l>
               <l>VVith dangers, and ſuſpitious eyes and eares,</l>
               <l>VVith luſt at hand, but wit and iudgment loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="81">
               <head>81.</head>
               <l>Laſtly this kind of man is made a ſlaue,</l>
               <l>The very ſlaue of ſlaues; for all the reſt</l>
               <l>Pay tributs, more or leſſe, of what they haue,</l>
               <l>But this of bloud is bound to pay the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="82">
               <head>82.</head>
               <l>Yet what do endles Riches, do they leaue</l>
               <l>A man in greater liberty of mind</l>
               <l>Then Honour, or then Pleaſure? they deceaue</l>
               <l>Themſelues that trauayle with a guide ſo blind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="83">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:19229:98"/>
               <head>83.</head>
               <l>All is but change of Tyrants, and this laſt</l>
               <l>Perhaps is more imperious then the reſt,</l>
               <l>For Honours rayſe, Pleaſures refreſh thy taſt</l>
               <l>But care of Wealth holds the whole man oppreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="84">
               <head>84.</head>
               <l>Ambitious perſons haue an open hand,</l>
               <l>And carnall men with almes would couer ſinne,</l>
               <l>But greedy mindes are like to Pooles that ſtand</l>
               <l>Where nothing iſſues out, that once gets in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="85">
               <head>85.</head>
               <l>And if they ſeeme their doubtfull ſteps to bend</l>
               <l>To vertues ſacred Temple, you may feare</l>
               <l>It is not loue of God, but hate to ſpend,</l>
               <l>Their harts are abſent, though their face be there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="86">
               <head>86.</head>
               <l>Now if the greateſt plague God ſends be ſinne,</l>
               <l>What ſhallbe ſayd of wealth, which breeds a vice,</l>
               <l>(A doore by which all others enter in)</l>
               <l>Knowne by the odious name of Auarice?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="87">
               <head>87.</head>
               <l>Other ſinnes make men vicious, and prophane;</l>
               <l>Beſides all that, this makes them vile, and baſe;</l>
               <l>Thou art the Anti racke, that doth reſtrayne</l>
               <l>Mans ſpacious mind, to thy penurious place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="88">
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:19229:98"/>
               <head>88.</head>
               <l>For whats thy obiect? Gould, whats gould? faire duſt;</l>
               <l>Who are thy friends? continuall thought, and care;</l>
               <l>Thy Counſailour is generall Miſtruſt,</l>
               <l>Thy foes thou thinkeſt all them, that richer are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="89">
               <head>89.</head>
               <l>Thou art the Miſt that doth benight Mankind,</l>
               <l>Before their tyme thou makſt their heads grow gray,</l>
               <l>Their minds grow black, thou makſt their reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blind,</l>
               <l>In all their life they keep no Holiday.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="90">
               <head>90.</head>
               <l>Thou fillſt them with inſatiable thirſt;</l>
               <l>And when they haue obtaynd abundant ſtore,</l>
               <l>Thou tellſt them they haue leſſe then at the firſt,</l>
               <l>And ſtill doſt preach to them, Get more, Get more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="91">
               <head>91.</head>
               <l>Thou ſtaruſt their bodyes with thy penury,</l>
               <l>Which thou calſt Thrift, thou makſt their ſoules fall ſicke</l>
               <l>Of inward dropſy, and of Lethargy:</l>
               <l>Others do kill, but thou doſt bury quicke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="92">
               <head>92.</head>
               <l>Theſe are the Pageants that do ſtalke about</l>
               <l>The worlds wide ſtreets, and which men follow ſo;</l>
               <l>I call them Men, but yet wiſe men will doubt</l>
               <l>That they are beaſtes, although like men they ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="93">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:19229:99"/>
               <head>93.</head>
               <l>Let muddy headed fiſh be ſo ſurprizd</l>
               <l>VVith ſlippery wormes, that cruell hookes do couer;</l>
               <l>Let ſimple flyes, that ſeeke their death, diſguiſd</l>
               <l>VVith glorious flames, about ſuch candles houer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="94">
               <head>94.</head>
               <l>But thou, O man, who art of heauenly race,</l>
               <l>Haſt power to decipher this dumbe ſhow,</l>
               <l>And take it for no better, then a caſe</l>
               <l>VVhich maſkes the rotten ſtuffe that lyes below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="95">
               <head>95.</head>
               <l>Plucke off this maſke, and thou ſhalt ſee the face</l>
               <l>Of that foule Idol whome thou didſt adore,</l>
               <l>And hate the cauſe of thy ſo great diſgrace,</l>
               <l>VVondring at it, but at thy ſelfe much more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="96">
               <head>96.</head>
               <l>And if thou be deſirous to enioy</l>
               <l>True Honour, Pleaſure, Profit, follow me;</l>
               <l>Ile be thy guide, and teach thee to imploy</l>
               <l>Thy paines on him, whoſe ſeruice makes men free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="97">
               <head>97.</head>
               <l>Recall thy thoughts, which Rauen-like do feed,</l>
               <l>Vpon the Carrion of inferiour thinges,</l>
               <l>And ſend them vp to Heauen, where they ſhall read</l>
               <l>Thy fortune written in the Booke of Kinges.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="98">
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:19229:99"/>
               <head>98.</head>
               <l>Of Kings of Heauen, for God who only is</l>
               <l>The King in his owne right, adopteth thee,</l>
               <l>To raigne with him in euerlaſting bliſſe,</l>
               <l>For all his Sonnes, myne owne coheires ſhallbe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="99">
               <head>99.</head>
               <l>Therefore my bloud vpon this Croſſe is ſould,</l>
               <l>To ſaue thy body, and thy ſoule from Hell;</l>
               <l>Changing thy houſe of clay, to Church of gould,</l>
               <l>VVherin the Holy Ghoſt himſelfe ſhall dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="100">
               <head>100.</head>
               <l>Ordeyning Sacraments, whereby mankind</l>
               <l>May purge offences, and acquire new grace;</l>
               <l>Miſterious Sacraments, which not thy mind,</l>
               <l>Much leſſe thy pen, can paint without diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="101">
               <head>101.</head>
               <l>Bidding his Angells ſerue thee, and vnfould</l>
               <l>The ſecrets of his loue, and Sathans hate;</l>
               <l>Confound thy ſelfe with wonder, to behould</l>
               <l>Such honour added to thy baſe eſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="102">
               <head>102.</head>
               <l>Honour, with Pleaſure: for what earthly ioy</l>
               <l>Doth equall that which a good conſcience giues?</l>
               <l>And doth full fill, whileſt yet it doth not cloy</l>
               <l>The Spirit, and the ſoule wherein it liues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="103">
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:19229:100"/>
               <head>103.</head>
               <l>Not like to worldly pleaſure, that transformes</l>
               <l>It ſelfe to payne through ſad remorſe of mind;</l>
               <l>But in the middſt of fortunes bitter ſtormes,</l>
               <l>A quiet paſſage, and ſafe port doth find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="104">
               <head>104.</head>
               <l>So ſhalt thou ſee that they who take moſt care</l>
               <l>To beare this Croſſe of myne with humble hart,</l>
               <l>To extaſy of ioy tranſported are,</l>
               <l>Their bodyes heere, in heauen their better part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="105">
               <head>105.</head>
               <l>Although they cannot long enioy that glory,</l>
               <l>Till after death, the end of all reſtraintes;</l>
               <l>But then, they ſhall contemplate the whole Story</l>
               <l>Of all Gods Attributes, with all his Saints:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="106">
               <head>106.</head>
               <l>And vnderſtand one God in Perſons three,</l>
               <l>Vniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g that which ſeemes ſo far aſunder;</l>
               <l>Whome eu'n the Angells tremble when they ſee;</l>
               <l>No trembling of baſe feare, but of high wonder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="107">
               <head>107.</head>
               <l>Where God is faine to giue a ſpeciall grace,</l>
               <l>To keep mans ſoule from melting with delight;</l>
               <l>In whoſe compariſon the withered face</l>
               <l>Of worldly thinges, though great, doth vaniſh quite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="108">
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:19229:100"/>
               <head>108.</head>
               <l>Looke vp to Heauens high vaute, conſider right</l>
               <l>The Starres, ſo bigge, though they ſo ſmall appeare;</l>
               <l>The Sunne (except this inſtant) ſwolne with light,</l>
               <l>Yet voyd of heate, although it heate men heere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="109">
               <head>109.</head>
               <l>Looke on the earth, and wonder at her ſeate,</l>
               <l>See how the Sea moates in her fortreſſe faire:</l>
               <l>Which though it be a Maſſe ſo hugely great,</l>
               <l>Hath no foundation but vnſtable ayre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="110">
               <head>110.</head>
               <l>Behold her garments wrought with curious coſt,</l>
               <l>With buſhes purld, with ſtreames of ſiluer laſt;</l>
               <l>With flowres imbrodered, with faire woods emboſt,</l>
               <l>Buttond with hilles, which bind it all ſo faſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="111">
               <head>111.</head>
               <l>This on her backe ſhe weares, but in her wombe</l>
               <l>Rich mettalls are, and Iewells beyond price;</l>
               <l>Which lye inter'd, as in a regall tombe,</l>
               <l>Till men do rayſe them vp, by ſtrang deuiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="112">
               <head>112.</head>
               <l>All this God made, and made man Lord of all;</l>
               <l>And of himſelfe, by giuing him Freewill;</l>
               <l>A Memory, and wit Imperiall,</l>
               <l>An Vnderſtanding both of good and ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="113">
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:19229:101"/>
               <head>113.</head>
               <l>A ſoule that might the ſeate of Vertues be,</l>
               <l>Of Iuſtice, Temperance, Prudence, Strength of mind,</l>
               <l>A hand, which with extreme facility</l>
               <l>Acts that, which is by buiſieſt braynes deſignd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="114">
               <head>114.</head>
               <l>A curious knot of ſenſes, Hearing, Smell,</l>
               <l>Sight, Taſt, and Touch, which men ſo much adore.</l>
               <l>Theſe are but patternes, which may ſerue to tell</l>
               <l>Of richer wares, that God layes vp in ſtore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="115">
               <head>115.</head>
               <l>For if his Foot-ſtoole (and the world is ſuch)</l>
               <l>Be ſo inricht, what is his Princely throne?</l>
               <l>And if mans miſeryes do ſhine ſo much,</l>
               <l>VVhat ſhall his glory do? God knowes alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="116">
               <head>116.</head>
               <l>And man may ſay no more therof but this,</l>
               <l>That when he hath deuiſd the moſt he can,</l>
               <l>The world to come, as far excelling is,</l>
               <l>As God immortall doth exceed frayle man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="117">
               <head>117.</head>
               <l>But thou, though fraile be not ſo fondly bent</l>
               <l>As to deſtroy thy ſoule, to flatter ſenſe,</l>
               <l>And ſell a Crowne of glory permanent,</l>
               <l>For traſh, which yet thou canſt not carry hence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="118">
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:19229:101"/>
               <head>118.</head>
               <l>For heere all dyes with thee, thy ſinnes excepted,</l>
               <l>And (that which followes ſinne) eternall paines;</l>
               <l>For hauing ſo prepoſterouſly neglected</l>
               <l>A Sunne ſo full, to chooſe a Moone that wanes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="119">
               <head>119.</head>
               <l>How much more noble were it, ſince thou art</l>
               <l>Compoſd of Beaſt and Angell, to procure</l>
               <l>Thy fleſh, to do her homage to that part,</l>
               <l>Which is ſuperiour, incorrupt and pure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="120">
               <head>120.</head>
               <l>So ſhalt thou grow like God thy heauenly Father;</l>
               <l>And ſuffering heere with me, with me ſhalt raigne,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt receaue the Holy Ghoſt, or rather</l>
               <l>Be fild top full, with ſhowres of his ſweet raine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="121">
               <head>121.</head>
               <l>That ſpotles Virgin will behould thy ſtate,</l>
               <l>As tender Mother doth her deereſt Sonne,</l>
               <l>The Angell that attends thee, will relate.</l>
               <l>The glorious courſe that thou beginſt to runne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="122">
               <head>122.</head>
               <l>Thou ſhalt be bidden to a dayly feaſt</l>
               <l>By thy good Conſcience, which all plenty bringes.</l>
               <l>And thy faire ſoule, from ſinnefull fleſh releaſt,</l>
               <l>Shall mount to Heauen vpon bright Angells winges.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="123">
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:19229:102"/>
               <head>123.</head>
               <l>This not for need that I inuite thee ſo,</l>
               <l>For know my glory will as brightly ſhine</l>
               <l>In thy damnation to eternall woe,</l>
               <l>As in the ſauing of that ſoule of thyne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="124">
               <head>124.</head>
               <l>My loue alone did force me to deſcend</l>
               <l>Into this Nothing, Loue the loadſtone is</l>
               <l>Which makes the iron rod of Iuſtice bend</l>
               <l>To mercy, pardoning all thou doſt amiſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="125">
               <head>125.</head>
               <l>And ſo I aske no retribution</l>
               <l>But only Loue, and if thou graunt not this,</l>
               <l>Tigers may teach thee more compaſſion,</l>
               <l>And ſoftnes flint, for thy hart harder is.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="126">
               <head>126.</head>
               <l>Such ſpeach thou wouldſt, nay ſuch thou didſt impart,</l>
               <l>Not to mine eares (for then thou wert growne domme</l>
               <l>And I was deafe) but to my ſinnefull hart,</l>
               <l>Then take this anſwere which from thence doth come.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="127">
               <head>127.</head>
               <l>Deare Lord, I graunt that thou all reaſon haſt,</l>
               <l>And I ſhould rage in Hell, who thus neglect</l>
               <l>Of thy ſtill preſent loue, the pledges paſt,</l>
               <l>To which my ſoule doth owe ſupreme reſpect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="128">
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:19229:102"/>
               <head>128.</head>
               <l>Wretch that I am, I want not grace to know</l>
               <l>The endles obligation I am in,</l>
               <l>The little that I pay, the much I owe</l>
               <l>To thy deare Paſſion, that huge price of ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="129">
               <head>129.</head>
               <l>But all this knowledge of what I ſhould do,</l>
               <l>Detects me of vnkindnes ſo much more,</l>
               <l>Becauſe myne actions do not ſute therto,</l>
               <l>Which are as cold, and careles as before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="130">
               <head>130.</head>
               <l>My taſt, my touch, my ſmell, myne eares, myne eyes,</l>
               <l>I graunt were giuen for ſcouts, who might fetch home</l>
               <l>A ladder, by the which my ſoule ſhould riſe</l>
               <l>From creatures, to the loue of thee alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="131">
               <head>131.</head>
               <l>The facultyes, and powers of my Mind,</l>
               <l>Myne Vnderſtanding, Will, and Memory,</l>
               <l>I graunt, were lent as lockes and keyes, to bind</l>
               <l>My hart to know, and loue, and thinke on thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="132">
               <head>132.</head>
               <l>All theſe thy mercyes, and a million more</l>
               <l>I haue miſpent, and with the ſelfe ſame armes</l>
               <l>Which thou hadſt willed me to keep in ſtore</l>
               <l>For my defence, I did my ſoule moſt harmes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="133">
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:19229:103"/>
               <head>133.</head>
               <l>So that they are not my foule ſinnes alone,</l>
               <l>Which ſtrike me with a ſad remorſe of mind;</l>
               <l>But eu'n thy mercyes, to ſuch height are growne,</l>
               <l>As that in them more cauſe of feare I find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="134">
               <head>134.</head>
               <l>For how can I, to whome thou giu'ſt ſuch grace,</l>
               <l>As would haue ſerud to make ſome men great Saints,</l>
               <l>Aduenture to appeare before thy face,</l>
               <l>In whome thou findſt no cauſe but of complaints.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="135">
               <head>135.</head>
               <l>From hence it is deare Lord, that I decline</l>
               <l>That ſeate of Iuſtice, and that royall Throne</l>
               <l>Where pureſt Angells, who moſt brightly ſhine,</l>
               <l>Do looſe their luſtre, when by thyne t'is ſhowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="156">
               <head>156.</head>
               <l>From hence it is, that I am trembling ſtill,</l>
               <l>VVhen I conſider that dread Maieſty,</l>
               <l>That light inacceſſible, which doth kill</l>
               <l>All ſoules, wherein it findes impiety.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="137">
               <head>137.</head>
               <l>From hence it is, that I did beg of thee,</l>
               <l>Not only that thou wouldſt thy ſelfe impart,</l>
               <l>But that it might in ſuch a faſhion be,</l>
               <l>As ſhould engraue thy Paſſion in my hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="138">
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:19229:103"/>
               <head>138.</head>
               <l>For on the Croſſe, thou art all ſweet, and ſoft,</l>
               <l>And poore, and humble, and ſurchargd with payne,</l>
               <l>For my vngratefull ſoule, which hath ſo oft</l>
               <l>Renewed thy wounds, and made them bleed againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="139">
               <head>139.</head>
               <l>O thou faire fountaine with fiue ſprings of loue,</l>
               <l>VVhich make ſuch ſtreames as that by running ſtill,</l>
               <l>They grow to be a Sea, which flowes aboue</l>
               <l>The bancks of all, that hath the name of Ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="140">
               <head>140.</head>
               <l>Not only quenching the hoat flames of Hell,</l>
               <l>(Though vulgar men conceaue that this is all)</l>
               <l>But ſanctifying wicked men ſo well,</l>
               <l>As makes them lead a life Angelicall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="141">
               <head>141.</head>
               <l>Lend me one grayne of that deare Loue of thyne,</l>
               <l>Which, by protection, may tranſmute me ſo</l>
               <l>From Lead to Gould, as that theſe debts of myne</l>
               <l>May both be payd, and I more rich may grow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="142">
               <head>142.</head>
               <l>Or rather I preſume to beg of thee,</l>
               <l>Not that ſo much my Loue may be increaſt,</l>
               <l>As that the obiect may quite changed be,</l>
               <l>And I loue moſt, what I haue yet lou'd leaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="143">
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:19229:104"/>
               <head>143.</head>
               <l>For there was euer planted in my hart</l>
               <l>Great power to loue, and happy had I beene,</l>
               <l>If only I had well applyed that part,</l>
               <l>To ſerue my God, inſteed of ſeruing ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="144">
               <head>144.</head>
               <l>Nay happy ſhould I be, if from this hower</l>
               <l>My loue were all diuorſt from humane thinges,</l>
               <l>And ſo eſpouſd to thee, as to want power</l>
               <l>Of ſeeking ought, but what thy ſeruice bringes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="145">
               <head>145.</head>
               <l>How ſoone wouldſt thou forget my follyes paſt:</l>
               <l>Thy Grammar which muſt conſter the expenſe</l>
               <l>Of all myne howres incongruouſly plaſt,</l>
               <l>Hath Futures, but no Preter perfect tenſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="146">
               <head>146.</head>
               <l>Heere then receaue all that doth yet remayne,</l>
               <l>I take thy word, which once thou gau'ſt to me,</l>
               <l>That thou wouldſt draw all ſoules to thee againe,</l>
               <l>When, on the Croſſe, thou ſhouldſt exalted be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="147">
               <head>147.</head>
               <l>Draw me, but draw me home, for els my hart</l>
               <l>Which is ſo ſlippery, and ſo heauy growne,</l>
               <l>Either by fraud, or els by force will ſtart</l>
               <l>From ſuch coniunction, as ſhould make vs one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="148">
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:19229:104"/>
               <head>148.</head>
               <l>Speake to my ſoule, but with ſo loud a voyce</l>
               <l>As I may heare; and in a tune ſo ſweet,</l>
               <l>That, deafe to other thinges, I may reioyce</l>
               <l>To tread the happy ſteps of thy pure feet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="149">
               <head>149.</head>
               <l>Turne backe ſometyme, and breath vpon me ſo</l>
               <l>That with delight I may aduance my pace;</l>
               <l>And not remembring how to creep, and go,</l>
               <l>May runne, and reach theſe odours of thy grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="150">
               <head>150.</head>
               <l>I aſke not that I may be worldly wiſe</l>
               <l>Nor learned, ſtrong, nor rich, nor much eſteemd,</l>
               <l>Such traſh as this I hope I ſhall deſpiſe</l>
               <l>Who am from all erroneous fayth redeemd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="151">
               <head>151.</head>
               <l>I aske not to be free from anxious thought</l>
               <l>Of ſuddaine death, or dropping downe to Hell:</l>
               <l>The matchleſſe price, wherewith my ſoule was bought</l>
               <l>Perſwades me that thou loueſt it much too well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="152">
               <head>152.</head>
               <l>I aske not that thou wouldſt theſe fetters looſe,</l>
               <l>Which do my ſoule from heauenly bliſſe detayne:</l>
               <l>For t'is more noble, and I rather chooſe</l>
               <l>To ſuffer for thee, then with thee to raigne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="153">
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:19229:105"/>
               <head>153.</head>
               <l>But let me only by thy hand be bleſt;</l>
               <l>Lend me one caſt of thy propitious eye,</l>
               <l>Inflame me with deſires to do the beſt;</l>
               <l>For good is naught, when better doth ſtand by.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="154">
               <head>154.</head>
               <l>O that I could conſider, as I know,</l>
               <l>The little which thy Law of me requires,</l>
               <l>The much that to thy ardent Loue I owe,</l>
               <l>And yet I freeze enuirond by ſuch fires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="155">
               <head>155.</head>
               <l>Thou bidſt me loue thee, and I beg the ſame;</l>
               <l>How come I then to miſſe what I intend?</l>
               <l>T'is, that I aske it of thee, but for ſhame,</l>
               <l>And no ſtrong purpoſe that I haue to mend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="156">
               <head>156.</head>
               <l>For loue conſiſteth not in words, but workes;</l>
               <l>Not in velleities, but conſtant will,</l>
               <l>To roote out paſſion (which ſo falſely lurkes)</l>
               <l>And make ſtiffe warre againſt all ſhew of ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="157">
               <head>157.</head>
               <l>Heerein I fayle, and do not only craue</l>
               <l>Strength for the tyme to come, but humbly ſue</l>
               <l>For pardon of ſinnes paſt; the more I haue,</l>
               <l>The greater prayſe is to thy mercy due.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="158">
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:19229:105"/>
               <head>158.</head>
               <l>Let not thy ſword of Iuſtice take my head;</l>
               <l>Let not my wretched hart be ſtond to death;</l>
               <l>Let not thy wheele of vengeance, which lyes ſpread</l>
               <l>Againſt all ſinners, take my dying breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="159">
               <head>159.</head>
               <l>But, if I may not liue, and pleaſe thee ſtill,</l>
               <l>Rather let fire of Loue conſume me quite;</l>
               <l>Or let teares drowne me, if it be thy will,</l>
               <l>Or endles ſighing breake my hart outright.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="160">
               <head>160.</head>
               <l>And for my tombe, I neither will aske more,</l>
               <l>Nor care for leſſe, then thoſe deare armes of thyne;</l>
               <l>VVhich haue ſuch vertue, as to keep in ſtore</l>
               <l>All that they touch, free from the wracke of tyme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="161">
               <head>161.</head>
               <l>Let others ſeeke for life, and liberty,</l>
               <l>And in that courſe eternized to be;</l>
               <l>The higheſt thoughts of my ambition, flye</l>
               <l>But to be dead, and buried thus in thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
